<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-22T16:49:29-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jay Riverlong</title><subtitle>Jay Riverlong's personal website. Essays and thoughts.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Spiteful Investor (or There Are Always Idiots at the Cutting Edge)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/20/investor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Spiteful Investor (or There Are Always Idiots at the Cutting Edge)" /><published>2020-11-20T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/20/investor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/20/investor.html">&lt;p&gt;I like to think I’m a pretty rational investor. Not too emotional,
not too prone to FOMO, willing to wait for good deals.
So, let me tell you about a bad and embarrassing decision I made.
This story may seem pretty dumb to you, as it does to me today.
I often read about great financial disasters and think
“that’s so stupid! I would never screw up this badly.”
It turns out that’s easier said than done;
some theoretical lessons are very hard to internalize in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late 2014, I was cautiously bullish on Bitcoin. I saw the appeal
of finite-supply assets in other markets, leaned cypherpunk-libertarian,
and had run into many issues with fiat payment processors in my poker days.
However, I had also seen Liberty Reserve shut down by the FBI,
watched quaint early scams like Auroracoin,
and thought it seemed clear that the government would eventually need to
shut down this state-threatening Wild West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was bullish, but hesitant to put real skin in the game.
Along came an opportunity to bet on Bitcoin with
no personal downside: I met a young founder who had just raised $2M
from a few investors for the purpose of getting them Bitcoin exposure.
Let’s call him Mephisto.
He had negotiated 25% carry on the profits of his small fund, which was an excellent deal.
His track record made sense:
he’d been in the industry since 2012, and had made some good money
on Bitcoin and trading FPGAs.
He had brought on a young woman – let’s call her Bellatrix –
to help manage operations.
As we talked, we realized I could help them generate alpha beyond
pure Bitcoin exposure. I knew financial derivatives very well, so
my task was broadly to profit off inefficiencies in these nascent markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was 23.
Working with Mephisto and Bellatrix was like sitting on the Hindenburg.
While I was combing the market for inefficiencies, they were
struggling to get the operations fully set up.
A few weeks in, it turned out
that Mephisto and Bellatrix had been fucking in secret.
They had an equity dispute.
He went off his medication, and
suffered a psychotic breakdown.
She accused him of rape.
They called the cops on each other.
He disappeared and re-encountered the substance abuse problem
that had put him on anti-psychotic medication in the first place.
To top it all off, they lost the cold storage credentials for a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled the escape cord and resigned cleanly.
Ironically, I took a financial loss here,
since I had to have my lawyers review everything and
ensure I wasn’t liable for any fiduciary mismanagement
these two chaos clowns might undertake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point it was early 2015. Bitcoin hovered between $200 and $250 per coin.
I was totally over it. The cautiously bullish view I had gotten around to
was eviscerated by my distaste for the Mephisto episode.
I was exasperated,
liquidated nearly my entire position and sat, for a long time,
more in the bear camp than not.
Thinking about Mephisto and Bellatrix,
I said to myself, if &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; is who is managing money in Bitcoin,
there’s no hope for the sector.
Bearish on Bitcoin at a $3B market cap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of my attitude was a spiteful emotional hedge.
I think my reasoning went like this:
investing in Bitcoin could go two ways.
I could lose money, and I would be disappointed.
I could also make money,
but in that case, Mephisto and his ilk would make wildly &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; money, and
I would be upset.
If I were to invest and succeed holding the same position as Mephisto,
I’d be envious of someone I despised.
I wanted Mephisto to fail, so I wanted Bitcoin to fail.
It’s a twisted rationalization – silly in retrospect, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d bet that the big-name no-coiners like Nouriel Roubini, Peter Schiff,
and David Girard have the same kind of emotional hedge.
They’ve been calling Bitcoin snake oil for years.
Knowing that you’ve been wrong all along and that all your opponents
have become millionaires would be devastating.
They’re stuck now: if they were ever to become bullish, they would
be tormented by their past decisions.
So they remain permabears, fingers in their ears,
calling it a scam and &lt;em&gt;praying&lt;/em&gt; it’ll eventually go to zero, even while the
number keeps going up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to be a rational investor when the seas are calm.
It’s hard when it gets emotional.
Importantly,
everyone
has a threshold – if the personal relationships are close enough,
or if the stress is great enough, suddenly even the most rational actors
crack. I saw it all the time playing poker: your opponents
are stone-faced rational actors until something gets to them. They’re tired or
distracted, and suddenly they get pissed off when they normally wouldn’t,
and make bets they shouldn’t. Very few people manage to stay rational
in charged moments. The better-disciplined folks will
summon all their willpower just to walk away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this episode, I let emotional stress override my assessment of the market.
Stupidly, I let my subjective, one-off personal experience bias me against
an entire industry. Stress had me do a 180 on a carefully considered position
of conviction. Refusing to take a position out of spite, or in order to pre-empt envy
in the case of success, is even more embarrassing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there was one other important thing I hadn’t considered or realized at the time:
the cutting edge is always full of idiots.
It’s a common trope that people who are all-in on frontier tech are usually somewhat crazy.
We have a romantic
view of folks on the frontier – eccentric geniuses – but much of the time
it’s gullible bozos and scammers feeding off them.
In a historical analogy, the Wild West does not just create outlaws, it
necessarily attracts them.
My mistake here was to let the worst people
color my representation of the market.
It doesn’t matter how many scammers
and con-men there are, it matters how many people are building stable infrastructure.
It doesn’t matter how many ways there are for it to fail, it only matters
that there’s one plausible way to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I like to think I’m a pretty rational investor. Not too emotional, not too prone to FOMO, willing to wait for good deals. So, let me tell you about a bad and embarrassing decision I made. This story may seem pretty dumb to you, as it does to me today. I often read about great financial disasters and think “that’s so stupid! I would never screw up this badly.” It turns out that’s easier said than done; some theoretical lessons are very hard to internalize in practice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two Life Lessons from A Series of Unfortunate Events</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/snicket.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two Life Lessons from A Series of Unfortunate Events" /><published>2020-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/snicket</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/snicket.html">&lt;p&gt;Important lessons often take a long time to gestate.
I didn’t really understand linear algebra until five years after
I first took it – like in many other fields,
I had to climb far up the tower to appreciate the foundations.
Getting Plato’s &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; took me ten years of fleeting thoughts.
Even for movies, forming an opinion sometimes takes me months of rumination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently been thinking about my
favorite childhood book series, &lt;em&gt;A Series of Unfortunate Events&lt;/em&gt;.
It seems that it took me nearly fifteen years to understand two of its core lessons.
ASOUE is a thirteen-novel Victorian-Gothic black comedy series
about three orphans and the uncle trying to steal their inheritance.
While the first few novels formulaically
follow this premise, the later novels uncover a set of deep conspiracies
surrounding their deceased parents and thieving adversaries.
As the universe of the story becomes more complex,
we realize that it’s not a simple tale of good and evil,
and the actions of the protagonists become steeped in moral ambiguity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was fifteen years old when I read the thirteenth and final novel, &lt;em&gt;The End&lt;/em&gt;.
To my endless disappointment, it concluded with nothing.
As far as I was
concerned,
every major question remained open.
Even trivially answerable questions, like about the contents of a particular plot MacGuffin,
were left cloaked in eternal silence.
If anything, the novel added &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; questions.
To a young completionist, this was awfully frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I grew older, my obsessive need for closure waned.
As I became busier, I stopped caring about tying up every end.
I learned that most people don’t care as much about literal
definitions as I do, and that most efforts are not completed but abandoned.
In that context, &lt;em&gt;The End&lt;/em&gt; made its final lesson a meaningful, if unpleasant one:
&lt;strong&gt;most ends are left frayed&lt;/strong&gt;.
The world branches forward unpredictably,
with unlucky branches dying off – no catharsis,
no punctuation, but sparks fizzling out and attentions shifting.
Reflecting on the story as an adult, it was the perfect ending to a series
about great mysteries and deep ambiguities: most of them stay unresolved forever.
And that’s all right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other important lesson I took away was one about conflict.
The core mysteries of ASOUE concern a metaphorical &lt;em&gt;Volunteer Fire Department&lt;/em&gt;
that had split into
two sides: one starts fires, the other puts them out.
Of course, this is enormously contrived. The two organizations are in
a symbiotic, but completely pointless relationship: they exist only to nullify
each others’ actions. Further, while the two sides are at first presented as morally black-and-white,
the reader learns that each side is a bit of a mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an adult, the yin-yang fire departments sound familiar.
I’ve learned that in order to give themselves purpose in life,
&lt;strong&gt;people play games&lt;/strong&gt;.
In a world where we are mostly safe from real war and disease,
we instigate new conflicts
to keep us busy and to satisfy our primal needs to compete and do battle.
If we have nothing to fight for,
we create it. Fukuyama &lt;a href=&quot;https://unherd.com/2020/09/why-fukuyama-was-right-all-along/&quot;&gt;realized this&lt;/a&gt;, and the danger it poses
to our society.
And once you realize that most conflicts are not well-reasoned,
good-faith differences of opinion but rather arbitrary symbolic battle,
then they all wind up looking just as unnecessary and ambiguous as the two volunteer fire departments.
Every dispute is sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, I’ve kept coming back to these two
core points of &lt;em&gt;A Series of Unfortunate Events&lt;/em&gt;,
which went way over my teenage head when
I first read them. Now, nearly fifteen years later, not only do they make more sense,
but they hold up a mirror to deep truths that I’ve encountered as I’ve
learned more about the world. This is the mark of good fiction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Important lessons often take a long time to gestate. I didn’t really understand linear algebra until five years after I first took it – like in many other fields, I had to climb far up the tower to appreciate the foundations. Getting Plato’s Republic took me ten years of fleeting thoughts. Even for movies, forming an opinion sometimes takes me months of rumination.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two Paradigms of Personal Computing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/27/machines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two Paradigms of Personal Computing" /><published>2020-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/27/machines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/27/machines.html">&lt;p&gt;A frequently recurring staple of Hacker News is the &lt;em&gt;personal computing rant&lt;/em&gt;:
modern computers are black boxes, far too locked down.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
We long for our desktop computers, the early-2000s computing paradigm,
and we want to take back control of our data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sympathize greatly with this view.
For the past five years, I have exclusively run Arch Linux.
I love the early-2000s style of personal computing: text-heavy interfaces,
words rather than icons, uniform keyboard shortcuts everywhere.
I do nearly all my computing in emacs.
It is feature rich, and no product manager is ever going to change the experience, interface, or shortcuts.
My workspace allows me to be &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;.
Contrary to much modern software, emacs responds instantaneously to my keystrokes.
Every action has an immediate effect, clear on the page, with no background process ambiguity.
This is enormously satisfying.
I would characterize this computing environment as a
spiritual descendant of the typewriter:
on its own, it is a dumb machine, but when you command it, it becomes a powerful
extension of you.
The user experience is given by speed, smoothness, reliability, and nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, you’ve got iPhones and iPads.
These are not machines that you command – on the contrary, you might argue
that all their notifications command you. With touch interfaces,
facial recognition, and
voice control, these are machines that are meant to merge with you.
Instead of becoming an &lt;em&gt;extension&lt;/em&gt; of you, it becomes &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of you.
Instead of you commanding it, it is meant to anticipate your commands.
Where is the data? How does it work? Who knows. They’re total black boxes,
effectively indistinguishable from magic, whereas your Linux Desktop is a
DIYable simple machine.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many contemporary writers think of personal computing as
one paradigm that is gradually evolving. I disagree: I think there are two,
deeply different paradigms of personal computing, reflecting deeply different desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Machine as extension of the self (your Windows XP Desktop).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Machine as part of the self (your iPhone).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plenty of devices exist in the space in-between. Android phones
try to give you some control back over your device, by which they necessarily
preclude themselves from truly being &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of you. Modern versions of OS X,
with the touchbar, Siri, and integrations into all your other Apple devices, are
starting to make the leap from extending the self to being part of the self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a genre, the personal computing rant comes out of the correct view that
these are all forms of personal computing, but it fails to recognize that
within this broad umbrella, we’ve seen paradigms arise that differ in both
intent and the human desire they’re meant to meet.
It’s not that one
class of devices is replacing the other.
They are fundamentally different, and one paradigm succeeds where the other
falls short of meeting the consumers’ needs.
The terminal never met the needs of those who want Amazon Alexa, and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live in the in-between. I happily imagine a world where my Apple Watch
monitors my glucose and blood oxygen, my Eight Sleep quantifies my rest,
I mark up documents on giant touchscreens, but I sit on a clacky
IBM keyboard to write code and blog posts in a terminal that hasn’t changed
in twenty years. While your iPhone might meld with your mind by quantifying
and anticipating your every need, my terminal melds with my mind by
being fast, constant, and &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; correct. Each has its place, and I would
never trade one for the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This essay was inspired by a recent hit on Hacker News,
in which the &lt;a href=&quot;http://misc-stuff.terraaeon.com/articles/locked-down-computers.html&quot;&gt;Author is Seriously Considering Going Back to Desktop Computers&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To me, a Linux desktop is almost more like a typewriter than it is like an iPhone.
I can peek inside and understand how most of the tech works.
I can debug it, swap out components, and so on.
It’s like a mechanism of levers and cogs: complicated, perhaps, but understandable
and possible to reason deeply about. An iPhone is inaccessible in all these
respects; it might as well be a magic wand. That’s not necessarily a bad thing,
these are just very different classes of object. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A frequently recurring staple of Hacker News is the personal computing rant: modern computers are black boxes, far too locked down.1 We long for our desktop computers, the early-2000s computing paradigm, and we want to take back control of our data. This essay was inspired by a recent hit on Hacker News, &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No More Bold Visions of the Future</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/24/future.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No More Bold Visions of the Future" /><published>2020-10-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/24/future</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/24/future.html">&lt;p&gt;What do I want the future to be like?
What amazing inventions do I want to see, and help build in my lifetime?
I realized this morning that I don’t know.
I was shocked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been tinkering with technology since I was a child,
and I’ve been
investing in early-stage companies for the past five years.
More than sixty bets on the future.
I’m meant to have bold visions of a better world,
theses I support,
and capital that I allocate in a technologically optimistic way.
I began investing
in startups because I wanted to help shape the future.
And while I still get excited
talking to founders with bold ideas, I have none of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a teen, growing up on a diet of
Carl Sagan’s Cosmos and Alvin Toffler’s
Futurism, I had plenty of big ideas:
spaceflight, supersonic travel, mag-lev trains,
geodesic domes,
bio-nanotech for longevity, and social organization to provide maximum freedom for all.
Cheesy, but optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I am 29 and I have no big, optimistic ideas.
I think of plenty of arbitrages and improvements in efficiency.
And while I believe that better infrastructure
enables more construction and innovation, closing an obscure
pricing gap just isn’t like dreams of great adventure and
exploration on the frontier of human experience and possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend much time thinking about solutions to existing problems – the
incentive mismatch in mass media that is causing accelerating polarization,
how to remedy the effects of climate change, and so on.
But these are all &lt;em&gt;fixes&lt;/em&gt;, reactions.
It feels like I’m in the belly of the ship, frenetically plugging leaky holes, never
even having the space of mind to think &lt;em&gt;where the ship should go&lt;/em&gt;.
Ostensibly, those decisions are made on the bridge of the ship,
which, in October 2020, seems to be populated by well-intentioned individuals,
but hamstrung in their ability to make good collective decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent years have shown me how difficult it is to make &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; meaningful
public decision.
Every debate is endlessly contentious,
every subject has meaningful nuance,
and every decision has exceedingly hard-to-predict second-order-effects.
The world is much more complex than it was even twenty years ago,
and
the effects are paralyzing.
This is clearly felt among policymakers,
but I feel it even as a technologist:
I understand that virtually all tools
can be used – and more often than not, &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be used – for both good and evil,
and how hard the results are to predict over years in our dynamic world.
I learned that technology can rarely solve fundamental social problems, and
I’ve
seen the public perception rollercoaster of “this technology/person/policy is good” to “this is evil”
more times than I can count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This puts me in a real bind for having high-conviction views that aren’t microscopically focused.
As an example, for the past few years I have struggled developing a long-term view on bitcoin.
By network effect, I think it is clear that in the long term, we will have &lt;em&gt;either&lt;/em&gt;
fiat or crypto – either fully centralized or fully decentralized – not both.
Which world do I want to live in? I’m not sure.
On the one hand, it is clear that our existing
US financial system is fragile with systemic risk, a playball exposed to potentially irresponsible
governance.
You might call its mechanics unfair to the masses, but you’d also
need to point out that it has &lt;em&gt;actually worked&lt;/em&gt; in creating prosperity
over the past 110 years.
(And, comparing the US to other countries, it has
worked remarkably well!)
I agree with need for overhaul of the
system, but I’m not sure if it’s wise throw out the entire thing
and open up the world’s largest
power vacuum in the process. This rarely ends well.
I cannot tell, with intellectual honesty, which avenue is best
to pursue. I doubt that anyone does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other arenas of big problems and changes yield similar dilemmas.
Perhaps consequently, I have found myself not dreaming big anymore.
I dream small, where the effects
are predictable.
On dreaming big, there is the paralysis of responsibility and effects,
but there is also a level of cynicism that has
come to me over the years, as big dreams turn out to be much more fraught and
complicated as they move into reality.
The nuance, complexity, difficulty, responsibility, and often &lt;em&gt;irreversibility&lt;/em&gt;
in effecting big changes
has slowly removed the stars from my eyes as I look at technology.
Maybe that’s a good thing as I come to appreciate the gravity of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the same time,
if we don’t take big, bold, bets, we’ll be forever stuck in the valleys of local optima.
As Bezos says, the size of your risk-taking should increase with the size of your
enterprise – at scale, we should be taking many daring gambles, all the time.
But it doesn’t feel like that’s really happening.
It feels like we spend lots of effort debating marginal nuance,
sitting in the belly of the ship doing maintenance, rather than charting the course forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to be an optimist in 2020.
I admire the few&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that still have the courage to dream big and to remind ourselves
that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a future that could be amazing and that is worth fighting for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This article in particular was inspired by Blake Scholl and Boom’s
stalwart efforts to return us to an era of supersonic flight, and
Founders Fund’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/foundersfund/status/1313151184287477767?s=20&quot;&gt;opening notes&lt;/a&gt; to their annual meeting. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What do I want the future to be like? What amazing inventions do I want to see, and help build in my lifetime? I realized this morning that I don’t know. I was shocked.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Influencers as Tech Founders: Real Monetization at Last</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/17/influencer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Influencers as Tech Founders: Real Monetization at Last" /><published>2020-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/17/influencer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/17/influencer.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Dobrik&quot;&gt;David Dobrik&lt;/a&gt;,
a YouTube star with 26 million followers, is launching a social media app
called &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/dispo-live-in-the-moment/id1491684197&quot;&gt;Dispo&lt;/a&gt;.
There’s a good chance it turns him into a billionaire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dobrik is wealthy already. His monthly YouTube check is around
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.menshealth.com/entertainment/a29798708/david-dobrik-salary/&quot;&gt;$275k&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
and he probably makes a little more from his merchandise sales.
After a seven-year career becoming one of the most famous YouTubers, he’s probably
worth around $30 million. However, if he succeeds with Dispo, his earnings-to-date would
pale in comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dispo is a compelling product, and there’s a good chance it will be very successful, for two reasons.
First, Dobrik is outrageously popular with an everyman appeal and a
loyal following in a highly valuable
demographic.
Second, Dobrik’s reach is &lt;em&gt;enormous&lt;/em&gt;. By himself, he has 26 million
subscribers on YouTube, 23 million on TikTok, and 14 million on Instagram.
The rest of his entourage have millions more. Dobrik himself
has accumulated 8.5 &lt;em&gt;billion&lt;/em&gt; YouTube views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With only light marketing, Dobrik has gotten a million downloads for Dispo already.
If he starts seriously pushing Dispo,
he will easily get millions more.
Normally, the biggest hurdle for consumer software/social media apps is solving
the initial chicken-and-egg problem: how do you get people to sign up if no-one else
is on it? Dobrik bulldozes this problem. He is a one-man network effect.
While other companies spend
years slowly growing by word-of-mouth and spending millions of dollars on marketing,
Dobrik eclipses them from day one: he
gets his first million users by just telling his followers to download his cool new app.
While traditional brands
might balk at forking over tens of millions of dollars in cash
to influencer advertising campaigns of hard-to-assess effectiveness,
for Dobrik, this is free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to overstate how important this is. Lots of great products die because
they can’t get early-stage consumer traction, sometimes for no reason other than bad luck.
Dobrik can catapult a product
into the growth stage. He creates what normally takes &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt; of brand development instantly with zero cost.
Normally, an early-stage consumer product
in a highly competitive space like social media will pay about $10-30 in customer
acquisition costs (CAC) to register a single new user.
Dobrik’s following gifts him
the equivalent of tens of millions of dollars in CAC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumer software presents an elegant solution to an age-old problem: influencers
(more traditionally, celebrities) have millions of people watching their every move, but often struggle to
monetize all these eyeballs, even though attention is arguably the most valuable
scarce resource in our internet economy.
Historically, these people have sold
merchandise, been paid for appearances, done book deals, acted in movies/TV, endorsed products,
and sometimes even put out music albums.
These things all make money, but
relative to the value of their brand and the attention it gets,
these monetization techniques are earning pennies on the dollar. These are
five- and six-figure deals when their full CAC potential is worth hundreds of millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Dobrik succeeds, it will change the influencer monetization game.
While top-tier
influencers previously made single-digit millions of dollars, commercial success
for Dispo could be worth hundreds of millions, if not more.
If Dispo just raises a Series A or Series B, Dobrik’s share in Dispo (at least on paper) would
be more valuable than his current net worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless if Dobrik succeeds in this way, some influencer
will, sooner or later.
Consumer tech has been moving
steadily from San Francisco to Los Angeles over the past few years – virtually
all the cool new consumer companies are out of LA – and it’s only a matter of time
until the tech and influencer worlds intertwine more in this way.
For a start, TikTok influencers
at the Sway House are starting
to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibtimes.com/tiktok-influencers-sway-boys-turn-angel-investors-just-trying-make-smart-investments-3051715&quot;&gt;angel invest&lt;/a&gt;
into consumer social companies, and use their followings to help grow those businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intertwining seems inevitable. The entrepreneurial spirit is already there.
Emma Chamberlain (10 million YouTube followers) started a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.refinery29.com/en-us/2020/09/10042481/emma-chamberlain-coffee-merch-brand-interview&quot;&gt;coffee company&lt;/a&gt;.
Bryce Hall and Josh Richards (combined 36 million TikTok Followers) started
an &lt;a href=&quot;https://dankanator.com/74391/josh-richards-bryce-hall-launching-ani-energy-drink/&quot;&gt;energy drink company&lt;/a&gt;.
The only issue is that
merch or beverage companies have low upside and command low multiples, compared to software.
By opportunity cost, it’s not the best use of these influencers’ brands.
It’s only a matter of time until they start co-founding businesses in the
high multiple, high-upside consumer software space.
In the past, consumer tech made influencers. Soon, influencers will make consumer tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dobrik commented that he had some advertising issues
that shrunk his earnings on some of his videos by 99%, but I suspect this
was a temporary issue. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">David Dobrik, a YouTube star with 26 million followers, is launching a social media app called Dispo. There’s a good chance it turns him into a billionaire.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stripe Atlas: the Key to a $100B+ Company</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/10/atlas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stripe Atlas: the Key to a $100B+ Company" /><published>2020-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/10/atlas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/10/atlas.html">&lt;p&gt;Stripe is a well-known innovator in digital payments.
They attacked one of the most intimidating and locked-down markets,
and made it look like child’s play.
They have a compounding competitive edge
in processing payments more efficiently for their customers,
and the best-crafted
APIs in the entire industry.
Stripe is admired on these grounds, and more:
they have their own &lt;a href=&quot;https://press.stripe.com/&quot;&gt;press&lt;/a&gt;,
in line with their thoughtful, public intellectual staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stripe’s mission is to increase the GDP of the internet. As part of that
mission, one of their many products is Atlas, a service that allows
entrepreneurs from around
the world to incorporate Delaware LLCs and C-Corporations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that Atlas is core to Stripe becoming a $100B+ company.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
But what’s so special about an incorporation service?
Hundreds of thousands
of companies get incorporated every year, and there are plenty of online
incorporation services already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a start, Atlas is much better than its competitors.
Though this might at first look like a well-commoditized market,
it is not at all.
Services like LegalZoom, CooleyGo, etc. offer a smaller set of incorporation
options and
a lower quality of legal formation documents.
Meanwhile, Atlas is as good
as having an Orrick lawyer do the job, while being an online form
a tenth of that price. Even a cheap lawyer is still twice as expensive for the job.
Plus, Atlas is unique in that it services international entrepreneurs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, even being the best incorporation service in the world might be worth at
most a few billion dollars.
The exceptional value in Atlas is in the lock-in it enables for B2B services added on top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest challenge of B2B services is customer acquisition.
How do you win over enterprise clients when existing relationships are so sticky?
The current dominant strategy is to be the first one there.
Start working with a company at the
earliest stages, in order to
make actual money off them a few years down the line,
when they’re much bigger and need more expensive services.
This strategy is
everywhere:
AWS extends credits to lock the earliest startups into their
cloud platform.
Brex advertises specifically to seed-stage startups, but they only
start to really make money when those startups are Series-C companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atlas is the ultimate player in that strategy.
There’s no earlier stage to get
involved than at incorporation.
Stripe is already using Atlas in the obvious way:
companies incorporated with Atlas automatically have a Stripe account,
and can get automatically get a Silicon Valley Bank account&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; set up so they
can start processing payments, via Stripe, immediately.
That’s extremely
powerful lead-gen.
But the potential for Atlas is much greater yet:
Atlas could automatically set up the company with a corporate credit card, and
all the required insurance.
It could set a customer up with a password manager, a virtual mail address,
accounting,
and so on. Each of these are multi-billion-dollar markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The endgame for Stripe Atlas is that it offers a
&lt;em&gt;business in a box&lt;/em&gt;, and
in turn it determines the B2B service&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; spend of such a business in perpetuity.
This is staggeringly powerful: first, it demolishes barriers to entry for
new entrepreneurs, handling all the tedious operational setup items, so the
entrepreneur can focus 100% on building a great product.
This is a real social good, for entrepreneurs and their customers around the entire globe.
Second, it puts up massive barriers to entry for competing service providers:
things like credit cards, insurance, accounting, virtual mail, etc. all
have low churn. Once a company launches with Atlas, a random
accounting service provider would effectively be forever locked out from
getting that company as a customer. Atlas reigns as gatekeeper supreme.
For an infrastructure company, owning the point at which customers otherwise
start to
&lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; their infrastructure is a position of unparalleled competitive strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclosure: I am not an employee of Stripe, paid by Stripe, and do not currently
have any financial interest in Stripe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As of April 2020, Stripe is valued at around $36 billion. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Of course, the day that Stripe gets a banking license, that’s going to be
a Stripe bank account. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While most of this is B2B SaaS, it’s noteworthy that not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of it
is strictly software (for example, accounting or legal services). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Stripe is a well-known innovator in digital payments. They attacked one of the most intimidating and locked-down markets, and made it look like child’s play. They have a compounding competitive edge in processing payments more efficiently for their customers, and the best-crafted APIs in the entire industry. Stripe is admired on these grounds, and more: they have their own press, in line with their thoughtful, public intellectual staff.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Never Invest in the Business Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/12/angel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Never Invest in the Business Model" /><published>2020-09-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/12/angel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/12/angel.html">&lt;p&gt;I am an angel investor. I have been investing personally in early-stage companies,
Pre-Seed through Series B, since 2015. I do it not for money but for love of the game;
the greatest pleasure to me is to learn from entrepreneurs smarter than me, and help them succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last five years, as I look at my wins and misses, one thing seems clear:
at the earliest stages, business models do not matter at all.
This is a deeply unpopular
position, in part because philosopher-king VCs love to talk about business abstractions
and ask about moats, network effects, returns to scale, value chains, innovator’s dilemmas and so forth.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
But at the seed stage, very little of this matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startups rarely stick to the original business plan.
There’s always a pivot: sometimes in the product, sometimes in go-to-market,
sometimes in the whole thing. In addition, exogenous shocks (COVID-19 being a great example)
perturb the best laid plans of mice and men, and every startup eventually finds itself
in deep and unfamiliar waters.
These are the moments that dictate success or failure, and what matters then?
Cash in the bank, and the nimbleness and thoughtfulness of the team. Those are the only things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a lot of run-ins with this pattern over the last eight months due to COVID.
The businesses that were most vulnerable to COVID (and, inversely, least able
to take advantage of COVID) were the ones that were most exposed to their
own business plans, that had the least nimble founders, and left the least
optionality for pivots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, great teams always have a leg up.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, my position is that the business model at the pre-seed/seed stage doesn’t matter.
It’s barely worth diligencing. This gets me a lot of flak from other investors,
presumably because they feel smart when they write their multi-page memos,
and here I am saying that the emperor has no clothes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar, and somewhat more popular position, is that startup financials don’t matter.
If you barely have revenue, your future forecasts are worthless. Reality
will always differ greatly, and anyone with a pulse
knows this.
However, looking at a startup’s forecasts is still valuable, because it
tells you whether the startup is financially sophisticated and can put together
a good financial model, which is a good general indicator of their maturity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My position goes one step further: it’s not just the forecasts that never
survive first contact with reality, it’s the entire business model.
Some parts will be harder, others will be easier, and some will change altogether.
Add random macro-scale perturbations like COVID, recessions, regulatory shifts,
and you can assume that &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; early-stage business model is subject to great
change, so much so that you might discard it altogether.
However, evaluating it still has significant value
in that it
tells you about the thoughtfulness of the founders, which is critical.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I don’t invest in business models. I invest in great founders
who are gritty, resourceful, and can assemble great teams. I treat finances and business models like
brain-teasers in interviews; performative exercises that are fun to debate
and tell me a lot about the maturity of the underlying entrepreneur,
but I almost completely discard their content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, don’t believe me? Let’s take a look at these giants
and tell me whether you would have “invested in the business model”
when they were founded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 2009 2D Browser MMO. Just another video game in an endless
  sea of competitors. This eventually became &lt;strong&gt;Slack&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 2012 video conferencing platform, when there were hundreds
  of competitors and the market was locked down by Microsoft and Google.
  This moatless company became &lt;strong&gt;Zoom&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 2005 video-based online dating service. &lt;strong&gt;YouTube&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 1994 online bookshop. &lt;strong&gt;Amazon&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 2006 online snowboard equipment shop. &lt;strong&gt;Shopify&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too much business risk? You love the tech but there’s no moat?
You want a network effect? Try betting on the founder instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;I suspect these topics get attention for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(a)&lt;/strong&gt; They add an air of intellectual legitimacy to venture investing.
    Like technical analysis for stocks, it adds pseudo-rigor,
    making the process of investing look more scientific.
    Sometimes these patterns are truthfully there, but they are usually
    only apparent in retrospect.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(b)&lt;/strong&gt; It’s just marketing for VCs. In this industry, it takes ten years
    before you figure out whether someone is actually good or not.
    In the absence of that evidence, for most VCs the entire game is marketing
    and making themselves sound as smart as possible, where buzzword business-school
    theories are very helpful for conning rubes. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are some counterexamples of “Great Teams that Failed”.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Magic&quot;&gt;General Magic&lt;/a&gt;
is a good example, but closer inspection usually reveals that part of the team was really lacking.
For example, General Magic certainly had the best technologists of the day,
but the &lt;em&gt;actual product being shipped&lt;/em&gt;, thanks to weak management, was hot garbage.
It is a special tragedy when a company has a partially excellent team
and a partially terrible team, because the lowest common denominator
usually dominates the outcome. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In other words, if I’m not 100% on board with the business model but
I believe in the founder, I’ll invest. If the business model is actually implausible,
then the founder has not thought deeply enough, and I’m out. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I am an angel investor. I have been investing personally in early-stage companies, Pre-Seed through Series B, since 2015. I do it not for money but for love of the game; the greatest pleasure to me is to learn from entrepreneurs smarter than me, and help them succeed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">For the Future of Work, Look to Gaming</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/06/work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="For the Future of Work, Look to Gaming" /><published>2020-09-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/06/work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/06/work.html">&lt;p&gt;In 2002, my mom started a new job in finance.
One day, I visited her office.
As part of the grand tour, she showed me her
Lotus Notes setup on her PC, and explained that she received around 400 emails a day.
This &lt;em&gt;baffled&lt;/em&gt; my eleven year old mind: “why don’t you guys just use MSN?” My
friends at school used Microsoft’s Messenger for everything. Some of my friends
in the US had me hopping on AOL, but either one seemed obviously better than
my mom and her highly-paid colleagues shooting one-line emails through their bulky setups.
Nearly twenty years later, Slack and Microsoft Teams are finally making real-time chat
commonplace even among the most traditional enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 2000s, I was deep in MMO gaming (specifically &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RuneScape&quot;&gt;RuneScape&lt;/a&gt;).
I joined and led clans of hundreds of other players,
sometimes in PVP, but most often just to make money.
For us kids, these were remarkably successful group efforts:
large groups of teenage strangers around the world organized themselves, mostly over text chat, to work together
for hours every day.
I still know my major timezone overlaps off by heart from back then.
We used &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PhpBB&quot;&gt;phpBB forums&lt;/a&gt;
for longer-form discussion and official matters, and set up
internal Wikis for knowledge management.
We used IRC to chat in real-time,
and set up dozens of custom scripts to integrate with external services.
If we
needed audio to chat in real-time,
we’d use &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ventrilo&quot;&gt;Ventrilo&lt;/a&gt;,
which would support
up to 400 people simultaneously.
For sharing short screen recordings, we used
&lt;a href=&quot;https://gyazo.com/&quot;&gt;Gyazo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://puush.me/&quot;&gt;Puush&lt;/a&gt;, a decade before &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.loom.com/&quot;&gt;Loom&lt;/a&gt; was founded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, the past few months of COVID quarantine have been a real throwback for me.
As a teen, I sat at my desk for fourteen hours a day, coordinating buyouts of ingame items,
playing on one screen, watching IRC and forums on the other, while chatting over Ventrilo.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Now, as an adult, I am doing the same, just with real work, Slack, and Zoom instead.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the world has been adjusting to this new normal, and venture/tech Twitter
(mostly people who were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; obsessive online-gaming teens in the early 2000s)
has been abuzz with theories about what collaboration in this new world looks like.
To me, it looks a great deal like the toolset I used to very competitively&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; play online games.
Some tools, like Notion, GitHub, and Roam Research are genuinely unprecedented
in that they have no prior product analogies, but for the most part, you can
predict the 2020 remote work toolkit by looking
at the 2010 gaming toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s unsurprising that there would be a strong correspondence between online
gaming and work tools. Both are collaborative team efforts, and require low-latency communication
over text, audio, and video. Both make use of complex external services to manage
recruiting, onboarding, collective knowledge, and to solve complicated
coordination problems over multiple timezones for dozens, if not hundreds of teammates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look ahead. What does gaming in 2020 tell us
about collaborative work in the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twitch&quot;&gt;Twitch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/&quot;&gt;Twitch&lt;/a&gt; is a livestreaming/social platform, most popular for video games.
Streamers on Twitch have slowly expanded to now include real-life vlogging,
teaching, live coding, painting, writing, and other non-gaming genres.
What’s most interesting is that streamers are starting to use Twitch to share their
&lt;em&gt;creative efforts&lt;/em&gt; as they build: some people are now even &lt;a href=&quot;https://24hrstartup.com/&quot;&gt;building businesses&lt;/a&gt;,
all in public, on Twitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this style of content production and engagement is
going to shift &lt;em&gt;how work is done&lt;/em&gt; in a few years.
Most employees will be streaming as they work, and their colleagues
may drop in on their streams with ideas and suggestions.
It’ll feel weirdly invasive
at first.
There’s certainly a hump to get over when
live-streaming your thoughts and showing your intimate, unfinished work-product drafts.
However, once people get used to it, it’s collaboration supercharged.
You’ll work, take a break, peruse your coworkers’ streams, find something interesting, drop in,
chat for five minutes, share context, and get back to your own stuff.
The feedback loop of creation becomes much tighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;video-as-institutional-knowledge&quot;&gt;Video as Institutional Knowledge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closely related to Twitch is YouTube – after you’ve done a stream, you’ll upload a copy for posterity.
This solves a problem in how companies deal with the loss of institutional knowledge
– namely, &lt;em&gt;how to do stuff&lt;/em&gt; – as they grow. As people leave, so do all the little procedures
and processes that glue together a large operational organization. All companies try to remedy this
through written knowledge bases, and the vast majority fail. Screen recordings
of &lt;em&gt;how employees work&lt;/em&gt; can be powerful stores of institutional knowledge.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;audio-preferred&quot;&gt;Audio Preferred&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Face-to-face communications for routine meetings are going away.
I’m in a lot of Zoom meetings these days, and
I don’t want to stare at another person’s face,
and try to read their expressions.
It wears me out.
I don’t want to carefully adjust
my background to look presentable.
Most people I know who are on 3+ calls a day
will subtly push toward audio-only.
New users may start off excited about video meetings and seeing other people’s faces,
but as they become power users, video becomes too taxing and they move toward audio only.
Outside of important/first-time external meetings,
power users and well-acquainted teammates don’t want all the baggage
of video calls, they want &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TeamSpeak&quot;&gt;TeamSpeak&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;splinter-groups&quot;&gt;Splinter Groups&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as meetings go, the current big open problem is that it is extremely difficult
to replicate the experience of meeting as a group, splintering into smaller conversations,
and hopping from conversation to conversation, the way you might at a professional event
(or a party in Silicon Valley; the two are identical).
Ventrilo solved this problem
over a decade ago:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; create ephemeral channels/groups within your VoIP server
that people can join, and that close when they have no members. Supporting this
is the next big step for Zoom.
If they fall short, they very seriously open up
the market for any other entrant that can facilitate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;arvr&quot;&gt;AR/VR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all the talk about shifting paradigms under remote work, there’s been little talk
of AR/VR collaborative solutions. There are tons of vendors! But they’re all uncanny-valley
experiences that very imperfectly try to replicate the experience of face-to-face meetings,
or (even worse) conferences. All of these collaborate-in-VR solutions feel awkwardly skeuomorphic,
and I expect that nothing will come of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because, just like in the above point, face-to-face comms are an &lt;em&gt;artifact&lt;/em&gt;, not a &lt;em&gt;goal&lt;/em&gt;.
The goals are always to exchange information, build trust, and to make decisions.
Strapping into an Oculus Rift to sit in a virtual meeting room with a bunch of
Lara Croft lookalikes doesn’t advance the goal, it only distracts. Even a perfect VR
experience would only distract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going out on a limb, I expect that if users do end up going for 3D interaction,
it’s going to look a lot more like a blend of traditional MMORPGs and &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/get-started-hubs-mozilla&quot;&gt;Mozilla Hubs&lt;/a&gt;
than anything requiring an AR or VR device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discord&quot;&gt;Discord&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Discord starts marketing itself for a more professional crowd, it will
destroy Slack. It’s a far superior software product – lighter-weight, faster,
and it natively supports audio and video chat inside the platform.
Discord is a $10B+ company in the making. Perhaps controversially, I think
if users adapt to audio being more important than video, Discord is a serious competitor to Zoom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lighter-weight-applications&quot;&gt;Lighter-Weight Applications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All good gaming-adjacent software is light and fast.
Bulky software would slow down your computer and you’d lose in games!
Similarly, we’re enduring an epidemic of slow enterprise software.
Asana, JIRA, Confluence, Slack, Google Drive,
and so forth: using any of these tools is like wading through molasses.
There’s lag when you enter keystrokes, interfaces load slowly due to hundreds of API calls
under the hood, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I desperately hope that as SaaS providers try harder to provide mind-melding interfaces
between man and machine, they’ll eventually realize that a lack of speed
is the biggest barrier between the two; that the speed of response and navigation
is the single most important feature to a serious user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, we are in a strange period of adjustment as people learn to work remotely.
Users cling to representations of real life, meetings, and face-to-face Zooms.
But this is an inconvenience, and it’ll become more rare for routine work.
Audio is king in the remote world work; video – of actual humans – is less relevant,
simulacrum of a past paradigm.
On the other hand, video of &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; is of paramount importance, and the combination
of live streaming and video storage will reshape how employees work, collaborate,
and share institutional knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this world, AR and VR are somewhat counter-intuitive losers, only useful
in very niche applications. If people collaborate in some kinds of 3D spaces,
it’ll be mostly for rapid prototyping, sketching, etc.
It is clear
that collaborative, multi-user, version-controlled/historied software will succeed
in this paradigm; I expect more products like Figma and Google Docs to arrive, and
single-user software like PhotoShop to quietly leave the scene. And I pray that
this new, glorious software will be fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The fact that Clubhouse basically put a superior product/marketing skin over Ventrilo-style VoIP, put it on mobile, and then stuck a $100M price tag on it, blew my mind. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The familiarity of this sensation was pleasant until it started &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/08/21/incel.html&quot;&gt;driving me crazy&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;You might laugh at the notion of a competitive RuneScape player, but it ended up paying my way through college.
A story for another time. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For example, think about how, for virtually all but the largest companies,
 the instructions for setting up a new developer environment
are almost always flawed or out of date.
Following a screen recording of the most recent employee to get onboarded
would be a much more reliable source to draw on. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mumble_(software)&quot;&gt;Mumble&lt;/a&gt; solved it in a different way: for online 3D spaces,
like in FPS games, not only can you break up into channels, etc. but the loudness of your voice, as heard by another player,
is proportionate to your distance from them. Insofar as supporting the skeuomorphic VR experience goes,
this might be a clean way to make it feel more organic. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In 2002, my mom started a new job in finance. One day, I visited her office. As part of the grand tour, she showed me her Lotus Notes setup on her PC, and explained that she received around 400 emails a day. This baffled my eleven year old mind: “why don’t you guys just use MSN?” My friends at school used Microsoft’s Messenger for everything. Some of my friends in the US had me hopping on AOL, but either one seemed obviously better than my mom and her highly-paid colleagues shooting one-line emails through their bulky setups. Nearly twenty years later, Slack and Microsoft Teams are finally making real-time chat commonplace even among the most traditional enterprises.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 is Turning Me into an Incel</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/29/incel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 is Turning Me into an Incel" /><published>2020-08-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/29/incel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/29/incel.html">&lt;p&gt;Nobody’s saying it, so I will: I haven’t had sex in six months, and I am losing my mind.
The mental health impacts of COVID-19 and associated long-term lockdowns are devastating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever obedient, I stayed mostly inside until early July.
I made the most of lockdown: plenty of Zoom catch-ups
with friends, reading, writing, and work.
But being inside, I stopped exercising,
and my life became overwhelmingly sedentary.
I felt this physically inactive lifestyle impact my sleep, diet,
even hormones and mood.
It wore me out. After three or four months, I had gained weight, and felt much weaker.
Crises always compound, and as if COVID-19 wasn’t enough, now I’m stuck with
body image issues, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desperate to be outside and exercise, I temporarily moved to Park City, UT
a few weeks ago.
That was fantastic for lifting my spirits, and I feel better and healthier
just getting some sunshine again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the loneliness remains. I don’t really know anyone in Utah, and though
there are now lots of tech-people camping out here, this is the worst time
imaginable for meeting new people in person, or getting included in their group
activities when you haven’t been quarantining with them already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, the lack of human contact is debilitating.
I’ve been occasionally quarantining
with friends, doing socially-distanced hangouts, etc.
but I haven’t had
a real hug in months, certainly not from a woman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a real first for me.
I’ve always been pretty physically active. Since becoming an adult,
the longest I’ve gone without sex might have been three months? The longest without
a hug or hanging out physically close in a group: maybe a few weeks? The longest
without a light touch or shaking a hand: maybe a few days?
Not only is there real psychological or physiological deprivation going on,
this experience is especially jarring because it’s so new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tens of millions of people are going through similar
difficulties right now. I wonder what the aggregate damage is.
It is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.lww.com/psychosomaticmedicine/Fulltext/2019/07000/Loneliness,_Living_Alone,_and_All_Cause_Mortality_.6.aspx&quot;&gt;well-established fact&lt;/a&gt;
that loneliness is associated with a host
of psychological and physiological issues, and generally raises morbidity.
Now we have that en masse: millions of people are currently
living lifestyles close to solitary confinement.
I certainly have been feeling my mental health degrade as I itch for regular
human contact again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, and the recent violence in Kenosha, has had me thinking about violent incels.
People like Elliot Rodger,
Kyle Rittenhouse, etc. are easy to mock.
They are dweeby, entitled losers who can’t get laid and then take it out on the world.
It’s very difficult to sympathize with them.
Obviously there are many factors of social ostracization, isolation, and radicalization,
but I feel like COVID-19 induced lockdowns
has given me a small taste of part of their existence: just sitting around,
not having in-person friends, and not having sex is &lt;em&gt;terrible&lt;/em&gt;.
If that is their existence for years-on-end, with added issues on top, then no wonder
these guys completely lose it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In turn, I worry that COVID-19 lockdowns, by the constraints they impose, will
greatly grow the incel underclass. Millions of frustrated young men, stuck at home
with nothing on their hands but &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doomscrolling&quot;&gt;doomscrolling&lt;/a&gt;
in an unbelievably politically charged time?
I couldn’t imagine a more lethal recipe for mass radicalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a directly actionable conclusion to this piece.
Tens of millions of people, myself included,
are having their lives’ first real experiences with real isolation,
and it’s awful.
Learning from it, it is unsurprising – indeed, it seems inevitable – that
incels act out the way they do, and I worry that lockdowns are adding millions
to their numbers.
In general, I’m worried that in the US, where lockdowns have been
more severe, less successful, and much longer-lasting than elsewhere,
we’ve created a recipe that is in practice only moderately effective for preventing
spread of COVID-19, but at the same time is absolutely wrecking the mental health
of those who follow them.
Economics aside, is this cure worse than the disease? What are the second-order effects going to be?
While I am certainly no COVID-19 denier, it’s nudging
me to ask whether Sweden had the right &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COVID-19_pandemic_in_Sweden&quot;&gt;approach&lt;/a&gt; after all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Nobody’s saying it, so I will: I haven’t had sex in six months, and I am losing my mind. The mental health impacts of COVID-19 and associated long-term lockdowns are devastating.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Does Steve Bannon Think?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/bannon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Does Steve Bannon Think?" /><published>2020-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/bannon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/bannon.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Bannon appeared on our collective radars four years ago in August 2016, as the chief
strategist of Trump’s campaign. After Trump won, baffled voters on the left
looked to Bannon as the explanation, the &lt;em&gt;eminence grise&lt;/em&gt;, the man behind the curtain.
Bannon
was mysterious, said some fascist-sounding things, and looked unhealthy like a Hollywood villain.
It was easy to box him in as Darth Sidious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bannon lasted twelve months with Trump. He was fired in August 2017 after he
pushed the “fine people on both sides” line for addressing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unite_the_Right_rally&quot;&gt;Charlottesville&lt;/a&gt;.
He then disappeared from media coverage, as swiftly as he emerged.
I had forgotten about him until
I heard a quick line in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RmsN4_hftvI&quot;&gt;an interview&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Millennials, they’re like 19th century Russian serfs. They’re in better shape,
they have more information, they’re better dressed, but they don’t own anything.
Millennials don’t have a chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was very true. Bannon’s comments about millennials being a generation of
permanent renters, whose economic situation resembled feudalism&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; more than anything else,
struck me as succinct, correct, and hardly expressed by anyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, I was curious: surely there’s more to Bannon than the one-dimensional
media caricature, especially due to his significant impact on the success
of Trump’s election. So, I asked: &lt;strong&gt;what does Steve Bannon really think?&lt;/strong&gt;
I present my findings, as well as my reflections, below.
My view is that Bannon’s publicly advertised positions make significant sense
and are worth discussing, but Bannon himself is a suave trickster: some of his
purported views are certainly not genuine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;views&quot;&gt;Views&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon describes himself as an &lt;strong&gt;economic nationalist&lt;/strong&gt;. He believes that
  the value of &lt;em&gt;citizenship&lt;/em&gt; has suffered greatly in the past decades.
  In the US,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
  the government has allowed its obligations to its citizens to fall behind
  its obligations toward corporations. Instead of maximizing citizen quality
  of life, we are maximizing shareholder value.
  The lower-middle and working classes have lost the value of their citizenship;
  Bannon seeks to restore it.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the flip-side, Bannon believes that the world is effectively run by a
  &lt;strong&gt;permanent political class&lt;/strong&gt;: elites who never lose, and who
  have dispassionately managed the decline of the US, using
  globalization to accrue more wealth and power to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon sees the &lt;strong&gt;2008 financial crisis&lt;/strong&gt; as a key coup for these elites:
  the banks were bailed out, not a single banker was punished,
  and the losses were socialized. That’s not capitalism. Following 2008,
  under Obama, the Fed’s balance sheet expanded from $1T to $4.5T.
  That quantitative easing (read: inflation) debased the value of the USD.
  The little guy – folks who hold, and depend on cash – paid for it.
  On the other hand,
  for people that hold real estate, IP, or equities,
  the last ten years have been the greatest run in history.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon describes this state as &lt;strong&gt;neofeudalism&lt;/strong&gt;: people who don’t own
  assets are effectively serfs. Millennials especially are
  permanent renters. They do not own anything, and the system is so efficient
  that they will never own anything. The resulting economic fragility is terrible:
  people aren’t having children, can’t cover emergencies, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon views both Democrats and Republicans to blame. First for 2008,
  second for continuous &lt;strong&gt;wage suppression&lt;/strong&gt;. To Bannon, both parties seek
  to let their corporate donors extract maximum profits – for Democrats,
  that’s by (legal or illegal) immigration&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that floods the
  labor supply, for Republicans that’s by free trade deals, which
  encourage outsourcing by
  having American labor compete in price with foreign labor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon views the &lt;strong&gt;Republican party&lt;/strong&gt; as playing to its donors, and
  opposed to their voter interests.
  In the last 20 years, the Republicans have sold their voters a Koch-brothers,
  Heritage-foundation, limited-government, free-trade vision.
  It has wrecked their education and healthcare systems, and sent all the jobs
  overseas. The effects have been ruinous.
  The Republican primary candidates of 2015/2016 were the strongest
  lineup of all time; any one of them would have won most presidential
  elections. But Trump could beat them all, because voters
  aren’t falling for the traditional Republican scam and policy mumbo-jumbo anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Bannon’s view, in 2016, voters cared about &lt;strong&gt;basic sovereignty&lt;/strong&gt;.
  Immigration, trade, employment, &lt;em&gt;where’s my paycheck&lt;/em&gt;.
  Voters care about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Trump_Access_Hollywood_tape&quot;&gt;locker room talk&lt;/a&gt;,
  but that’s easily outweighed when bigger things are at stake.
  In 2016, a record number of people thought the country was on the wrong track.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
  Voters want their sovereignty, their value as citizens back.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To Bannon, core to this loss of sovereignty for everyday citizens are &lt;strong&gt;three items&lt;/strong&gt;:
  (1) the recession and subsequent inflation,
  (2) pointless, expensive wars in Iraq and Afghanistan,
  and (3) outsourcing of American manufacturing to China.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon views &lt;strong&gt;China&lt;/strong&gt; as a totalitarian, mercantilist, murderous dictatorship.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
  He believes that the CCP poses the greatest threat to all freedom-loving people
  and industrial democracies, like Nazi Germany in the 1930s, a profound threat
  to the Westphalian order and Western democracy. Westerners are not taking the
  concentration camps in Xinjiang and annexation of Hong Kong as seriously as they should.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In turn, Bannon views the shareholder-value-maximization-induced outsourcing
  of &lt;strong&gt;US manufacturing&lt;/strong&gt; to China as a gargantuan mistake, inextricably causing to America’s decline.
  It has decimated
  employment in rural America, and lost American &lt;em&gt;key competence&lt;/em&gt;
  in essential industries. Bannon believes that the CCP has been running
  economic war on the US,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Americans haven’t realized it because of our Wall Street
  interests in China. We’ve gained a little more short-term economic efficiency,
  but lost
  the sovereignty and welfare of our working class – the backbone of US society – and enabled China
  to lock down and own advanced manufacturing in perpetuity. A disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With respect to Bannon’s core issues, he views Trump as an “&lt;strong&gt;imperfect, but armor-piercing shell&lt;/strong&gt;”: under Trump,
  the loss of American manufacturing, and foreign/trade policy with China,
  have gone from being marginal issues to front-and-center.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trump&lt;/strong&gt; won because of his basic appeal to the sovereignty of his voters;
  addressing immigration and outsourcing to China as the key issues. He had planned
  to run on those issues for over a decade.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; He knew
  how to connect with working-class voters, how to rally them, and how to be accessible –
  getting rid of the political nomenclature and policy jargon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon points out that politics has transitioned from the field of traditional politicians
  to the field of those who truly understand media. &lt;strong&gt;Mass communications&lt;/strong&gt; is
  overwhelming and omnipresent. Trump is a master of communications, he knows how to drive the media,
  to force the media to play on his field. The media is always &lt;em&gt;reacting&lt;/em&gt;, overwhelmed
  by his incessant scandal-generation. Bannon called the strategy “flooding the zone with shit,”
  and it’s undeniably effective.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, in this era of mass media, the country is all about politics. 118 million people voted in the 2018 midterms.
  Bannon’s view is that in terms of turnout, &lt;strong&gt;democracy&lt;/strong&gt; has never been more engaged and robust.
  This view is obviously facile: the early 1900s had similar levels of political engagement,
  until the polarization boiled over and you had armed coups. Angry discourse is manageable
  until interests have diverged so far that they’re irreconcilable, at which point
  the guns come out. It doesn’t take much to figure out that polarization is harmful.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;commentary&quot;&gt;Commentary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these views were expressed between 2018 and 2020.
Taken at face value, they seem reasonable.
Bannon’s articulation of why Trump won is clearer than any pundit’s or leftist’s,
and he raises
a serious question about priorities: &lt;strong&gt;are we on the left wasting our time
arguing about pronouns when our children will get shipped to concentration camps in Xinjiang?&lt;/strong&gt;
Are we dumb for sweating the small stuff and the optics, while not paying attention to the
big issues that, on net, might be a million times more impactful?
Bannon’s mission is clear: the CCP is the great threat to Western democracy and way of life;
boycott it at all costs, bring back American technological expertise
in manufacturing, and in the process restore the welfare of the working/lower-middle classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what’s suspicious about Bannon’s “economic nationalism” is that while he’s all about
economic &lt;em&gt;problems&lt;/em&gt;, he has little to say about economic &lt;em&gt;solutions&lt;/em&gt;.
While he aggressively
blames the elites for 2008 and for shipping jobs to China, he doesn’t have anything
to say for solving neofeudalism.
Obviously bringing back jobs will help a little,
but it’s neither a full solution, nor does it address the core problem.
Neofeudalism comes out of highly efficient, industrialized
wealth inequality, which occurs because the rate of return on capital is
greater than the rate of return on labor. This was the big problem that Piketty
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital_in_the_Twenty-First_Century&quot;&gt;pointed out&lt;/a&gt; in 2013.
While Bannon points out the same problem, and says that it’s important to restore
asset ownership to the working/middle classes, he doesn’t offer any solutions for &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;.
Shouldn’t an economic nationalist have cogent economic solutions to propose?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/news/q-and-a/the-narcissism-and-ego-that-led-to-steve-bannons-arrest&quot;&gt;good journalism&lt;/a&gt;
from people who have tracked Bannon more closely than I, who claim that Bannon’s
“economic nationalism” angle is new. Immigration has been his core issue
forever. It’s central to his economic nationalism, which raises a crucial question:
is Bannon’s economic nationalism just a vehicle for advancing his hostile views
on China and immigration, which he has made the #1 and #2 priorities in his
agenda?
While there’s no debate that Bannon is a nationalist, it’s suspect
how sincere the &lt;em&gt;economic&lt;/em&gt; part of his economic nationalism is.
If it is sincere, then there’s a real question as to how well thought-through it really is,
since an overwhelming number of economists across the political spectrum view
immigration as a net economic benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, there’s something unsettling and sly about Bannon’s purported economic nationalism:
he &lt;em&gt;insists&lt;/em&gt; that he’s not an ethnic nationalist, but somehow he always ends up
very closely aligned with them. Debaters &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8AtOw-xyMo8&quot;&gt;point this out&lt;/a&gt;,
but Bannon is a slippery debater: “everyone keeps calling me a fascist,
but fascists, by definition, want bigger states! I want to deconstruct the administrative state.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Bannon plays excellent definitions-games – he is able to easily
refute the accusation by definition, and in turn totally evade the &lt;em&gt;connotation&lt;/em&gt; that
his counterparties mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bannon also always has well-prepared counterexamples
to his opponents’ predictable attacks, but he never refutes them
on an abstract level.
For example, when confronted about Breitbart’s hateful, misleading content, he skillfully outmaneuvers
his leftist interrogator by describing how Breitbart was made to subvert the
Republican establishment.
His defense of the “fine people on both sides” comment is an especially powerful example of his argumentative contortions.
Bannon’s refutations regarding allegations of his ethnic nativism leave me
with the feeling of when someone is playing games,
moving the goalposts and feeding you bullshit, but you don’t have the time in the venue
to pick them apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bannon’s insincerity is clear in his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pm5xxlajTW0&quot;&gt;Frontline&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gDqAnOyAgt4&quot;&gt;interviews&lt;/a&gt; with PBS:
he plays to the intellectual audience with the most
centrist-populist version of his beliefs, but he’s hoodwinking the viewer:
he fawns over Trump, both personally and politically.
But we know that Bannon had been &lt;em&gt;fired&lt;/em&gt; from the White House,
and had then publicly disparaged Trump, and his family, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Bannon#Quotes_in_Michael_Wolff_books&quot;&gt;Michael Wolff’s Fire and Fury&lt;/a&gt;.
In the interview, Bannon is plainly lying in attempt to preserve whatever relationship with Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, no matter how candid Bannon seems, his integrity is weak.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/national-security/senate-intelligence-committee-donald-trump-jr-jared-kushner-stephen-bannon-erik-prince/2020/08/15/a7905a84-def5-11ea-b205-ff838e15a9a6_story.html&quot;&gt;Allegations&lt;/a&gt;
have emerged that Bannon lied to congressional investors during Mueller’s Investigation.
More shockingly – and in brazen irony – he’s now even been arrested for embezzling money
from his “We Build the Wall” non-profit fundraising campaign. Convincing Americans
they need to build a border wall, privately raising money for it, then defrauding
them of those funds, takes unbelievable chutzpah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion that I’m led to is that Bannon is a special type of grifter:
sly, insincere, and self-serving.
What kind of &lt;em&gt;nationalist&lt;/em&gt; lies to congressional investigators?
He’s a deeply skilled political operative. Who knows what his true personal goals are;
but I suspect the “economic nationalist” agenda he laid out above is not the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the economic nationalist agenda Bannon advocates is coherent,
and many points seem reasonable, certainly worthy of serious discussion.
Perhaps the issue with Bannon is the same as with Trump – they find a valid platform
to run on, something that deeply resonates with the masses, and where there is
genuine need for great change – but they wrap that in their own buffoonery and grift.
It turns out that even when running on a righteous cause,
all the habits formed over the decades, the little cons and lies,
they stick. No man can escape himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Millennials’ economic situation is feudalistic since
millennials do not &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; the underlying goods they are adding value to. Just
like how the agrarian serfs were allowed to subsist on their lord’s farm land,
the lord always captured more value. Similarly, millennials do not have any
equity in the enterprises they contribute to, and their cash compensation
is usually a small minority of the economic value they create for their employers.
Like the agrarian serfs of old, millennials are locked into a life of subsistence. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bannon thinks that this issue is not just specific to the US, but across the board:
in most western nations, the value of citizenship has suffered. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Possibly to thwart accusations of racism or &lt;em&gt;ethnic&lt;/em&gt; nationalism as opposed
to economic nationalism, Bannon will often remark that those lower-middle
and working class populations are, to a significant extent, Hispanic
and African-American. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In passing, Bannon also accuses Republicans of covertly encouraging
&lt;em&gt;illegal&lt;/em&gt; immigration as cheap labor. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;While Bannon repeatedly sticks to the “right track, wrong track” anecdote
as one of the key reasons for Trump winning, I couldn’t actually find
polling that substantiated his “record high” claims. It seems like voter outlook
in 2016 was similar to that of 2008 and 1992. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Bannon clarifies that he views the Chinese people as fine like any other,
and the ruling CCP cadre as a great evil. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;See currency manipulation, stockpiling PPE while telling the rest of the world
that COVID-19 is no big deal, etc. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;His presidential ambitions became clear around 2010, when he started
writing cheques to major conservative leaders, and he published &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_to_Get_Tough&quot;&gt;Time
to Get Tough&lt;/a&gt;, a policy book. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In none of the interviews that I watched could I get a read on what exactly
Bannon understands to be the administrative state, or the precise issues with it.
Bannon paints with a broad brush. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Introduction</summary></entry></feed>