<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-12T14:57:11-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jay Riverlong</title><subtitle>Jay Riverlong's personal website. Essays and thoughts.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Never Invest in the Business Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/12/angel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Never Invest in the Business Model" /><published>2020-09-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/12/angel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/12/angel.html">&lt;p&gt;I am an angel investor. I have been investing personally in early-stage companies,
Pre-Seed through Series B, since 2015. I do it not for money but for love of the game;
the greatest pleasure to me is to learn from entrepreneurs smarter than me, and help them succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last five years, as I look at my wins and misses, one thing seems clear:
at the earliest stages, business models do not matter at all.
This is a deeply unpopular
position, in part because philosopher-king VCs love to talk about business abstractions
and ask about moats, network effects, returns to scale, value chains, innovator’s dilemmas and so forth.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
But at the seed stage, very little of this matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startups rarely stick to the original business plan.
There’s always a pivot: sometimes in the product, sometimes in go-to-market,
sometimes in the whole thing. In addition, exogenous shocks (COVID-19 being a great example)
perturb the best laid plans of mice and men, and every startup eventually finds itself
in deep and unfamiliar waters.
These are the moments that dictate success or failure, and what matters then?
Cash in the bank, and the nimbleness and thoughtfulness of the team. Those are the only things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a lot of run-ins with this pattern over the last eight months due to COVID.
The businesses that were most vulnerable to COVID (and, inversely, least able
to take advantage of COVID) were the ones that were most exposed to their
own business plans, that had the least nimble founders, and left the least
optionality for pivots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, great teams always have a leg up.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, my position is that the business model at the pre-seed/seed stage doesn’t matter.
It’s barely worth diligencing. This gets me a lot of flak from other investors,
presumably because they feel smart when they write their multi-page memos,
and here I am saying that the emperor has no clothes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar, and somewhat more popular position, is that startup financials don’t matter.
If you barely have revenue, your future forecasts are worthless. Reality
will always differ greatly, and anyone with a pulse
knows this.
However, looking at a startup’s forecasts is still valuable, because it
tells you whether the startup is financially sophisticated and can put together
a good financial model, which is a good general indicator of their maturity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My position goes one step further: it’s not just the forecasts that never
survive first contact with reality, it’s the entire business model.
Some parts will be harder, others will be easier, and some will change altogether.
Add random macro-scale perturbations like COVID, recessions, regulatory shifts,
and you can assume that &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; early-stage business model is subject to great
change, so much so that you might discard it altogether.
However, evaluating it still has significant value
in that it
tells you about the thoughtfulness of the founders, which is critical.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I don’t invest in business models. I invest in great founders
who are gritty, resourceful, and can assemble great teams. I treat finances and business models like
brain-teasers in interviews; performative exercises that are fun to debate
and tell me a lot about the maturity of the underlying entrepreneur,
but I almost completely discard their content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, don’t believe me? Let’s take a look at these giants
and tell me whether you would have “invested in the business model”
when they were founded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 2009 2D Browser MMO. Just another video game in an endless
  sea of competitors. This eventually became &lt;strong&gt;Slack&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 2012 video conferencing platform, when there were hundreds
  of competitors and the market was locked down by Microsoft and Google.
  This moatless company became &lt;strong&gt;Zoom&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 2005 video-based online dating service. &lt;strong&gt;YouTube&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 1994 online bookshop. &lt;strong&gt;Amazon&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 2006 online snowboard equipment shop. &lt;strong&gt;Shopify&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too much business risk? You love the tech but there’s no moat?
You want a network effect? Try betting on the founder instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;I suspect these topics get attention for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(a)&lt;/strong&gt; They add an air of intellectual legitimacy to venture investing.
    Like technical analysis for stocks, it adds pseudo-rigor,
    making the process of investing look more scientific.
    Sometimes these patterns are truthfully there, but they are usually
    only apparent in retrospect.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(b)&lt;/strong&gt; It’s just marketing for VCs. In this industry, it takes ten years
    before you figure out whether someone is actually good or not.
    In the absence of that evidence, for most VCs the entire game is marketing
    and making themselves sound as smart as possible, where buzzword business-school
    theories are very helpful for conning rubes. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are some counterexamples of “Great Teams that Failed”.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Magic&quot;&gt;General Magic&lt;/a&gt;
is a good example, but closer inspection usually reveals that part of the team was really lacking.
For example, General Magic certainly had the best technologists of the day,
but the &lt;em&gt;actual product being shipped&lt;/em&gt;, thanks to weak management, was hot garbage.
It is a special tragedy when a company has a partially excellent team
and a partially terrible team, because the lowest common denominator
usually dominates the outcome. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In other words, if I’m not 100% on board with the business model but
I believe in the founder, I’ll invest. If the business model is actually implausible,
then the founder has not thought deeply enough, and I’m out. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I am an angel investor. I have been investing personally in early-stage companies, Pre-Seed through Series B, since 2015. I do it not for money but for love of the game; the greatest pleasure to me is to learn from entrepreneurs smarter than me, and help them succeed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">For the Future of Work, Look to Gaming</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/06/work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="For the Future of Work, Look to Gaming" /><published>2020-09-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/06/work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/06/work.html">&lt;p&gt;In 2002, my mom started a new job in finance.
One day, I visited her office.
As part of the grand tour, she showed me her
Lotus Notes setup on her PC, and explained that she received around 400 emails a day.
This &lt;em&gt;baffled&lt;/em&gt; my eleven year old mind: “why don’t you guys just use MSN?” My
friends at school used Microsoft’s Messenger for everything. Some of my friends
in the US had me hopping on AOL, but either one seemed obviously better than
my mom and her highly-paid colleagues shooting one-line emails through their bulky setups.
Nearly twenty years later, Slack and Microsoft Teams are finally making real-time chat
commonplace even among the most traditional enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 2000s, I was deep in MMO gaming (specifically &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RuneScape&quot;&gt;RuneScape&lt;/a&gt;).
I joined and led clans of hundreds of other players,
sometimes in PVP, but most often just to make money.
For us kids, these were remarkably successful group efforts:
large groups of teenage strangers around the world organized themselves, mostly over text chat, to work together
for hours every day.
I still know my major timezone overlaps off by heart from back then.
We used &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PhpBB&quot;&gt;phpBB forums&lt;/a&gt;
for longer-form discussion and official matters, and set up
internal Wikis for knowledge management.
We used IRC to chat in real-time,
and set up dozens of custom scripts to integrate with external services.
If we
needed audio to chat in real-time,
we’d use &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ventrilo&quot;&gt;Ventrilo&lt;/a&gt;,
which would support
up to 400 people simultaneously.
For sharing short screen recordings, we used
&lt;a href=&quot;https://gyazo.com/&quot;&gt;Gyazo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://puush.me/&quot;&gt;Puush&lt;/a&gt;, a decade before &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.loom.com/&quot;&gt;Loom&lt;/a&gt; was founded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, the past few months of COVID quarantine have been a real throwback for me.
As a teen, I sat at my desk for fourteen hours a day, coordinating buyouts of ingame items,
playing on one screen, watching IRC and forums on the other, while chatting over Ventrilo.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Now, as an adult, I am doing the same, just with real work, Slack, and Zoom instead.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the world has been adjusting to this new normal, and venture/tech Twitter
(mostly people who were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; obsessive online-gaming teens in the early 2000s)
has been abuzz with theories about what collaboration in this new world looks like.
To me, it looks a great deal like the toolset I used to very competitively&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; play online games.
Some tools, like Notion, GitHub, and Roam Research are genuinely unprecedented
in that they have no prior product analogies, but for the most part, you can
predict the 2020 remote work toolkit by looking
at the 2010 gaming toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s unsurprising that there would be a strong correspondence between online
gaming and work tools. Both are collaborative team efforts, and require low-latency communication
over text, audio, and video. Both make use of complex external services to manage
recruiting, onboarding, collective knowledge, and to solve complicated
coordination problems over multiple timezones for dozens, if not hundreds of teammates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look ahead. What does gaming in 2020 tell us
about collaborative work in the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twitch&quot;&gt;Twitch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/&quot;&gt;Twitch&lt;/a&gt; is a livestreaming/social platform, most popular for video games.
Streamers on Twitch have slowly expanded to now include real-life vlogging,
teaching, live coding, painting, writing, and other non-gaming genres.
What’s most interesting is that streamers are starting to use Twitch to share their
&lt;em&gt;creative efforts&lt;/em&gt; as they build: some people are now even &lt;a href=&quot;https://24hrstartup.com/&quot;&gt;building businesses&lt;/a&gt;,
all in public, on Twitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this style of content production and engagement is
going to shift &lt;em&gt;how work is done&lt;/em&gt; in a few years.
Most employees will be streaming as they work, and their colleagues
may drop in on their streams with ideas and suggestions.
It’ll feel weirdly invasive
at first.
There’s certainly a hump to get over when
live-streaming your thoughts and showing your intimate, unfinished work-product drafts.
However, once people get used to it, it’s collaboration supercharged.
You’ll work, take a break, peruse your coworkers’ streams, find something interesting, drop in,
chat for five minutes, share context, and get back to your own stuff.
The feedback loop of creation becomes much tighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;video-as-institutional-knowledge&quot;&gt;Video as Institutional Knowledge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closely related to Twitch is YouTube – after you’ve done a stream, you’ll upload a copy for posterity.
This solves a problem in how companies deal with the loss of institutional knowledge
– namely, &lt;em&gt;how to do stuff&lt;/em&gt; – as they grow. As people leave, so do all the little procedures
and processes that glue together a large operational organization. All companies try to remedy this
through written knowledge bases, and the vast majority fail. Screen recordings
of &lt;em&gt;how employees work&lt;/em&gt; can be powerful stores of institutional knowledge.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;audio-preferred&quot;&gt;Audio Preferred&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Face-to-face communications for routine meetings are going away.
I’m in a lot of Zoom meetings these days, and
I don’t want to stare at another person’s face,
and try to read their expressions.
It wears me out.
I don’t want to carefully adjust
my background to look presentable.
Most people I know who are on 3+ calls a day
will subtly push toward audio-only.
New users may start off excited about video meetings and seeing other people’s faces,
but as they become power users, video becomes too taxing and they move toward audio only.
Outside of important/first-time external meetings,
power users and well-acquainted teammates don’t want all the baggage
of video calls, they want &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TeamSpeak&quot;&gt;TeamSpeak&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;splinter-groups&quot;&gt;Splinter Groups&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as meetings go, the current big open problem is that it is extremely difficult
to replicate the experience of meeting as a group, splintering into smaller conversations,
and hopping from conversation to conversation, the way you might at a professional event
(or a party in Silicon Valley; the two are identical).
Ventrilo solved this problem
over a decade ago:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; create ephemeral channels/groups within your VoIP server
that people can join, and that close when they have no members. Supporting this
is the next big step for Zoom.
If they fall short, they very seriously open up
the market for any other entrant that can facilitate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;arvr&quot;&gt;AR/VR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all the talk about shifting paradigms under remote work, there’s been little talk
of AR/VR collaborative solutions. There are tons of vendors! But they’re all uncanny-valley
experiences that very imperfectly try to replicate the experience of face-to-face meetings,
or (even worse) conferences. All of these collaborate-in-VR solutions feel awkwardly skeuomorphic,
and I expect that nothing will come of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because, just like in the above point, face-to-face comms are an &lt;em&gt;artifact&lt;/em&gt;, not a &lt;em&gt;goal&lt;/em&gt;.
The goals are always to exchange information, build trust, and to make decisions.
Strapping into an Oculus Rift to sit in a virtual meeting room with a bunch of
Lara Croft lookalikes doesn’t advance the goal, it only distracts. Even a perfect VR
experience would only distract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going out on a limb, I expect that if users do end up going for 3D interaction,
it’s going to look a lot more like a blend of traditional MMORPGs and &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/get-started-hubs-mozilla&quot;&gt;Mozilla Hubs&lt;/a&gt;
than anything requiring an AR or VR device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discord&quot;&gt;Discord&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Discord starts marketing itself for a more professional crowd, it will
destroy Slack. It’s a far superior software product – lighter-weight, faster,
and it natively supports audio and video chat inside the platform.
Discord is a $10B+ company in the making. Perhaps controversially, I think
if users adapt to audio being more important than video, Discord is a serious competitor to Zoom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lighter-weight-applications&quot;&gt;Lighter-Weight Applications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All good gaming-adjacent software is light and fast.
Bulky software would slow down your computer and you’d lose in games!
Similarly, we’re enduring an epidemic of slow enterprise software.
Asana, JIRA, Confluence, Slack, Google Drive,
and so forth: using any of these tools is like wading through molasses.
There’s lag when you enter keystrokes, interfaces load slowly due to hundreds of API calls
under the hood, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I desperately hope that as SaaS providers try harder to provide mind-melding interfaces
between man and machine, they’ll eventually realize that a lack of speed
is the biggest barrier between the two; that the speed of response and navigation
is the single most important feature to a serious user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, we are in a strange period of adjustment as people learn to work remotely.
Users cling to representations of real life, meetings, and face-to-face Zooms.
But this is an inconvenience, and it’ll become more rare for routine work.
Audio is king in the remote world work; video – of actual humans – is less relevant,
simulacrum of a past paradigm.
On the other hand, video of &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; is of paramount importance, and the combination
of live streaming and video storage will reshape how employees work, collaborate,
and share institutional knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this world, AR and VR are somewhat counter-intuitive losers, only useful
in very niche applications. If people collaborate in some kinds of 3D spaces,
it’ll be mostly for rapid prototyping, sketching, etc.
It is clear
that collaborative, multi-user, version-controlled/historied software will succeed
in this paradigm; I expect more products like Figma and Google Docs to arrive, and
single-user software like PhotoShop to quietly leave the scene. And I pray that
this new, glorious software will be fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The fact that Clubhouse basically put a superior product/marketing skin over Ventrilo-style VoIP, put it on mobile, and then stuck a $100M price tag on it, blew my mind. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The familiarity of this sensation was pleasant until it started &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/08/21/incel.html&quot;&gt;driving me crazy&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;You might laugh at the notion of a competitive RuneScape player, but it ended up paying my way through college.
A story for another time. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For example, think about how, for virtually all but the largest companies,
 the instructions for setting up a new developer environment
are almost always flawed or out of date.
Following a screen recording of the most recent employee to get onboarded
would be a much more reliable source to draw on. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mumble_(software)&quot;&gt;Mumble&lt;/a&gt; solved it in a different way: for online 3D spaces,
like in FPS games, not only can you break up into channels, etc. but the loudness of your voice, as heard by another player,
is proportionate to your distance from them. Insofar as supporting the skeuomorphic VR experience goes,
this might be a clean way to make it feel more organic. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In 2002, my mom started a new job in finance. One day, I visited her office. As part of the grand tour, she showed me her Lotus Notes setup on her PC, and explained that she received around 400 emails a day. This baffled my eleven year old mind: “why don’t you guys just use MSN?” My friends at school used Microsoft’s Messenger for everything. Some of my friends in the US had me hopping on AOL, but either one seemed obviously better than my mom and her highly-paid colleagues shooting one-line emails through their bulky setups. Nearly twenty years later, Slack and Microsoft Teams are finally making real-time chat commonplace even among the most traditional enterprises.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Does Steve Bannon Think?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/bannon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Does Steve Bannon Think?" /><published>2020-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/bannon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/bannon.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Bannon appeared on our collective radars four years ago in August 2016, as the chief
strategist of Trump’s campaign. After Trump won, baffled voters on the left
looked to Bannon as the explanation, the &lt;em&gt;eminence grise&lt;/em&gt;, the man behind the curtain.
Bannon
was mysterious, said some fascist-sounding things, and looked unhealthy like a Hollywood villain.
It was easy to box him in as Darth Sidious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bannon lasted twelve months with Trump. He was fired in August 2017 after he
pushed the “fine people on both sides” line for addressing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unite_the_Right_rally&quot;&gt;Charlottesville&lt;/a&gt;.
He then disappeared from media coverage, as swiftly as he emerged.
I had forgotten about him until
I heard a quick line in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RmsN4_hftvI&quot;&gt;an interview&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Millennials, they’re like 19th century Russian serfs. They’re in better shape,
they have more information, they’re better dressed, but they don’t own anything.
Millennials don’t have a chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was very true. Bannon’s comments about millennials being a generation of
permanent renters, whose economic situation resembled feudalism&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; more than anything else,
struck me as succinct, correct, and hardly expressed by anyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, I was curious: surely there’s more to Bannon than the one-dimensional
media caricature, especially due to his significant impact on the success
of Trump’s election. So, I asked: &lt;strong&gt;what does Steve Bannon really think?&lt;/strong&gt;
I present my findings, as well as my reflections, below.
My view is that Bannon’s publicly advertised positions make significant sense
and are worth discussing, but Bannon himself is a suave trickster: some of his
purported views are certainly not genuine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;views&quot;&gt;Views&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon describes himself as an &lt;strong&gt;economic nationalist&lt;/strong&gt;. He believes that
  the value of &lt;em&gt;citizenship&lt;/em&gt; has suffered greatly in the past decades.
  In the US,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
  the government has allowed its obligations to its citizens to fall behind
  its obligations toward corporations. Instead of maximizing citizen quality
  of life, we are maximizing shareholder value.
  The lower-middle and working classes have lost the value of their citizenship;
  Bannon seeks to restore it.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the flip-side, Bannon believes that the world is effectively run by a
  &lt;strong&gt;permanent political class&lt;/strong&gt;: elites who never lose, and who
  have dispassionately managed the decline of the US, using
  globalization to accrue more wealth and power to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon sees the &lt;strong&gt;2008 financial crisis&lt;/strong&gt; as a key coup for these elites:
  the banks were bailed out, not a single banker was punished,
  and the losses were socialized. That’s not capitalism. Following 2008,
  under Obama, the Fed’s balance sheet expanded from $1T to $4.5T.
  That quantitative easing (read: inflation) debased the value of the USD.
  The little guy – folks who hold, and depend on cash – paid for it.
  On the other hand,
  for people that hold real estate, IP, or equities,
  the last ten years have been the greatest run in history.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon describes this state as &lt;strong&gt;neofeudalism&lt;/strong&gt;: people who don’t own
  assets are effectively serfs. Millennials especially are
  permanent renters. They do not own anything, and the system is so efficient
  that they will never own anything. The resulting economic fragility is terrible:
  people aren’t having children, can’t cover emergencies, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon views both Democrats and Republicans to blame. First for 2008,
  second for continuous &lt;strong&gt;wage suppression&lt;/strong&gt;. To Bannon, both parties seek
  to let their corporate donors extract maximum profits – for Democrats,
  that’s by (legal or illegal) immigration&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that floods the
  labor supply, for Republicans that’s by free trade deals, which
  encourage outsourcing by
  having American labor compete in price with foreign labor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon views the &lt;strong&gt;Republican party&lt;/strong&gt; as playing to its donors, and
  opposed to their voter interests.
  In the last 20 years, the Republicans have sold their voters a Koch-brothers,
  Heritage-foundation, limited-government, free-trade vision.
  It has wrecked their education and healthcare systems, and sent all the jobs
  overseas. The effects have been ruinous.
  The Republican primary candidates of 2015/2016 were the strongest
  lineup of all time; any one of them would have won most presidential
  elections. But Trump could beat them all, because voters
  aren’t falling for the traditional Republican scam and policy mumbo-jumbo anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Bannon’s view, in 2016, voters cared about &lt;strong&gt;basic sovereignty&lt;/strong&gt;.
  Immigration, trade, employment, &lt;em&gt;where’s my paycheck&lt;/em&gt;.
  Voters care about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Trump_Access_Hollywood_tape&quot;&gt;locker room talk&lt;/a&gt;,
  but that’s easily outweighed when bigger things are at stake.
  In 2016, a record number of people thought the country was on the wrong track.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
  Voters want their sovereignty, their value as citizens back.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To Bannon, core to this loss of sovereignty for everyday citizens are &lt;strong&gt;three items&lt;/strong&gt;:
  (1) the recession and subsequent inflation,
  (2) pointless, expensive wars in Iraq and Afghanistan,
  and (3) outsourcing of American manufacturing to China.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon views &lt;strong&gt;China&lt;/strong&gt; as a totalitarian, mercantilist, murderous dictatorship.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
  He believes that the CCP poses the greatest threat to all freedom-loving people
  and industrial democracies, like Nazi Germany in the 1930s, a profound threat
  to the Westphalian order and Western democracy. Westerners are not taking the
  concentration camps in Xinjiang and annexation of Hong Kong as seriously as they should.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In turn, Bannon views the shareholder-value-maximization-induced outsourcing
  of &lt;strong&gt;US manufacturing&lt;/strong&gt; to China as a gargantuan mistake, inextricably causing to America’s decline.
  It has decimated
  employment in rural America, and lost American &lt;em&gt;key competence&lt;/em&gt;
  in essential industries. Bannon believes that the CCP has been running
  economic war on the US,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Americans haven’t realized it because of our Wall Street
  interests in China. We’ve gained a little more short-term economic efficiency,
  but lost
  the sovereignty and welfare of our working class – the backbone of US society – and enabled China
  to lock down and own advanced manufacturing in perpetuity. A disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With respect to Bannon’s core issues, he views Trump as an “&lt;strong&gt;imperfect, but armor-piercing shell&lt;/strong&gt;”: under Trump,
  the loss of American manufacturing, and foreign/trade policy with China,
  have gone from being marginal issues to front-and-center.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trump&lt;/strong&gt; won because of his basic appeal to the sovereignty of his voters;
  addressing immigration and outsourcing to China as the key issues. He had planned
  to run on those issues for over a decade.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; He knew
  how to connect with working-class voters, how to rally them, and how to be accessible –
  getting rid of the political nomenclature and policy jargon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bannon points out that politics has transitioned from the field of traditional politicians
  to the field of those who truly understand media. &lt;strong&gt;Mass communications&lt;/strong&gt; is
  overwhelming and omnipresent. Trump is a master of communications, he knows how to drive the media,
  to force the media to play on his field. The media is always &lt;em&gt;reacting&lt;/em&gt;, overwhelmed
  by his incessant scandal-generation. Bannon called the strategy “flooding the zone with shit,”
  and it’s undeniably effective.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, in this era of mass media, the country is all about politics. 118 million people voted in the 2018 midterms.
  Bannon’s view is that in terms of turnout, &lt;strong&gt;democracy&lt;/strong&gt; has never been more engaged and robust.
  This view is obviously facile: the early 1900s had similar levels of political engagement,
  until the polarization boiled over and you had armed coups. Angry discourse is manageable
  until interests have diverged so far that they’re irreconcilable, at which point
  the guns come out. It doesn’t take much to figure out that polarization is harmful.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;commentary&quot;&gt;Commentary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these views were expressed between 2018 and 2020.
Taken at face value, they seem reasonable.
Bannon’s articulation of why Trump won is clearer than any pundit’s or leftist’s,
and he raises
a serious question about priorities: &lt;strong&gt;are we on the left wasting our time
arguing about pronouns when our children will get shipped to concentration camps in Xinjiang?&lt;/strong&gt;
Are we dumb for sweating the small stuff and the optics, while not paying attention to the
big issues that, on net, might be a million times more impactful?
Bannon’s mission is clear: the CCP is the great threat to Western democracy and way of life;
boycott it at all costs, bring back American technological expertise
in manufacturing, and in the process restore the welfare of the working/lower-middle classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what’s suspicious about Bannon’s “economic nationalism” is that while he’s all about
economic &lt;em&gt;problems&lt;/em&gt;, he has little to say about economic &lt;em&gt;solutions&lt;/em&gt;.
While he aggressively
blames the elites for 2008 and for shipping jobs to China, he doesn’t have anything
to say for solving neofeudalism.
Obviously bringing back jobs will help a little,
but it’s neither a full solution, nor does it address the core problem.
Neofeudalism comes out of highly efficient, industrialized
wealth inequality, which occurs because the rate of return on capital is
greater than the rate of return on labor. This was the big problem that Piketty
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital_in_the_Twenty-First_Century&quot;&gt;pointed out&lt;/a&gt; in 2013.
While Bannon points out the same problem, and says that it’s important to restore
asset ownership to the working/middle classes, he doesn’t offer any solutions for &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;.
Shouldn’t an economic nationalist have cogent economic solutions to propose?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/news/q-and-a/the-narcissism-and-ego-that-led-to-steve-bannons-arrest&quot;&gt;good journalism&lt;/a&gt;
from people who have tracked Bannon more closely than I, who claim that Bannon’s
“economic nationalism” angle is new. Immigration has been his core issue
forever. It’s central to his economic nationalism, which raises a crucial question:
is Bannon’s economic nationalism just a vehicle for advancing his hostile views
on China and immigration, which he has made the #1 and #2 priorities in his
agenda?
While there’s no debate that Bannon is a nationalist, it’s suspect
how sincere the &lt;em&gt;economic&lt;/em&gt; part of his economic nationalism is.
If it is sincere, then there’s a real question as to how well thought-through it really is,
since an overwhelming number of economists across the political spectrum view
immigration as a net economic benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, there’s something unsettling and sly about Bannon’s purported economic nationalism:
he &lt;em&gt;insists&lt;/em&gt; that he’s not an ethnic nationalist, but somehow he always ends up
very closely aligned with them. Debaters &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8AtOw-xyMo8&quot;&gt;point this out&lt;/a&gt;,
but Bannon is a slippery debater: “everyone keeps calling me a fascist,
but fascists, by definition, want bigger states! I want to deconstruct the administrative state.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Bannon plays excellent definitions-games – he is able to easily
refute the accusation by definition, and in turn totally evade the &lt;em&gt;connotation&lt;/em&gt; that
his counterparties mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bannon also always has well-prepared counterexamples
to his opponents’ predictable attacks, but he never refutes them
on an abstract level.
For example, when confronted about Breitbart’s hateful, misleading content, he skillfully outmaneuvers
his leftist interrogator by describing how Breitbart was made to subvert the
Republican establishment.
His defense of the “fine people on both sides” comment is an especially powerful example of his argumentative contortions.
Bannon’s refutations regarding allegations of his ethnic nativism leave me
with the feeling of when someone is playing games,
moving the goalposts and feeding you bullshit, but you don’t have the time in the venue
to pick them apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bannon’s insincerity is clear in his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pm5xxlajTW0&quot;&gt;Frontline&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gDqAnOyAgt4&quot;&gt;interviews&lt;/a&gt; with PBS:
he plays to the intellectual audience with the most
centrist-populist version of his beliefs, but he’s hoodwinking the viewer:
he fawns over Trump, both personally and politically.
But we know that Bannon had been &lt;em&gt;fired&lt;/em&gt; from the White House,
and had then publicly disparaged Trump, and his family, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Bannon#Quotes_in_Michael_Wolff_books&quot;&gt;Michael Wolff’s Fire and Fury&lt;/a&gt;.
In the interview, Bannon is plainly lying in attempt to preserve whatever relationship with Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, no matter how candid Bannon seems, his integrity is weak.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/national-security/senate-intelligence-committee-donald-trump-jr-jared-kushner-stephen-bannon-erik-prince/2020/08/15/a7905a84-def5-11ea-b205-ff838e15a9a6_story.html&quot;&gt;Allegations&lt;/a&gt;
have emerged that Bannon lied to congressional investors during Mueller’s Investigation.
More shockingly – and in brazen irony – he’s now even been arrested for embezzling money
from his “We Build the Wall” non-profit fundraising campaign. Convincing Americans
they need to build a border wall, privately raising money for it, then defrauding
them of those funds, takes unbelievable chutzpah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion that I’m led to is that Bannon is a special type of grifter:
sly, insincere, and self-serving.
What kind of &lt;em&gt;nationalist&lt;/em&gt; lies to congressional investigators?
He’s a deeply skilled political operative. Who knows what his true personal goals are;
but I suspect the “economic nationalist” agenda he laid out above is not the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the economic nationalist agenda Bannon advocates is coherent,
and many points seem reasonable, certainly worthy of serious discussion.
Perhaps the issue with Bannon is the same as with Trump – they find a valid platform
to run on, something that deeply resonates with the masses, and where there is
genuine need for great change – but they wrap that in their own buffoonery and grift.
It turns out that even when running on a righteous cause,
all the habits formed over the decades, the little cons and lies,
they stick. No man can escape himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Millennials’ economic situation is feudalistic since
millennials do not &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; the underlying goods they are adding value to. Just
like how the agrarian serfs were allowed to subsist on their lord’s farm land,
the lord always captured more value. Similarly, millennials do not have any
equity in the enterprises they contribute to, and their cash compensation
is usually a small minority of the economic value they create for their employers.
Like the agrarian serfs of old, millennials are locked into a life of subsistence. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bannon thinks that this issue is not just specific to the US, but across the board:
in most western nations, the value of citizenship has suffered. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Possibly to thwart accusations of racism or &lt;em&gt;ethnic&lt;/em&gt; nationalism as opposed
to economic nationalism, Bannon will often remark that those lower-middle
and working class populations are, to a significant extent, Hispanic
and African-American. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In passing, Bannon also accuses Republicans of covertly encouraging
&lt;em&gt;illegal&lt;/em&gt; immigration as cheap labor. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;While Bannon repeatedly sticks to the “right track, wrong track” anecdote
as one of the key reasons for Trump winning, I couldn’t actually find
polling that substantiated his “record high” claims. It seems like voter outlook
in 2016 was similar to that of 2008 and 1992. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Bannon clarifies that he views the Chinese people as fine like any other,
and the ruling CCP cadre as a great evil. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;See currency manipulation, stockpiling PPE while telling the rest of the world
that COVID-19 is no big deal, etc. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;His presidential ambitions became clear around 2010, when he started
writing cheques to major conservative leaders, and he published &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_to_Get_Tough&quot;&gt;Time
to Get Tough&lt;/a&gt;, a policy book. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In none of the interviews that I watched could I get a read on what exactly
Bannon understands to be the administrative state, or the precise issues with it.
Bannon paints with a broad brush. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Introduction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 is Turning Me into an Incel</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/incel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 is Turning Me into an Incel" /><published>2020-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/incel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/21/incel.html">&lt;p&gt;Nobody’s saying it, so I will: I haven’t had sex in six months, and I am losing my mind.
The mental health impacts of COVID-19 and associated long-term lockdowns are devastating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever obedient, I stayed mostly inside until early July.
I made the most of lockdown: plenty of Zoom catch-ups
with friends, reading, writing, and work.
But being inside, I stopped exercising,
and my life became overwhelmingly sedentary.
I felt this physically inactive lifestyle impact my sleep, diet,
even hormones and mood.
It wore me out. After three or four months, I had gained weight, and felt much weaker.
Crises always compound, and as if COVID-19 wasn’t enough, now I’m stuck with
body image issues, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desperate to be outside and exercise, I temporarily moved to Park City, UT
a few weeks ago.
That was fantastic for lifting my spirits, and I feel better and healthier
just getting some sunshine again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the loneliness remains. I don’t really know anyone in Utah, and though
there are now lots of tech-people camping out here, this is the worst time
imaginable for meeting new people in person, or getting included in their group
activities when you haven’t been quarantining with them already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, the lack of human contact is debilitating.
I’ve been occasionally quarantining
with friends, doing socially-distanced hangouts, etc.
but I haven’t had
a real hug in months, certainly not from a woman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a real first for me.
I’ve always been pretty physically active. Since becoming an adult,
the longest I’ve gone without sex might have been three months? The longest without
a hug or hanging out physically close in a group: maybe a few weeks? The longest
without a light touch or shaking a hand: maybe a few days?
Not only is there real psychological or physiological deprivation going on,
this experience is especially jarring because it’s so new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tens of millions of people are going through similar
difficulties right now. I wonder what the aggregate damage is.
It is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.lww.com/psychosomaticmedicine/Fulltext/2019/07000/Loneliness,_Living_Alone,_and_All_Cause_Mortality_.6.aspx&quot;&gt;well-established fact&lt;/a&gt;
that loneliness is associated with a host
of psychological and physiological issues, and generally raises morbidity.
Now we have that en masse: millions of people are currently
living lifestyles close to solitary confinement.
I certainly have been feeling my mental health degrade as I itch for regular
human contact again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, and the recent violence in Kenosha, has had me thinking about violent incels.
People like Elliot Rodger,
Kyle Rittenhouse, etc. are easy to mock.
They are dweeby, entitled losers who can’t get laid and then take it out on the world.
It’s very difficult to sympathize with them.
Obviously there are many factors of social ostracization, isolation, and radicalization,
but I feel like COVID-19 induced lockdowns
has given me a small taste of part of their existence: just sitting around,
not having in-person friends, and not having sex is &lt;em&gt;terrible&lt;/em&gt;.
If that is their existence for years-on-end, with added issues on top, then no wonder
these guys completely lose it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In turn, I worry that COVID-19 lockdowns, by the constraints they impose, will
greatly grow the incel underclass. Millions of frustrated young men, stuck at home
with nothing on their hands but &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doomscrolling&quot;&gt;doomscrolling&lt;/a&gt;
in an unbelievably politically charged time?
I couldn’t imagine a more lethal recipe for mass radicalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a directly actionable conclusion to this piece.
Tens of millions of people, myself included,
are having their lives’ first real experiences with real isolation,
and it’s awful.
Learning from it, it is unsurprising – indeed, it seems inevitable – that
incels act out the way they do, and I worry that lockdowns are adding millions
to their numbers.
In general, I’m worried that in the US, where lockdowns have been
more severe, less successful, and much longer-lasting than elsewhere,
we’ve created a recipe that is in practice only moderately effective for preventing
spread of COVID-19, but at the same time is absolutely wrecking the mental health
of those who follow them.
Economics aside, is this cure worse than the disease? What are the second-order effects going to be?
While I am certainly no COVID-19 denier, it’s nudging
me to ask whether Sweden had the right &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COVID-19_pandemic_in_Sweden&quot;&gt;approach&lt;/a&gt; after all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Nobody’s saying it, so I will: I haven’t had sex in six months, and I am losing my mind. The mental health impacts of COVID-19 and associated long-term lockdowns are devastating.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SPACs, Micro-LPs, Substack: Disintermediation at Last</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/16/spac.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SPACs, Micro-LPs, Substack: Disintermediation at Last" /><published>2020-08-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/16/spac</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/16/spac.html">&lt;p&gt;It has long been said that the internet has a power to remove
middlemen, to make opportunity more accessible, and to lower barriers to entry.
Throughout Spring/Summer 2020, we’ve seen this promise rapidly become true, at scale,
in a number of industries.
These markets have eliminated middlemen both as
gatekeepers (hurdles to access) and as distributors (aggregators of supply and demand).
As such, these markets have emerged peer-to-peer structures, greatly increasing their &lt;em&gt;resolution&lt;/em&gt;.
Let’s look at these dynamics in a few examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rolling Funds&lt;/strong&gt;: productized by AngelList, they’ve enabled
    faster, more granular raising of venture capital funds.
    They’re perfect for reputable angel investors
    to raise external funds from smaller LPs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/shl/status/1291760138571849728&quot;&gt;Sahil Lavingia&lt;/a&gt;
    and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@CindyBiSV/capitalx-is-live-rolling-fund-3d7ccfe9736a&quot;&gt;Cindy Bi&lt;/a&gt;
    are leading examples. Fundraising, especially as a first-time fund manager,
    used to take hundreds of meetings with HNWIs and funds-of-funds. Now, someone with a strong online following
    can raise hundreds of small cheques from people they have never even spoken with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corollary is an increase in the resolution of the market.
Suddenly, the set of entities you can raise from, or who are able
to invest in these markets, is no longer a pool of professional capital allocators,
but &lt;em&gt;nearly anyone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The minimum cheque size changes too, and the micro-LP emerges.
In the past, a multi-millionaire might write a $250K cheque to
Kleiner Perkins. Now, a tech worker might write twenty-five $10k cheques to smart solo GPs.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Substack&lt;/strong&gt;: not only are new writers like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-07-02/nathan-tankus-s-newsletter-subscribers-don-t-care-about-diplomas&quot;&gt;Nathan Tankus&lt;/a&gt;
     making a name for themselves (and a full-time income)
    on the newsletter subscription site, it’s also
    attracting well-established journalists like Alison Roman, Alex Kantrowitz,
    Anne Helen Petersen, and more.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
    With a couple thousand subscribers each at $5 a month,
    they’re probably making more than they were at their traditional
    institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The (editorial) gatekeeper has disappeared, and the unbundling again
increases the resolution of the market: instead of reading a journal’s opinion columns,
I might just subscribe to a number of newsletters and curate my own columns.
Instead of the author being paid by the journal,
which might not be entirely aligned with the author’s views, the author is paid directly
by their readers. In terms of authenticity, this peer-to-peer model is superior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OnlyFans&lt;/strong&gt;: People had been talking about
    “Patreon, but for porn” for years; here it is at last.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
    This is yet another way for people to capitalize on their
    online popularity, connect peer-to-peer with their audience, and cut out
    traditional gatekeepers&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and distributors. What’s particularly
    interesting about
    OnlyFans is that it is &lt;em&gt;obviously superior&lt;/em&gt; to the traditional
    distribution model: old-school porn studios used to sell videos by the view.
    As pornstars of the 2010s pioneered with private Snapchats, it turned out
    that community and (the illusions of) exclusivity and attention
    are real drivers of engagement, and, in turn, revenue. Having a presence
    on OnlyFans is massively more lucrative than being a traditional pornstar.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPACs&lt;/strong&gt;: there’s been a surge in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alexdanco.com/2020/07/24/spac-man-begins/&quot;&gt;Special Purpose Acquisition Companies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;,
    which are effectively massive blank cheques ($100M+) to highly reputable investors,
    for them to use to take private companies public. Like
    rolling funds, these are primarily vehicles betting on the reputations of
    their champions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, these trends are not entirely novel.
For example, Patreon and Bandcamp are spiritual precursors to Substack and OnlyFans.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
But the pace has picked up, and in a COVID world,
tech accelerates and we’ll  see more of these
enterprises soon. For example,
homeschooling, whether by choice or not, is
rapidly becoming more common.
I expect that someone will  &lt;em&gt;completely remake&lt;/em&gt;
online tutoring, and teachers will move from the classroom to giving 1:1 online lessons.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
In this environment, top-performing teachers will finally be paid fairly.
Similar trends are already emerging for fitness coaches and therapists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s remarkable about these trends is that they’re taking place &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; and not earlier.
In terms of pure technology or regulation, any of these companies could have been started
ten or twenty years ago. Why did it take until 2020 for simple
innovations – paid individual subscriptions, monetizing reputation –
to take off? I cannot imagine any answer other than that the internet has
finally hit a certain maturity in that it is possible for people to achieve
real reputation at scale &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; the gimmick of going viral. The online
self-published media that we have – Twitter, Medium, YouTube, etc. and all their deeply imperfect
discovery algorithms – is a mess, but it seems to be successfully giving a voice
to creators &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; enabling reasonably effective discovery/distribution of content.
Platforms to capitalize on reputations are developing as quickly as it is
actually possible to develop monetizable reputations at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The middlemen of old were gatekeepers and aggregators: content creators would apply to middlemen,
who would in turn distribute the content to an established
base of consumers. The middleman both aggregated supply and demand in the market.
The matching of the two sides of the market was coarse at best.
The technology we have now – what Twitter, Twitch, etc. ultimately represent –
are opaque interest matching engines
that enable sufficient distribution and discovery of content,
such that the supply and demand sides can actually be matched on a peer-to-peer basis at scale.
This is remarkable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Credit is due to Justin de Guzman, who succinctly captured the spirit and core point
of this essay in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/defaultalive/status/1293771885998567424&quot;&gt;single tweet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Some accredited investor rules apply. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Consequently, I wouldn’t be surprised if we start seeing even more angels
who play in Pre-Seed/Seed/Series A, and more party rounds that boot out the
traditional venture firms. I don’t think this would actually have an effect
on round pricing, but it would – very importantly – usually delay the
addition of the first investor board member to the Series A or B. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://simonowens.substack.com/p/why-high-profile-writers-choose-substack&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m baffled that no-one else had built OnlyFans previously.
It seemed the only real hurdle was compliance and getting onboarded
with payment providers. Now, someone out there is building a bootstrapped,
soon-to-be billion-dollar business, because they were willing to go through
compliance slog that no-one else could be bothered doing. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Camsites often take 30 - 50% of their streamers’ revenues! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You’d be shocked by how &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.esquire.com/lifestyle/sex/news/a43706/porn-salaries/&quot;&gt;little money&lt;/a&gt;
even the most popular traditional
pornstars make. Being on OnlyFans, or even on a regular camsite, with a
couple hundred followers, is easily a better deal (while also being much safer for the star).
Mia Khalifa – briefly one of the biggest names in porn –
made &lt;a href=&quot;https://nypost.com/2019/08/12/mia-khalifa-claims-she-made-only-12k-doing-porn/&quot;&gt;less than $12k&lt;/a&gt;
during her tenure. Being a male pornstar is basically a minimum-wage job.
Porn is a somewhat neglected industry that has been decimated by online piracy,
and doesn’t have a powerful institution like the RIAA to defend it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you’re willing to stretch the definition a little, you could argue
that Instagram influencer advertising – where a brand works directly with
the influencer – disintermediates the traditional advertising agency model.
In the context of our discussion, it’s also another good example of
building and capitalizing on reputation in one stroke. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the reason behind 1:1 specifically as opposed to “small class sizes”,
please see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloom%27s_2_sigma_problem&quot;&gt;Bloom’s Two Sigma Paper&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It has long been said that the internet has a power to remove middlemen, to make opportunity more accessible, and to lower barriers to entry. Throughout Spring/Summer 2020, we’ve seen this promise rapidly become true, at scale, in a number of industries. These markets have eliminated middlemen both as gatekeepers (hurdles to access) and as distributors (aggregators of supply and demand). As such, these markets have emerged peer-to-peer structures, greatly increasing their resolution. Let’s look at these dynamics in a few examples:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Poverty Fashionable to Millennials</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/08/poverty.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Poverty Fashionable to Millennials" /><published>2020-08-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/08/poverty</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/08/poverty.html">&lt;p&gt;There is a number of online “alternative lifestyle” movements that have been
gaining steam among millennials. They are appealing in their leanness:
do more with less. At first, they seem cute and liberating.
Scores of Instagram influencers and bloggers romanticize these
lifestyles, and their subreddits are buzzing with zealots. Key examples below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FIRE (Financial Independence, Retire Early)&lt;/strong&gt;: live frugally now to save
    money as quickly as possible, then buy a place in a low cost-of-living area
    and live (mostly) off your savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Van Life&lt;/strong&gt;: Buy a van, trick it out with a beautiful
    bed and a kitchen. Live lightly, travel the world, work remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tiny Houses&lt;/strong&gt;: Nobody needs 5,000 square feet. Why not play with constraints,
    and build a full house with the square feet of a studio?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remote Work&lt;/strong&gt;: work your high-paying-job from a low-cost-of-living area,
    save up money, and save on commuting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these lifestyles are marketed as all about freedom,
they come with major restrictions:
they are overwhelmingly for the single and childless.
Having
children is very expensive, so it’s hard to make that work with FIRE.
On the other hand, van life and tiny houses are logistically
prohibitive to having children.
By going down these routes, their adherents
will delay having kids, likely by years. That’s usually a bad trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do these lifestyles constrain, they also reflect a severe already-existing
capital constraint.
Broadly, &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of these movements are reactions
to poverty.
Living in a van, tiny house, or remotely all stem from one factor:
real estate in your preferred area (perhaps the place you call “home”)
is too expensive.
You can’t afford to buy or rent a real
place there, so you move into an Instagrammable shed,
or you move away altogether.
These lifestyles are solutions to problems
of poverty – but in making those solutions fashionable, they hide
the ugly reality underneath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, these movements romanticize and hide
the true &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Millennials#In_the_United_States&quot;&gt;generational poverty of millennials&lt;/a&gt;.
This is a generation of people who will never retire,
who may never even buy real estate of their own.
In terms of intergenerational wealth, these people are screwed.
And I would like to see that point raised and addressed,
instead of making do with solutions of desperation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There is a number of online “alternative lifestyle” movements that have been gaining steam among millennials. They are appealing in their leanness: do more with less. At first, they seem cute and liberating. Scores of Instagram influencers and bloggers romanticize these lifestyles, and their subreddits are buzzing with zealots. Key examples below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Problem of Preference Falsification in Online Dating</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/02/online-dating.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Problem of Preference Falsification in Online Dating" /><published>2020-08-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/02/online-dating</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/02/online-dating.html">&lt;p&gt;Online dating is as old as the internet.
It has exploded in popularity in recent years:
roughly &lt;a href=&quot;https://gallery.mailchimp.com/2506bda6ca9a8b7ce8b3c54b4/files/1a8cc94c-6198-4f3d-b27d-8a6060ed6c5d/Tyro_Dating_Market_Thesis_Final_For_Twitter_Pub_v2.pdf&quot;&gt;40% of straight couples now meet online&lt;/a&gt;.
It has given women more safety and choice as they participate in the dating market,
and brought down divorce rates as people date more widely and make better-informed decisions than in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these benefits are effects of online dating becoming &lt;em&gt;more common&lt;/em&gt;,
not &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt;. The recipe for online dating itself has been static since the 90s:
some pictures, a quick description of yourself and what you’re looking for in
a partner, and endless looking through other profiles. No matter whether
you’re on Hinge in 2020 or OKCupid in 2005, the structure is the same.
Only the volume is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disappointingly, innovation in online dating has mostly been marginal.
There are hundreds of dating apps, but differences are slim.
Some limit the number of daily matches, others force someone to chat first,
others yet differ in their question prompts to the users, etc. These are
micro-optimizations, but of minimal value because the existing model is
generally suboptimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s broken in the current model is that it encourages &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Preference_falsification&quot;&gt;preference falsification&lt;/a&gt;.
Normally, preference falsification is very overt – for example, when someone
lies to their friends about which political candidate they’re going to vote for.
In online dating, it’s subtle – people are usually not actively lying,
but they are (often unknowingly) misrepresenting, to themselves and to others, who they are
and what they’re looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;self-misrepresentation&quot;&gt;Self-Misrepresentation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People struggle to represent themselves accurately for two core reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Self-knowledge is hard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People try to make themselves appear as appealing as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first point is obvious, though unpleasant: lots of people go through life
doing things they hate, or simply killing time.
Few manage to ultimately find their passions. I’m sure you’ve met people
who were all about &lt;em&gt;Hobby X&lt;/em&gt;, until they dropped it one day
because it didn’t bring them joy and they were doing it for some other reason.
The second point is twisted game theory:
people are insecure in themselves, so they try to imagine what
the opposite gender might most like to see, and then to ape that.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, dating app profiles are full of wildly wishful
descriptions – &lt;em&gt;surfer, investment banker, loves reading, passionate
about sunsets&lt;/em&gt;. When you meet the real person,
it turns out they don’t care about sunsets and put that in purely as a romantic signal,
and they’ve been surfing just once a year ago but they’d sure love to try it again.
They actually spend 14 hours a day working and the remaining 2 watching
&lt;em&gt;King of the Hill&lt;/em&gt;, but they can’t write that – what would the other people on the app think?
Surely they’re only interested in surfing, sunset-loving, well-read investment bankers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These dating app bios are not just unrealistic to appeal to
potential matches, but also as constructions for the users themselves:
no-one wants to admit to themselves that
they are not living quite the life they aspire to.
Thus, when you give them a paintbrush, they paint an idealized version of themselves.
Reading is the dead giveaway:
barely anyone actually reads books, but virtually everyone says they love reading.
What they love is the idea of themselves being well-read.
Consequently, a love of reading is an extremely common bio line,
even when most people spend less than 1% of the year reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;false-preferences-about-partners&quot;&gt;False Preferences about Partners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People also struggle to accurately identify what they’re really looking for in a partner.
Again, there are two main reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Filters are necessary on dating apps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowing who is a good fit for you is another, even harder form of self-knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the enormous number of people on dating apps, having filters is
the only way to manage the quantity of potential matches.
The trouble is that
people usually have only weak priors to base those filters on.
This is especially bad for younger people, who haven’t dated very much,
and who might even fall to peer pressure dictating who they should date.
They filter hard, and consequently
never end up dating &lt;em&gt;broadly&lt;/em&gt;, which would be the only way to figure out what
kinds of people are good fits or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads into the second reason – you try to filter for people who will
be good fits, but that’s extremely difficult to know &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt;.
I’ve been personally surprised by this many times over.
Every time I thought I knew &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what kind of woman I wanted to date,
life threw me a curveball and I fell for someone totally outside that box.
By the time I was in my mid/late-20s, I learned to filter less:
romantic attraction and compatibility was actually very difficult to predict
without really getting to know the other person. I learned that common interests
didn’t mean much, whereas common &lt;em&gt;attitudes&lt;/em&gt; seemed to be the strongest predictor
of a fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But many people in the dating world aren’t having those experiences now.
They filter so specifically that they never learn who else might be out there.
I’m reminded of an acquaintance of mine – she spent the better part of three years
aggressively dating only people more successful than her – and not a single
one worked out. I was baffled that at no point did she ever consider whether her
“I am only dating CEOs” mantra was the wrong filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;outcomes-and-solutions&quot;&gt;Outcomes and Solutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dating pool is large and liquid, but the core issue is that
individual participants are hard to match because (1) they falsify who they are
and (2) they falsify what they want in their partners. This makes it
profoundly difficult to generate matches at a better-than-random rate.
Both of these issues are fundamentally due to the user having too much choice,
both in how they describe themselves and how they choose others.
Importantly, these are not really blamable faults of the users,
and it’s clear that the current generation
of dating apps will not remedy these problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am hopeful that the next generation of dating apps will solve this issue
by relying more on large-scale,
latent data: I am imagining an app where an amalgamation
of your Reddit, Spotify, Twitter, Facebook, Google Search, etc. histories
know you better than you know yourself – and that can be used to
match you perfectly with a partner.
I’ve been surprised that I haven’t
seen such technology in the wild just yet. Probably the greatest obstacle to
building a matching engine leveraging such data is that there isn’t any
good training data to use, but I would’ve expected some of the big incumbents
to use their datasets for this purpose by this point. We will see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The great tragedy in distorting the self is that it doesn’t work at all.
The real you has to come out eventually, at which point the ruse is up.
There is a great irony in users misrepresenting themselves:
they are selecting &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; people who might like their true selves.
Suppose they do match with the person that loves well-read, sunset-walking surfers,
and then their date eventually finds out – regardless of what they claim to be passionate about –
that all they really do is work, eat croissants, and watch TV. It’ll have been a waste of time. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Online dating is as old as the internet. It has exploded in popularity in recent years: roughly 40% of straight couples now meet online. It has given women more safety and choice as they participate in the dating market, and brought down divorce rates as people date more widely and make better-informed decisions than in the past.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In a GPT-3 World, Anonymity Prevents Free Speech</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/24/gpt3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In a GPT-3 World, Anonymity Prevents Free Speech" /><published>2020-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/24/gpt3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/24/gpt3.html">&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to have freedom of speech? Naively, it means that you have
the right to express ideas without fear of
governmental retaliation or censorship. But that’s not worth much in a vacuum.
Free speech is valuable when you are communicating with others: abstractly,
freedom of speech means the right to distribute information to an audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you frame freedom of speech not in terms of what comes out of your mouth,
but in terms of the interaction between yourself and another party,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; then edge cases
rapidly emerge. For example, suppose that you are on the street,
lawfully raising a protest sign supporting X.
You are hoping to persuade passers-by. The government
sends in &lt;em&gt;five hundred&lt;/em&gt; counter-protestors, peacefully raising &lt;em&gt;not X&lt;/em&gt; signs. Your
voice is drowned out in the crowd. You are unable to reach the passers-by; it’s
as if you were not there. Is this censorship? I am no constitutional lawyer,
but the effect is undeniably censorious – it is practically as if you had
been sent home by the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, I haven’t seen this type of scenario give rise to much
concern among constitutional scholars – perhaps for reasons of practicality.
Perpetually mobilizing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astroturfing&quot;&gt;astroturf&lt;/a&gt;
brigades to drown out individual voices is hardly practically feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this has dangerously changed as discourse has moved online.
The real-world constraints to astroturfing do not exist online.
With &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/ai-text-generator-gpt-3-learning-language-fitfully/&quot;&gt;GPT-3&lt;/a&gt;,
the marginal cost of distributing astroturfed propaganda online has firmly hit zero.
GPT-3 represents the newest generation of text-generating AI, and it is extremely
good – perfectly indistinguishable from a human in short form, articulate,
detailed, and capable of infinite variety
in style and tone.
Now it is actually possible for any online group discussion to be brigaded by
thousands of automated users – indistinguishable from real humans –
twisting the conversation, while drowning out the voices of real humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will become common in no time.
It’s too effective a weapon for malicious states to pass it up.
Manual online astroturfing
is already widespread. Both &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Water_Army&quot;&gt;China&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Research_Agency&quot;&gt;Russia&lt;/a&gt;
pay thousands of state employees to spread propaganda online.
As
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_interference_in_the_2016_United_States_elections&quot;&gt;Russiagate&lt;/a&gt;
and the now widespread conspiracy theories on Antivax, 5G, COVID-19, etc.
show, it’s very effective: social media platforms
have enabled divide-and-conquer strategies at unprecedented scale and granularity.
They have become a battleground for the opinions of people in the West,
and these people haven’t realized it yet.
Using fully automated, infinitely scalable tools to
infect the minds of your opponents with malicious ideas and sow discord
offers an unprecedentedly high ROI to the villains of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, we are moving into a world where bad actors can interfere with free
speech with a new form of censorship: the use of automated voices, indistinguishable
from real ones, to overpower genuine voices online, and to shape the appearance
of public discourse according to their goals. If you believe, as many scholars do,
that democratic
societies are critically reliant on your freedom to distribute information,
then this poses a severe threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The abstract problem is that on the internet, we don’t have a good way
to tell real humans from fake ones.
The current state-of-the-art tests
are CAPTCHAs with challenges that “only humans could pass”:
read the word,
click all the squares with traffic lights, and so forth.
Obviously these aren’t
going to resist automation for long.
They will be useless across the board in a few years, once general image recognition
tools are as good as some substantial minority of humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the long term,
AI will be effectively impossible to distinguish from humans
online.
The only
solution is to use what we have and they don’t – real-world identification.
A real-world ID could correspond to some set of private keys,
so you could sign your online actions to prove
their human authenticity.
You could have a large number of private keys,
so as to enable ample pseudonymity.
However, true anonymity – not leveraging real-world identity in some sense –
becomes impossible&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; without opening up the possibility of mass creation
of automated trolls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion: free speech is not just about freedom from straight-forward censorship,
but about your ability to participate in discourse without
state interference. GPT-3 marks a new generation of tools enabling states
to interfere in online discourse with unprecedented scale and persuasiveness,
enabling great damage at low cost.
It is clear that on the internet, AI will become indistinguishable from
genuine humans in the next few years. To that extent, we have to protect
our freedom of speech. It seems like
requiring real-world IDs and coupling them with public key cryptography
is the only way out, which keeps pseudonymity but loses anonymity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Losing anonymity to protect free speech is counter-intuitive and somewhat repulsive.
I believe in individual freedom as the highest ideal.
I used to think anonymity was one of the greatest values
provided by the internet. And I acknowledge that eliminating anonymity
to protect free speech comes with its own issues in the long run:
for example, a malicious government
could abuse the real-world-ID-to-private-key link to very effectively crack
down on free speech. I don’t &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; the solution I am advocating, but it’s a
difficult trade-off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;This is a common framing among constitutional scholars, for example
in the writings of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Meiklejohn&quot;&gt;Alexander Meiklejohn&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Clever leveraging of blockchain-style cryptographic protocols might actually
make it possible, at least in theory.
I am reminded of Monero’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ring_signature&quot;&gt;Ring Signatures&lt;/a&gt;
or ZCash’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-interactive_zero-knowledge_proof&quot;&gt;Non-Interactive Zero-Knowledge Proofs&lt;/a&gt;.
It’s possible that even if every real-world identity were linked to some
set of private keys, a user’s action could be computed in such a way to not reveal their identity;
similar how Monero and ZCash do not reveal identities of parties in a transaction.
For this theory to become reality, effectively the entire internet would have to run
on a blockchain,
which would be interesting.
I’ll try to explore the viability of this approach
in a future post. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What does it mean to have freedom of speech? Naively, it means that you have the right to express ideas without fear of governmental retaliation or censorship. But that’s not worth much in a vacuum. Free speech is valuable when you are communicating with others: abstractly, freedom of speech means the right to distribute information to an audience.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">America’s Starting to Look Like the Weimar Republic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/19/weimar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America's Starting to Look Like the Weimar Republic" /><published>2020-07-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/19/weimar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/19/weimar.html">&lt;p&gt;The First World War ended in late 1918 with the surrender of the German Empire.
Afterwards, the victorious Allies&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:0&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
drew up new borders and terms for post-war Europe at the Treaty of Versailles.
Key to those discussions was how to prevent Germany from inciting war in the future.
In attempt to neuter Germany,
the Allies stripped Germany of key economic areas, restricted Germany’s
military, and imposed harsh debts (reparations due) on Germany to the Allies.
This new, weak, smaller German state was the democratic Weimar Republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The humiliations of Versailles immediately festered as a nationalist movement.
Weimar was a powder keg from day one. The right
wanted to restore the autocratic German Empire, while the left
sought to establish a communist state. Both viciously blamed each other for loss of the war.
Weimar Germany was not for centrists, and the government was uniformly despised.
It would be taken over by the Nazi Party in 1933, after a short and miserable
life of perpetual assault by militias instigating coups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crucially, the Weimar Republic did not fall to polarization alone.
It was pushed over the edge by unparalleled economic hardship.
Germany was overwhelmed by the reparations it had to pay.
These debts crippled Germany’s abilities to access credit and to rebuild economically.
The only way out was for Germany to print more of its currency.
Predictably, this resulted in hyperinflation, and the economy was laid to waste.
The Allies then recognized they had put Germany in an impossible position.
They eased the reparations, and the US extended a large credit line in 1925.
Armed with capital, Germany made progress for a few years, but once the Great Depression hit in 1929,
the credit line was pulled, and Germany was once more facing economic devastation.
Millions lost their jobs, and combined with a decade-plus of political discontent,
the Nazi Party was elected into parliament. All they needed was a 19% popular vote
to get a seat at the table. The rest is history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, there is not an exact analogy between the US in 2020 and Weimar Germany.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
But some parallels come close enough for to deserve our attention.
In both cases, polarization eroded the political center,
and the Overton windows shifted dramatically.
In our case, moderates are leaving the public
discourse in droves, and those who continue to partake become inevitably more polarized.
Polarization is one of those one-way streets that is difficult to reverse course on.
I don’t see much in the way of a viable, constructive path back to normality,
especially in light
of the upcoming presidential election, which will almost certainly be inflammatory, regardless of who wins.
What if the political climate of 2020 is no aberration, but becomes the new normal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond polarization, the other great haunt of the Weimar Republic was economic turmoil.
The US also has severe debts, and the national deficit explodes year-after-year.
Crucially, the US controls the global reserve currency, and there’s no
single counterparty that can forcibly call in those debts.
As such, the US can print dollars at will, and the cost of that inflation is socialized
mostly among its creditors, i.e. the rest of the world.
This is a marvelous game to play&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; so long as your counterparties
believe that what they’re buying will hold value, but eventually
they figure out they’re getting diluted year after year. Then what?
Inflation is a game that always ends in tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I expect that in the US, we’re going to be hitting the money
printers often in the coming years. When COVID-19 began clobbering
the economy, the Federal Reserve reacted swiftly and aggressively,
doing everything it could do prop up the markets (short of directly buying up equities).
In my view, the Fed acted correctly in this situation, but it raises grave concern nonetheless:
we’ve become a one-trick-pony. The US government struggles to respond
quickly and impactfully with policy or large-scale organizational efforts.
Instead, we pump the markets to paper over the underlying destruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries like South Korea or Taiwan rapidly organized themselves and
overcame COVID-19 with relatively little disruption.
European countries were not quite as
effective, but the US response has been a disaster:
confusion, blame-games,
disobedience and irrationality all throughout the stack.
We have wound up with
both economic havoc &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a staggering number of deaths, wasting our lockdowns
while the rest of the world gets back to business.
This episode has exposed
us as a systemic house of cards – we have no state capacity at all
to stop cascading failures,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and no ability to organize effectively to meet
emergencies. We have only one tool in our toolbox that actually works – monetary policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Our country is so financialized that if
Aliens landed on planet earth, we would respond by lowering interest rates” – Anon&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two major issues with
monetary policy as our only tool: it is powerless when a non-financial, real-world
response is needed, and it debases the USD every time we use it.
The COVID episode has shown that we will likely use
this tool again in future crises. That’s a one-way-street.
As we move further down that street,
US creditholders will eventually realize that their USD holdings are,
and will for many years continue to be,
diluted in value. It will be a rude awakening for them, and in turn, for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, that scenario is a long way out.
Our economic position is still very strong.
But 2020 has made clear that there is a clear path to Weimar-style economic problems.
There is also a similarly clear path toward Weimar-like political polarization – we just
have to continue on our current track. What particularly worries me is that
we’re on these tracks already, and under 2020/COVID pressures,
there’s no easy way to turn back. Weimar ultimately fell to an exogenous shock –
the economic torpedo of the Great Depression. As COVID has shown us,
we’re systemically fragile, and not well-equipped to handle exogenous shocks. One or two more of these,
and the consequences will be ugly indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final, and perhaps most important parallel,
lies in leadership. Paul von Hindenburg, president of Weimar Germany,
was an ancient autocrat, generally uninterested in newfangled democratic
notions. While he nominally served the constitution, he cared about being King
and dealing with other Kings. In a time of great unrest, he was the
wrong pick to unify the population. Hindenburg was not “problematic”
in the sense of being dictatorial or a xenophobe – he just didn’t care much
about upholding democracy at a critical junction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Donald Trump was elected in 2016, many pundits on the left
immediately cried wolf about him having dictatorial ambitions or being a xenophobe.
In retrospect, those concerns came at the neglect of a very important
question: &lt;em&gt;not what Trump does next, but who comes next&lt;/em&gt;.
The damage that Hindenburg did was less in the course of his term,
but as it concluded: as a weak, old, divisive leader with a marginal-at-best
interest in democracy, he paved the way for a brash group of power-grabbers
who knew how to speak to the everyman. Those were the Nazis. In a similar
vein, I’m not worried by accusations of Trump being ill-willed, but rather
by him paving the way for more malicious actors in future years.
A neglected democracy can neither defend itself,
nor display its value proposition, in full force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:0&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Britain, France, Italy, Russia, USA &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:0&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;There are many key differences, like the American public not having a strong irredentist
sentiment – even though the clamoring over immigration comes close as a territorial
grievance. Current militia movements in the US, even given the current conflicts in Portland,
pale against those of the 1920s, where there were tens of thousands of militiamen
shedding blood in the streets. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Incidentally, this is why I’ve been long S&amp;amp;P since late 2016 – it was clear to me
that Trump would do &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; in his power to prop up the markets. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;One of the things that’s so fascinating about our response to COVID is
that it laid bare all the ways in which our system has fragile inter-dependencies:
for example,
since there is effectively no public healthcare (it is employer-based),
people have to go to work, otherwise they would get fired and lose their healthcare.
The workplace, of course, is a prime spot to spread disease.
There are no easy fixes when safety valves, stopgaps, and fallbacks
are lacking throughout the entire system. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;I can’t find the exact source for this statement insofar as I recall it,
but &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/itsmicnguyen/status/1239992374203420674&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; tweet comes close. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The First World War ended in late 1918 with the surrender of the German Empire. Afterwards, the victorious Allies[^0] drew up new borders and terms for post-war Europe at the Treaty of Versailles. Key to those discussions was how to prevent Germany from inciting war in the future. In attempt to neuter Germany, the Allies stripped Germany of key economic areas, restricted Germany’s military, and imposed harsh debts (reparations due) on Germany to the Allies. This new, weak, smaller German state was the democratic Weimar Republic.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No More Shampoo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/04/shampoo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No More Shampoo" /><published>2020-07-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-07-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/04/shampoo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/04/shampoo.html">&lt;p&gt;In December 2019, my girlfriend mentioned that my hair smelled unusually good.
What was I doing differently? Nothing, I thought. Everything was just as always.
Except that I had run out of shampoo a few weeks prior, and hadn’t noticed until then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a teen, I used plenty of hair products. Gels were cool in the early 2000s,
and sculpting wax remained in vogue even afterwards.
Such products require washing out at the end of the day, otherwise it feels gross,
and (ironically) would make your hair
unwieldy afterwards. By the time I got to college, I was used to shampooing my hair
most days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, my college roommate suffered from severe male pattern balding
as he hit his early 20s, and he made that suffering a core piece of his identity.
Fear is contagious, so
I quit hair products, and began to exclusively
use the most scalp-friendly shampoo I could find, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kiehls.com/hair/shampoos/amino-acid-shampoo/247.html&quot;&gt;Kiehl’s Amino Acid Shampoo&lt;/a&gt;.
I reduced my shampooing to twice a week, and was careful not to use too much.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
My hair was fine and usually short, so that was perfectly sufficient for the most part
of the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was until I ran out in mid-November 2019. I hadn’t even noticed, and my girlfriend
had complimented me on my hair, so I thought I might as well keep going.
I had previously read about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/NoPoo/&quot;&gt;NoPoo Movement&lt;/a&gt; – people
washing their hair with stuff like olive oil or quitting shampoo altogether –
and that had been intriguing.
Ever since I tried anti-dandruff shampoo and it immediately gave me dandruff,
I had a hunch that shampoo might just be a scam. I was ready to give NoPoo a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven or eight months later, I still haven’t used shampoo or conditioner once.
I rinse it with warm water every morning when I shower, give it a quick rub
with a towel, brush it, and I’m off to the races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results are fantastic. My hair is silky smooth, looks and feels clean,
and a slight build-up of natural oils makes it easy to form. If I run my hand
through my hair to push it back, it stays (mostly) in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping my hair in place had been a real
frustration with a frequent shampooing routine: my hair would be so light
and dry that it was impossible to rule – I would &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to use a product
to keep it from dangling into my forehead, or I’d have to get haircuts to specifically
trim the unruly parts that would stick out. Reducing shampoo – and eventually eliminating it – made it
possible to actually get somewhere combing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this time – thanks to COVID-19 – I haven’t had a haircut, so my hair
is now also longer than usual. (I feel like a stand-in from an ’80s movie.)
It’s easy to go NoPoo when you have short hair, because
there’s ultimately little hair to accumulate lots of grease and oil.
The threat of greasy hair is more severe when your hair is longer,
which is why I suspect it’s mostly men&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; who opt to abandon shampoo.
For me, it ended up fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abandoning shampoo works because it restores the natural
balance of oils on your scalp. Most shampoos are effectively like dish soap:
they aggressively remove grease from your head. That dries out your scalp,
so – no surprise – you produce &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; oils to compensate. That makes your hair
greasy in short order, so you then have to shampoo again. It’s even more extreme
if you apply additional grease in form of hair products.
Like a ketamine-cocaine bender, you are net balanced
while swinging between extremes. That’s not great.
Consequently, most people report that the toughest thing about abandoning shampoo
is the first two or three weeks, while your hair becomes quite greasy as your
scalp readjusts how much oil it needs to produce. I was fortunate that
during that time, I had been too busy to notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to get a haircut soon as COVID wraps up, but I don’t see myself
using shampoo again in the course of my everyday life. It might be worth
making exceptions if I somehow get really dirty in nature or doing some DIY stuff,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
but for the most part it just seems unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;While previously I would liberally use big globs of shampoo,
I was surprised to find that just a teaspoon-full of Kiehl’s
would suffice. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;That’s my anecdotal impression, not based on any rigorous quantitative evidence. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;I suspect that the initial popularity of shampoo came because people used to
get much dirtier than today. People would work on their cars, on their homes,
in their gardens, and actually get covered in physical dirt. That’s quite rare
nowadays. For apartment-dwelling millennials, there’s no DIY or repair work,
and certainly no gardening. I spend most of my time indoors. For people
like me who rarely/never get dirty in the first place, shampoo
seems like a relic from another time. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In December 2019, my girlfriend mentioned that my hair smelled unusually good. What was I doing differently? Nothing, I thought. Everything was just as always. Except that I had run out of shampoo a few weeks prior, and hadn’t noticed until then.</summary></entry></feed>