<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-01T16:42:15-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jay Riverlong</title><subtitle>Jay Riverlong's personal website. Essays and thoughts.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">No More Coffee</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/30/coffee.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No More Coffee" /><published>2020-06-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/30/coffee</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/30/coffee.html">&lt;p&gt;I never identified as a coffee snob or someone with a serious habit –
like everyone else, I made lots of self-deprecating jokes about how much coffee I drank –
until one day I realized that I had been drinking more coffee than anyone else I knew for the past fifteen years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started drinking coffee in high school. I would stay up all night competitively playing video games,
and then head to school on two or three hours of sleep. If I tried to attend class,
I would immediately pass out on my desk. There was a coffee machine in the cafeteria,
where I would solve that problem by purchasing a cup of scalding-hot black coffee for fifty cents.
It was shitty coffee, and I hated the flavor. But I needed it, and took the bitterness as
fair punishment for not sleeping.
That cup got me
wired – the caffeine rush would electrify my body, and
my hand would shake erratic, two-inch tall letters out of my Pilot V5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two hours later, I’d get another cup, and that would last me into the early afternoon.
I’d crash and fall asleep in class at 1:50pm, like clockwork. I’d get another cup at 2:00pm
between classes, to carry me through the rest of the day.
When I took my finals before graduating, the principal sent out a grade-wide
complaint that too many coffee cups got littered outside the exam rooms. They were all mine.
My #1 concern in high school was
dying of a heart attack due to my completely insane sleep and caffeine habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow I survived high school. My sleep patterns would,
over the course of the years, very slowly approach those of a normal person,
but coffee stuck. I would drink it to help stay up late, or to wake me up
after a short night. When things got really urgent I’d supplement with some Red Bull.
My tastes advanced a little bit: I quit the punitive straight black coffee,
and experimented with extravagances like sugar and milk. As I started to work
internships near Starbuckses, I would get vanilla-hazelnut lattes, and my
coffee runs were known for their consistency and punctuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After college and graduate school, things kicked up a notch. Lots of people
define their persona by their love of coffee, and I chose to be one of those.
I drank coffee – lattes, in particular – religiously. My first business card’s title read &lt;em&gt;Caffeine Fiend&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
I systematically sampled nearly every single cafe in San Francisco.
Weirdly, I knew I didn’t really love lattes. I liked them, but a latte can ultimately only be so good.
They were a habit, something I’d been doing for a long time, and had made
part of my persona.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Besides, I needed the kick. I realized that coffee
was useful in technical, creative work not because it increases wakefulness,
but because it increases &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt;. I had a latte machine in the office and a company to build,
so at some point I hit ten cups a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter March 2020. I had moved offices – no more free coffee – and was
spending more on cinnamon lattes than some people spend on their mortgage.
I was more cautious than most about COVID-19, and started isolating myself
in early March. Being a coffee addict but not a true aficionado, I did not own
anything in the way of a coffee machine. (I have never made much use of my kitchen.)
I had no way to make coffee at home,
and due to COVID I wasn’t in the mood to go out shopping. Almost four months later,
I still haven’t had any coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Losing coffee was unpleasant at first.
Abandoning a ritual can make the rest of the day feel weirdly incomplete.
But I soon stopped missing or thinking about it.
My quality of life had improved.
With coffee, the regular motions of the day become exaggerated – there would be spikes of focus
and the feeling of productivity&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,
but there would also be caffeine crashes every four hours.
The days that I used caffeine to push myself too far would invariably end in long headaches.
I often felt very seriously drained at the end of the workday, and couldn’t do anything in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last four months, without coffee, have been much better.
No headaches. No crashes.
Consequently – and ironically – I’m now probably &lt;em&gt;more awake&lt;/em&gt; on average throughout the day.
I’ve been very surprised by how little I actually needed the caffeine, even in the morning after a short night.
Thus, I’m not sure how much value caffeine actually provided me over the past few working
years. I had so much of it that the beneficial effects certainly wore off (I would
even drink coffee right before going to sleep). However, the downsides of
coffee – trading in later energy to have more focus now, the drain and crash later in the day –
never wore off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, as COVID wraps up and things go back to normal,
I don’t feel the need
to pick up coffee again. Maybe I’ll try decaf for the
pleasure of an evening latte, but I’m happy to kick the habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Cringe, I know. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;For me, this triggered careful introspection about whether I
really derived pleasure from the things I claimed to like, or whether those
claims were really just signaling about the person I would like to be, rather than who I actually am. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The jury is still out on how much more productive I &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; was, if at all. I wonder if there’s
some counter-intuitive effect by which access to coffee encourages worse sleep
(because you can stay up late and then just drink coffee when you’re tired)
which leaves you less productive overall. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I never identified as a coffee snob or someone with a serious habit – like everyone else, I made lots of self-deprecating jokes about how much coffee I drank – until one day I realized that I had been drinking more coffee than anyone else I knew for the past fifteen years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cancel Culture in 1974</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/28/cancel-culture.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cancel Culture in 1974" /><published>2020-06-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/28/cancel-culture</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/28/cancel-culture.html">&lt;p&gt;In 2008, Facebook was the hot new thing, and social media had &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; started rising.
One of my high-school classes was about trying to understand that shift better.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
We read about past problems with mass media,
and thought about how they might manifest in new media. To that end,
we read a German novel called &lt;em&gt;The Lost Honor of Katharina Blum&lt;/em&gt;
by Heinrich Böll. In recent years, with social media-induced cancel culture
becoming a hot issue, that novel has been on my mind frequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Katharina is a 27-year old housekeeper. She’s frugal, earnest, and hard-working – a model citizen.
    One evening, she meets a man named Ludwig at a party,
    and sleeps with him. Next day, the police knocks on her door: he’s a known
    communist terrorist, and suspected for robbery and murder. Katharina is taken in for
    questioning, and released.
    &lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;br /&gt;
    This episode is observed by a reporter for the
    tabloid NEWS. The reporter inquires with neighbors, stretches any statements,
    and publishes a piece
    declaring Katharina to be a gold-digging communist criminal, the depraved bride of a murderous terrorist.
    Katharina
    is swiftly excluded from society and receives death threats. Under the onslaught
    of harassment, her hospitalized mother dies from stress.
    &lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;br /&gt;
    In the meantime,
    Ludwig is found to have committed no robbery or murder, but
    by then, the campaign against Katharina has become its own force.
    One sympathizer argues that the actual facts are good, and that other
    newspapers are reporting the facts, but – as Katharina points out through her sobs –
    it doesn’t matter, because &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; reads the NEWS.
    &lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;br /&gt;
    For no fault of her own, Katharina’s life is in shambles:
    her career is over, and her friends distance themselves for self-preservation.
    In desperation, she tries to meet with the reporter who has been hounding her.
    The reporter tries to extort her for sex, whereupon she shoots him.
    Remorseless, she turns herself in to the police for justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 70s were a heyday for tabloid newspapers. Printing any scandal,
no matter how thin the facts, the tabloids were like the clickbait
outrage mills of today. Their reach was wide and deep: the NEWS of the novel
was a depiction in all but name of the leading tabloid in Germany, BILD,
which printed six million copies every day, purchased by one in ten Germans.
To be depicted unfavorably in BILD was social execution, and – as a paper dealing primarily in outrage and gossip –
BILD executed plenty. Capricious and careless, their reporters had the power to ruin lives
effectively at random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounds a lot like getting cancelled: for effectively no fault of your own,
the outrage mob, whether online or offline, can &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newspeak#Vocabulary&quot;&gt;unperson&lt;/a&gt;
you.
While today’s media are global and more plentiful, it’s not clear that
there’s been a net change in impact.
Getting smeared by your local tabloid was just as radioactive as is getting smeared on Reddit,
a career-ender all the same.
Further, even though traditional, local media has a much smaller reach than global media,
its local reach is what really matters to the person affected.
Local media has a much deeper local reach,
and a much greater capacity to “investigate” and report locally.
While modern media operate at much greater scale, it also carries a dilutive effect.
Net-net, people have always been getting disgraced, and
I don’t think it’s much likelier now than it was in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, cancel culture is an example of a pattern I like to call &lt;em&gt;there’s nothing new under the sun&lt;/em&gt;:
there are always scary changes between generations, but usually
they are just new manifestations of issues as old as time. For example,
many people today
complain that the young spend less time on necessary schoolwork than the
previous generation. But even Socrates said the exact same thing. In many domains,
perceptions of progress have been pessimistic since antiquity – perhaps because
memories of times past are always rose-colored by nostalgia – but reality works out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If today’s severity and randomness of cancel culture is not actually new,
is it different in any important respects? Today’s cancel culture
is one of escalating purity tests: born out of the more punitive contingents on the left,
it’s not enough to not be a racist or a sexist, but one must take stronger,
more condemnatory views, which function as powerful in-group signals.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Cancel culture is thus somewhat performative, and strongly ideologically motivated –
some people are likening it to the witch hunts for communists in the 50s under
Joseph McCarthy. The left is in a curious, self-damaging position, where
lots of center-leaning moderates – who are genuine progressives –
are not meeting the ideological standards of those further left, which functions
to their exclusion, thereby weakening the left overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that bad? Yes, probably. While I view the aims of social justice
as largely correct and well-intentioned, cancel culture seems to produce
unnecessary collateral damage that hurts its own cause.
It both fragments the left – infighting
over purity is a devastating waste in a time beset by serious problems
requiring collective action – and it is unfair to the people it ultimately
affects. But is any of this new? I don’t think it is. It’s the same old patterns
and motivations under new cover.
Thus, like everyone else, we acknowledge cancel culture as a trend,
but unlike everyone else, we see it as a trend that is very &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt;.
In turn, the question we ask about is radically different:
while everyone else asks “how has technology given rise to cancel culture”,
we know that it hasn’t, and instead ask “how can we use technology to mitigate cancel culture?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In retrospect, this was &lt;em&gt;remarkably&lt;/em&gt; progressive and prescient for a school.
The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_Spring&quot;&gt;Arab Spring&lt;/a&gt; protests hadn’t
even happened yet, and I think few people really understood at the time
how large the media shifts in years to come would be. My teacher,
who was a journalist by training, had a more forward-looking attitude than most. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;This kind of pattern is very well-known. It’s captured in many texts across
psychology and sociology, for example in Freud’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Narcissism_of_small_differences&quot;&gt;Narcissism of Small Differences&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In 2008, Facebook was the hot new thing, and social media had just started rising. One of my high-school classes was about trying to understand that shift better.[^1] We read about past problems with mass media, and thought about how they might manifest in new media. To that end, we read a German novel called The Lost Honor of Katharina Blum by Heinrich Böll. In recent years, with social media-induced cancel culture becoming a hot issue, that novel has been on my mind frequently.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Once Upon a Time in Hollywood: Tarantino’s Greatest Film</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/27/tarantino.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Once Upon a Time in Hollywood: Tarantino's Greatest Film" /><published>2020-06-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/27/tarantino</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/27/tarantino.html">&lt;p&gt;I was surprised when I first saw &lt;em&gt;Once Upon a Time in Hollywood&lt;/em&gt;.
That was it? After &lt;em&gt;Kill Bill&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Django Unchained&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Inglourious Basterds&lt;/em&gt;,
the ending felt like the action was just beginning – where’s the endless, outrageous,
cartoon-like violence Tarantino is known for? Where’s Charles Manson? And was
that really two hours and forty minutes? Where’s the second half of the movie?
&lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; had dazzled me with its visuals, and
transported me into an electric fairytale land where I didn’t feel the hours pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; is a tender, deeply affectionate dance with a magical moment in time.
The summer of ‘69 was a &lt;em&gt;graduation&lt;/em&gt; – a changing of the guards from the
film generation of the 50s to the new kids on the block, the hippie movement
coming to an end with the never-to-be-repeated crescendo of Woodstock,
and Hollywood losing its innocence with the Manson murders. Graduation
is always a bittersweet moment, where a long-unified cohort
disperses, like a great wave rising to its peak just before
it crashes on the rocks, shattering into a billion little pieces.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Soon, the soft, psychedelic sounds of the Beatles and Beach Boys would give way
to Led Zeppelin, and clean-cut TV westerns of Rick Dalton’s style would
be replaced by gritty images of Vietnam. But not yet. This is their swan song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end, &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; is Tarantino’s most thoughtful work.
In his other movies, the protagonists are larger-than-life figures taking epic acts of vengeance,
brimming with delightfully self-righteous monologues.
By contrast, &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt;’s
Rick Dalton is a bit of an everyman, a B-movie actor coming to terms
with his own fading career,
realizing that time is now working against him,
and that he will never become &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; the way
some of his earlier colleagues did, even if perhaps more by luck than skill.
Eclipsed by younger talent, he is disoriented in
a world that has changed around him. He suffers through his pains,
and rises to new heights in the end.
That act, to face his own inadequacies and carry on, makes him a hero
in an ordinary, relatable way.
He’s no Great (Anti-)Hero
like The Bride, Django, or Jules Winnfield – but he’s a real human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mirror image of Rick is his best pal, Cliff Booth.
It’s no coincidence that he wears
a &lt;em&gt;Champion&lt;/em&gt; t-shirt throughout the film: he is courageous,
strong, infinitely confident, and the center of female attention.
He embodies everything that was &lt;em&gt;cool&lt;/em&gt; about masculinity in the 60s.
His stage presence is captivating, and it’s hard not to be swept up by him.
Men want to be him, women want to have him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar, but opposite, is Sharon Tate, the final member of the triad.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
We see her from two different angles.
First, we accompany her on the ordinary errands of her day, like with Cliff.
In that course, we fall in love with her effortless grace, seeing
her radiant beauty, optimism, and lightness close-up. Second,
we see Tate as just another person in the crowd. At the Playboy Mansion,
she dances, just for herself, among hundreds of others – but to the viewer,
she stands out. At every crowded party or nightclub, there’s always &lt;em&gt;someone&lt;/em&gt; that
draws your attention. She is that person.
No matter
how objectively small her part in a scene, she is always
the subject of the viewer’s attention.
There’s a special kind of voyeurism there, since Tate
doesn’t have much in the way of dialogue – or, strictly speaking, any impact
on plot.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Tate captures us with her &lt;em&gt;atmosphere&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; is
entirely a work of atmosphere. She is the soul of the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond soul, &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; also has spark.
I was surprised not to see sex come up more in other critics’ reviews:
&lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; is deeply charged with attraction. Though there’s no
overt love story, the movie is full of reminders that it’s LA in 1969,
and everyone is riding
high on the wave of sexual freedom. &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; is studded with beautiful people,
and countless suggestive shots create an  undercurrent of sexual charge
that only adds to &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt;’s electric feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; is all about feeling. As a film, it is almost entirely a sensual experience.
Some people &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/moviescirclejerk/comments/hfexhk/me_when_i_say_jackie_brown_is_tarantinos_best_film/fvye4wu/&quot;&gt;say&lt;/a&gt;
that it’s all flavor and no substance, but that’s precisely the point: some of the
best Michelin-starred meals are all flavor, because that’s what
ultimately really impacts the audience. In that vein,
&lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; is an audiovisual masterpiece. Not only is it generally shot beautifully
with impeccable detail, but it delivers scenes that are both transportive and
synesthetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key to that &lt;em&gt;transportation&lt;/em&gt;, to the immersion of the viewer, is the soundtrack.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There’s a
clever trick here: much of the movie is set in cars, while driving.
The accompanying music is credibly on the radio, and the fact that we can hear it
makes us feel like we’re really there, in the car with the characters. The pairing
of songs to scenes is, of course, perfect – just consider when
Cliff first sees Pussycat. Those twenty seconds of flirting looks exchanged
while &lt;em&gt;Mrs. Robinson&lt;/em&gt; plays contain more tension and intrigue than some entire films.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt;, Tarantino masters that heavily multisensory &lt;em&gt;short scene&lt;/em&gt;, where
an unbelievable amount of audiovisual detail and stimulus is packed into a few
seconds. The scene where Cliff feeds his dog while making dinner and
cracking open a beer, feels so extremely high-resolution in every sense –
every bubble in the beer is crisp and pristine, nothing is blurred, and
the audio of every iota of the process is so clear that it could be ASMR.
By its sheer amount of lush detail, this minute-long scene could be a short film.
Watching it blew my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I do not know what it means for a movie to be
&lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;, but I know how it makes me feel,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; is a masterpiece
of eliciting feeling through mood and atmosphere. As a sensual experience,
&lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; is spectacular.
We are passengers in Tarantino’s car,
and he’s taking us on
the most incredible ride down the Boulevard,
sharing all his favorite sights and sensations.
Through twists and turns,
we look out the window,
dazzled the whole way,
trying to take in all the scenery’s rich detail,
pulled in by every one of our senses as we fly by.
Others have called the film a love letter to Hollywood,
to the 60s, a valentine for Tate. The truest love letters
are not works of cold analysis, but works of pure emotion. And that is
&lt;em&gt;Once Upon a Time in Hollywood&lt;/em&gt;: so much loving detail poured in by Tarantino,
to share with us a wonderful ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;A friend used this metaphor back when we were graduating from
high school. It stuck. &lt;em&gt;Graduation&lt;/em&gt; is a rare and wonderful feeling. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Rick, Cliff, and Sharon form a triple in that they each take a different
part of a “main character”:
nominally, the movie is about Rick Dalton. He’s the one with a real
character development arc, a well-rounded figure with plenty of flaws
and trials to overcome. He gets all the dialogue.
However, Rick isn’t the one we, as an audience,
really care about or root for: that’s Cliff Booth, the real champion of the story.
Cliff’s presence pumps us up, we love watching him act cool and kick ass.
He’s a simple character, but he gets the most screen time.
But neither Cliff nor Rick are the real core of the movie,
the focus is off-center: though she doesn’t have
much screentime or dialogue, the movie is about, and for, Sharon Tate.
It wouldn’t exist without her. She is &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt;’s aesthetic core. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;That’s insofar as there is a plot – everything that happens in the movie happens
regardless of Tate’s actions, except for the very end, where her disembodied
voice finally admits Dalton to her ranks.
&lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; is more a movie of vignettes than led by
a traditional plot, but that’s not a weakness: it is a pure audiovisual &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt;.
It communicates an immense beauty and richness of feeling, the way that a
really strong piece of instrumental music doesn’t need lyrics –
in fact, lyrics would only be a distraction – to move the listener. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;When Tarantino plays with a concept for a new movie, he starts by flipping through
his &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.discogs.com/en/quentin-tarantino-is-as-proud-of-his-soundtracks-as-he-is-of-his-films/&quot;&gt;record collection&lt;/a&gt;,
trying to find the soundtrack for a story. As he narrows in on the music, he then
carefully marries tunes to characters and plot-points. &lt;em&gt;Hollywood&lt;/em&gt; excels as an
&lt;em&gt;audio&lt;/em&gt;visual experience. Music was a cultural pillar of the late ’60s,
and Tarantino takes us on a wonderful musical journey. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;I take a somewhat contrarian and unpopular position in the arts,
in that I consider myself an artistic hedonist. I am a sucker for stimulus.
Unlike most critics,
I care little about meaning, commentary, reference, or clever flourishes –
I care about the sensation that a work evokes in its audience.
To me, film, music, and the visual arts are first and foremost sensual
experiences, and I am most rapt by work that dazzles its audience with
original spectacle. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I was surprised when I first saw Once Upon a Time in Hollywood. That was it? After Kill Bill, Django Unchained, and Inglourious Basterds, the ending felt like the action was just beginning – where’s the endless, outrageous, cartoon-like violence Tarantino is known for? Where’s Charles Manson? And was that really two hours and forty minutes? Where’s the second half of the movie? Hollywood had dazzled me with its visuals, and transported me into an electric fairytale land where I didn’t feel the hours pass.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Superstimulus in 2020</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/24/superstimulus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Superstimulus in 2020" /><published>2020-06-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/24/superstimulus</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/24/superstimulus.html">&lt;p&gt;During these COVID-19 stay-at-home days, I’ve watched a lot of movies, old and new.
Many cultural shifts are caught on film over the decades,
but I’ve been most surprised by the change in &lt;em&gt;pacing&lt;/em&gt;.
In films from the 70s, individual scenes are long. They’re filled
with pensive pauses and close-ups, and you get entire minute-long shots of
pure framing and mood-setting.
Movies from recent years have fast cuts, with not a single moment wasted.
A modern feature-length film feels much &lt;em&gt;denser&lt;/em&gt; in the sheer amount of content
and audiovisual spectacle it gives to the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s another density shift between modern movies and YouTube videos.
Nowadays, a single, well-made ten or twenty-minute video packs as much content and excitement
as a full movie. I’m not much of a YouTube fan at all, but watching indie vloggers
over the past few weeks of quarantine has been infinitely more engaging than
primetime television of old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core dynamic behind this surge in stimulating content is the
massive, decentralized (democratic?) nature of social media.
YouTube videos, for example, have not always been this exciting.
But they’re quick to make
in huge numbers and get feedback on, so they’ve been much faster to evolve than full movies.
Millions of creators
have iterated on their short-form content in Darwinian
competition for our attention, so we’ve iterated our way to entertainment where even the mundane stuff
packs one hell of a punch. It’s like seeing an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_algorithm&quot;&gt;evolutionary algorithm&lt;/a&gt; optimize
for our eyeballs in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome of this rapid evolution is nowhere more apparent than on Instagram.
Millions of beautiful women,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; competing for likes and followers,
have been iterating towards optimally attractive pictures.
And they’re putting past generations to shame.
I remember seeing the tabloids of the late 1990s and early 2000s.
The sex symbols of the time got just as much interest as those today,
but the difference in photo quality or attractiveness is enormous.
Looking at shoots of major models from then
– the Spice Girls, Madonna, Britney Spears, and so forth,
but to viewers in 2020, those photos look mostly unremarkable.
Going back further, would a &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.pinimg.com/736x/67/ae/1d/67ae1d94014e0e2e1188f0c5db13d39b.jpg&quot;&gt;swimsuit photo&lt;/a&gt;
of Marilyn Monroe, &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; most famous
sexual icon of all time, even catch your attention scrolling through Instagram? Not mine, frankly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has changed? After all, being attractive has always been important.
While Marilyn Monroe’s time was more conservative,
the 90s were culturally similarly liberal to today. How are today’s Instagram
influencers – tens of thousands of them – publishing photos that are
in a complete different league, way beyond the top-100 supermodels of the 1990s?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has happened is simple: the iPhone has armed
hundreds of millions of women with a studio-quality instant camera, making it possible
to shoot, share, and receive feedback on hundreds of photos in a single day.
Along the way, once-professional tools like photo filters and lighting have been commoditized.
Consequently, the barrier to entry for competition has been obliterated, and in the free
market of attention, this competition among millions upon millions of women
globally, in rapid iteration over billions of photos, has yielded tens of thousands
of Instagram models that regularly produce photos that are
lightyears better than anything made even ten years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, what is happening in aggregate is an evolutionary process:
broadly, Instagram influencers, who are mostly women, are optimizing their pictures to draw attention, mostly from men
(and as a corollary, from other women who look up to them).
In this optimization, they are approaching
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supernormal_stimulus&quot;&gt;superstimulus&lt;/a&gt; –
they’re implicitly identifying the features that men most respond to, then slightly exaggerate them.
If the reception is positive, then that becomes the new baseline, and you rinse and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This iteration toward superstimuli is &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;/em&gt; that our cravings can be exploited in any way. In entertainment, food,
news, porn, drugs – they are domains of free-market competition
for consumers’ attention and favor, with marginal trial-and-error experiments
every day, ever inching their way to getting our neurons to fire as powerfully
as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does this lead? It gave us Vine and TikTok, for a start. If you had
told someone in the 80s or 90s that 6-30 second videos would take the
entertainment world by storm, they would’ve been surprised to say the least.
That’s less time than in the setup for a joke. It’s shorter than a standard TV ad.
And we’re quite clearly
not hitting any resistance in terms of minimum timespan yet – entertainment can and will
become more compressed, though I struggle to imagine what that will actually look or feel like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that social media will continue to squeeze out the traditional
media institutions. There are two reasons for this: first, the barriers to
entry are eroding rapidly. Distribution has become commoditized, and the institutions no
longer function as gatekeepers. Tools once limited to corporations – special effects,
lighting, even CGI – have similarly become accessible to budding creatives. Secondly, and more importantly,
in social media, you have &lt;em&gt;billions&lt;/em&gt; of creators/consumers. As a decentralized
mass in free-market competition, they iterate every day, and our entertainment
evolves to become ever more enticing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the corporate, traditional side, we have Quibi.
The folks at Quibi broadly had the right idea from looking at YouTube, Vine, Snap Stories, TikTok, etc. –
people want shorter, more compelling, denser content.
Consumers just skip and fast-forward through TV shows,
sometimes even through YouTube videos.
There’s a lot of hunger for densely packed bite-size episodic entertainment,
and Quibi was the first real institutional attempt to satisfy that public craving.
But Quibi fell short – you can speak about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vulture.com/2020/05/jeffrey-katzenberg-quibi-failure-coronavirus.html&quot;&gt;various reasons&lt;/a&gt;
for its failure, but a key issue is that the content ultimately wasn’t compelling.
And I expect that institutionally-directed (“centrally planned”) content can simply never be as good
as content that arises from mass Darwinian competition (“free market”). I wouldn’t be surprised
if traditional film and television studios subside over the next fifteen years,
as independent creators become both far more empowered and far greater in numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Foster Wallace anticipated the ultimate conclusion of this trend in his 1996 novel
&lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt;, a novel
most generally about how people seek entertainment (stimulation) in their lives.
While substance abuse (perhaps the most obvious form of superstimulus exploitation) features
heavily, the driving force in the novel is a film: the titular
&lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt; is a movie so perfectly entertaining that a viewer will be
enthralled by it, watching it on repeat, unable to eat or drink until they die.
That seems like a far cry from where we are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, on a macroscopic level, you could argue that we’re already there:
we live in a society of political infotainment, where everyone
is permanently outraged – or very well entertained.
Despite their deep interest in the current affairs,
actual engagement (voter turnout, passed legislation, etc.) is low.
Everyone loves the stimulus and the simulacrum of the real thing,
but no-one engages the actual substance. And we’re in dire straits as a consequence.
In the political arena, as a public body, you could very well claim that we are
perfectly enthralled, and it’s killing us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s a counterpoint. This trend matches a pattern,
where fears of change between one generation and the next
always seem new and pressing, but those changes actually have been going on &lt;em&gt;forever&lt;/em&gt;.
For example, many people today might complain that the young have worse manners
and spend less time on schoolwork than the previous generation. But that complaint
has been uniformly raised by every generation since the days of Socrates. Fears
that the modern generation is too engaged in new, dubious media and not enough in the
valuable media of old, has also been raised every year since antiquity.
Maybe the true pattern is that as we
optimize in a direction, approaching some superstimulus,
the underlying goalposts change,
and we never quite fall into the Siren Song trap of Infinite Jest, but we keep on moving.
Time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;I’m writing this from a heterosexual male point-of-view. I have no doubt
that the mechanics in other attraction directions are similar, but
in a context like this I can only write about my own subjective experience.
Moreover, the Instagram influencer trend is female-dominated, so I think
this is broadly accurate, though I am painting with a big brush. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">During these COVID-19 stay-at-home days, I’ve watched a lot of movies, old and new. Many cultural shifts are caught on film over the decades, but I’ve been most surprised by the change in pacing. In films from the 70s, individual scenes are long. They’re filled with pensive pauses and close-ups, and you get entire minute-long shots of pure framing and mood-setting. Movies from recent years have fast cuts, with not a single moment wasted. A modern feature-length film feels much denser in the sheer amount of content and audiovisual spectacle it gives to the audience.</summary></entry></feed>