<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-07T21:58:16-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jay Riverlong</title><subtitle>Jay Riverlong's personal website. Essays and thoughts.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Institutional Seed Rounds are Bad for Founders</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/07/seed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Institutional Seed Rounds are Bad for Founders" /><published>2021-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/07/seed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/07/seed.html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote my first angel checks in 2014. I’ve now written almost 70.
The landscape has changed greatly: back in the day,
I would see seed rounds valued at $4-8M post-money, with $1-2M invested
so the investors would get about 25% of the company.
To boot, the lead investor would usually get a board seat,
and the company would take another 10% dilution in form of an options pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2021, deals at $4-8M post-money are called pre-seeds.
Today’s seed has crept toward the Series A of old, with post-money valuations
generally not below $10M, the median in the $12M-15M range, and the high end
at $20M or beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fantastic that founders are able to raise at greater valuations, and commensurately more money.
Instead of raising $1M at $4M post, founders today are raising $3M at $12M post. That’s great, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, maybe. You’ll notice that the &lt;em&gt;investor ownership&lt;/em&gt; at the seed stage – 25% – is the only
element that has remained constant. The founder is still &lt;em&gt;selling the same amount of the company&lt;/em&gt;.
They’re getting more dollars in return. Is that a good deal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, maybe. Dollars in the bank have diminishing returns for a seed-stage founder.
Can you make productive use of $250K on day one? Totally. $1M? Probably, over 12-18 months.
$3M? It gets harder to allocate larger amounts of capital efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is compounded by the fact that successful startups are now raising rounds &lt;em&gt;faster&lt;/em&gt; than before.
VCs are hungry to deploy capital, so follow-on rounds and pre-empts are happening more than before.
I’ve seen companies raise their Series As at good valuations while only half-way to the “traditional” Series A
benchmark. I’ve seen Series Bs three months after the A. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this environment, VCs are under significant pressure to deploy their funds.
They aggressively push capital on founders.
The result is that good companies are raising, at the seed stage, capital they will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; deploy.
And that’s a waste of the dilution they take on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strong startups are raising monster seed rounds, $3M plus.
In the old paradigm, that would be for a 18-24 month runway,
so implying an average spend of $125-167k a month.
Actually doing that &lt;em&gt;productively&lt;/em&gt; is hard.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
It implies building a 15+ person team.
That’s tough in itself. But now you actually need to deploy &lt;em&gt;even faster&lt;/em&gt;,
because the old paradigm has been broken.
If you’re good, you may no longer need 18 or 24 months to get to the Series A.
You’ll get there in 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, suppose you raised a $3M seed, and you get to your Series A in 12 months.
You’ve still got $2M in the bank.
You &lt;em&gt;paid&lt;/em&gt; 17% of your company – a co-founder-level chunk – for that capital.
You gave away a board seat. You swallowed the options pool shuffle.
All that for capital that you now don’t need.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You raise your Series A.
The press will cheer you on for being capital efficient.
Your friends will congratulate you on the great brand name that’s getting put on your website
and on your board. And you will bow and shake hands and perform all the social graces,
with the venture capital force-feeding tube still
hanging out of your mouth. But knowing that you’ve thrown away 17% of your company
at the seed should make you sick to your stomach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maybe you’ll raise a smaller seed. You’d like the same valuation, of course.
But the institutions won’t like that.
“Sorry, we have a minimum ownership requirement of 20%”, they’ll tell you.
Needless to say, minimum ownership requirements are bullshit.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is a founder to do? The simple answer is to abandon the institutional raise,
and stick with angels and angel-style investors. This is another big change since 2014:
the number of angels in the market must have increased 100-fold. I’m being hyperbolic,
but it feels like half the valley is angel investing these days.
&lt;em&gt;Everyone&lt;/em&gt;, VC firms and individuals alike, are aggressively deploying capital.
Importantly, angels will pay institutional valuations, and the better ones are
so well-networked that they can help you put together an entire round.
It’s now well possible to put together a multi-million dollar round without a traditional venture firm
involved: the best example is probably &lt;a href=&quot;https://tech.eu/brief/front-series-c/&quot;&gt;Front’s Series C&lt;/a&gt;,
a $59M round led entirely
by individuals, with traditional VC firms only getting small allocations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four other key benefits to skipping the institutions as you break your round down
for many smaller checks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The use of SAFEs enables &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/hiresfund.html&quot;&gt;high-resolution fundraising&lt;/a&gt;.
Close parties as they commit. You
no longer need to get everyone together in an institutional round to close. (Of all rounds that collapse,
timing is usually the main factor.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No board seats. If you don’t have a lead investor, then no investor has the muscle to negotiate
themselves meaningful corporate control.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many small investors who hustle usually constitute a bigger, more helpful network than your one point-person at a VC firm,
 particularly for early-stage companies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You dictate the deal terms. Again, with no lead investor, no-one has the muscle to force better terms for themselves.
 You’re in control.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a competitive time in the market. Many people, myself included, have written
about how &lt;a href=&quot;https://jayriverlong.github.io/2020/08/16/spac.html&quot;&gt;personal brands are disrupting venture capital&lt;/a&gt;
via Rolling Funds and other mechanisms. it turns out that going with the newly liquid kids on the block
has material advantages over going with the capital gatekeepers of old. This is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Startups can burn capital aggressively, pay for top-tier services and best-in-class salaries,
but that kind of spending culture usually sets up for difficult conversations about operating
economics at later stages, so I can’t recommend it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Astute readers will point out that maybe it wasn’t so unwise to take on more capital,
because you &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; not have gotten to your Series A so quickly. Sure. However,
in our example, tacking on a six or twelve-month buffer would have implied only another 4-8% dilution,
as opposed to the 17%. You’re still talking about a &lt;strong&gt;massive&lt;/strong&gt; piece of equity. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are many respects in which they are bullshit, and many reasons for it,
but going through all of them in detail seems like good material for another essay. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I wrote my first angel checks in 2014. I’ve now written almost 70. The landscape has changed greatly: back in the day, I would see seed rounds valued at $4-8M post-money, with $1-2M invested so the investors would get about 25% of the company. To boot, the lead investor would usually get a board seat, and the company would take another 10% dilution in form of an options pool.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bitcoin and Secrecy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/27/bitcoin.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bitcoin and Secrecy" /><published>2020-12-27T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/27/bitcoin</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/27/bitcoin.html">&lt;p&gt;Growing up, I read mysteries and pirate stories. Buried treasure, hidden behind
cryptic puzzles. I read Dan Brown novels about secret societies and great meanings
hidden in small messages. In the modern day, it seemed that this romantic notion
of secrecy – that great wealth can be hidden in small messages – was over forever.
Your money sits in bank accounts, with brokerage firms, in contracts, and so forth.
Hiding a treasure? &lt;em&gt;Owning&lt;/em&gt; something that only you have control over? Good luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt some sadness that this era of simple mystery and treasure seemed over.
(To be fair, more transparency is also a good thing.) But Bitcoin changes this:
you can store an arbitrary amount of wealth behind a single private key. And you
can turn that single private key into a twelve-word passphrase. You can destroy
the key, and remember just those twelve words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, &lt;strong&gt;your identity&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;your memory&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;your money&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;your speech&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turn your passphrase into a song or a poem and write it down, there’s your cryptic puzzle
hiding a treasure. Split it into pieces and hide them with seven objects in
obscure corners of the world, there are your horcruxes. There’s the substrate for
true ownership, for guarding treasure, and for the mystery stories of old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplicity of Bitcoin – that ownership of a few words, short enough to be
remembered, can store arbitrary, uncensorable wealth – re-creates that romantic
notion of secrecy. The old map pointing to vast treasure is new again.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Growing up, I read mysteries and pirate stories. Buried treasure, hidden behind cryptic puzzles. I read Dan Brown novels about secret societies and great meanings hidden in small messages. In the modern day, it seemed that this romantic notion of secrecy – that great wealth can be hidden in small messages – was over forever. Your money sits in bank accounts, with brokerage firms, in contracts, and so forth. Hiding a treasure? Owning something that only you have control over? Good luck.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The San Francisco that Could Have Been</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/sf.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The San Francisco that Could Have Been" /><published>2020-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/sf</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/sf.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m running through Lands End. It’s 8AM on a winter day.
Cool mist hangs in the air, and
the gravel crunches under my running shoes.
I’m looking
at my Apple Watch, checking the time as I run down the hill, past the Cliff House,
looking at the Pacific as it shines in the morning sun
like a pool of liquid silver stretching to the horizon.
California is good.
I hear the waves crashing, and the air softly smells of salt and pines.
To my left,
I see the Pacific Towers:
eight fifty-five story glass obelisks stretching into the
sky, all connected by a public park up top, six hundred feet in the air.
A marvel of modern engineering, only paralleled by a few buildings in
Shanghai. The year is 2030. I’m fortunate to rent a one-bedroom in the Pacific Towers
for $2700 a month. I live on the fourteenth floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shower while Siri reads me my emails. “Archive, archive, skip, schedule for 10AM”:
speech recognition lets me take care of a full night of notifications.
Though my executive and product leaders are in San Francisco,
my company otherwise runs on a 24/7 global team, so work accumulates
throughout the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I step out of the shower. My bathroom’s ceiling fans all immediately point hot air at me
to help me dry off faster. (It’s cozy, too.) I’m rubbing my hair with a towel when
soft ringing emanates throughout the apartment. “Who is it?” I ask. “It’s Jess Bergman”
Siri replies. Six hundred speakers and microphones hidden in the walls throughout my 900 square feet
make it feel remarkably natural to talk to my virtual assistant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pick up”. Jess is on the phone. She’s telling me that one
of our customers, an oil-shipping company, suffered some kind of bizarre bug
where we dispatched one of their tankers without filling it entirely.
It’s a costly error – $8M in oil that’s left sitting somewhere.
Jess and I
suspect some of the customer’s tanker sensors are defective, and we line up
a diagnostic team to take a look. We sell logistical optimization
software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m heading down the elevator to the Pacific Towers to the underground BAMF stop.
BAMF was the 2022 successor to BART – everyone recognized “Bay Area Rapid Transit”
as a hilarious oxymoron, an embarrassment compared to our global peers, so our local
government and industry leaders created Bay Area Mega Fast: an autonomous metro system
modeled after the Hong Kong and Tokyo subways – just twice as fast. Trains arrive
every 30 seconds, and I’ll be at my office in the Tenderloin in exactly 114 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s only one stop in-between. I’m proud to say that my company helped design
some of the BAMF network for optimal throughput –
like all Bay Area projects, it’s a public-private partnership, and the government
brought in the best logistical optimizers from industry.
Even eight years ago, I’m flattered to say that was us. We’re better now,
but we still have a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m wearing my Raycasters inside the BAMF train.
They’re one brand of many smart glasses that overlay
useful information on my field of vision. I usually turn off the
auto-recognize, subtitles, and maps, but keep on my vital sign displays.
The data is beamed straight from my apple watch. Eyeball control makes it super easy
to navigate the interface. It seems that my blood sugar is a little low. I flick
through the suggestions. “Eat a quarter of a Snickers bar”, it says. Great, I’ve got some at the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m out the BAMF and straight up the elevator. My company has half the 85th floor
of the Civic Spiral. The building is a glass tornado. It was completed two years ago,
and it’s the tallest office building in the world. Rent here is unbelievably
expensive – nearly $200 per square foot per year. But it’s a good splurge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a meeting to talk about the status on the oil shipping bug
and get a little more clarity. I’m chatting with the team in Dubai, and my
EARS2 earphones do real-time translation from Arabic to English. It’s amazing.
The EARS2 founder is a buddy of mine, his office is just the floor below.
He’s got an unbelievable view of the Golden Gate Bridge and the Alcatraz International Airport,
where Elon Musk’s grasshopper rockets land and take off all day, sending San Francisco
residents around the globe at Mach 2 for lunch meetings. I think it’s extravagant, but to each their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I step out for lunch with Sam Fultzmann. He’s the craziest guy I know,
which is why I love having lunch with him.
We step outside the Civic Spiral and grab little electric longboards
to scoot to our favorite Shawarma shop. The longboards recognize me by RFID
sensor and automatically bill my Stripe bank account, accurately to the millionth of a dollar.
We arrive at Bilal’s Bar and Grill on Market Street.
The line for seating is forever long.
The GDP of the Tenderloin is nearly a trillion dollars now, but some things just don’t change.
We register ourselves for a seating spot
with a watch tap, and go for a walk under the trees while we wait.
San Francisco got a lot greener
after human-driven cars were banned in 2023. The streets were narrowed since
autonomous vehicles and personal things like bicycles and skateboards just needed
much less space. The fact that just seven years ago, people were driving around
twenty-foot-long trucks &lt;em&gt;for just themselves&lt;/em&gt; that they left parked 92% of the time
is so crazy that I can hardly fathom it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it’s winter, it’s pretty warm outside. There isn’t a building &lt;em&gt;under&lt;/em&gt; 300 feet around me,
it’s glass and concrete as far as the eye can see. That makes it a little warmer on the ground,
but the trees help, and there’s a Fremont company experimenting with upper-stratosphere reflective
seeding to mitigate global warming, which is the overarching culprit here.
I’m due to stop by there later today, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over lunch, Sam tells me that he angel invested in Telomize, a Palo Alto company that
does telomere lengthening for anti-aging. (Everyone’s an angel investor now that
there’s an income tax break if you invest your income in early-stage companies.)
We haven’t cracked the aging nut yet, but we’re close.
I quiz Sam about the prospects of the company, and he admits that he invested
just to get early access to their product. He’s on it right now. I joke that
it could be harmful, but Sam doesn’t care: whatever, there’s no regulatory body
that can stop him from experimenting with novel treatments.
He has an 8G feed
continuously streaming 200 GB a second of vital sign data back to Telomize
company to track the effectiveness and safety of the treatment. There are 35,000
other crazies like him, and between the lot of them they’re constructing a pretty good
medical study in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tell Sam about the oil problem. He tells me he read a book the other day
about Rockefeller and the Oil Magnates of the turn of the 20th century: “did you know
that Cleveland, Ohio used to be the wealthiest city in the United States?” he bursts
out, guffawing. “Cleveland? These guys don’t even have a space program”, I laugh.
(The Bay Area has three now, all private enterprise with some public backing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What happened?” I ask Sam. “Well, jeez, it’s like Cleveland just sort of found
itself in the middle of an oil boom, geographically. One year they were like
any other second-tier industrializing city, and then they suddenly had this
huge influx of wealth and enterprise that they didn’t really understand…
or know how to keep, once things started moving.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So what happened, specifically?” I ask. “Well, the same thing that happens whenever
you try to hold sand with your hands and don’t get a bucket: phoosh, it runs through
your fingers and then it’s gone. A few decades later the oil industry was in Oklahoma,
Texas, everywhere, and then Cleveland was just a small part of it. Standard Oil and what-have-you
relocated to New York City.” Sam takes a bite from his meatless burger.
“I think the people of Cleveland were so caught off-guard by the enormous opportunity
that hit them in the face that they reacted with some level of arrogance, hubris, and
spent their time kind of pooh-poohing the industry, not realizing how lucky they
were to be in pole position in the &lt;em&gt;competition&lt;/em&gt; for this ginormous industry.
So they were asleep at the wheel, and only when the industry moved into other cities
did the people of Cleveland understand, by the sheer voracity of competition,
 how valuable this new industry was.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You’re telling me the golden goose made a nest in their back yard and they basically
just stayed inside drinking beers and jacking off.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah. And sometimes plucking the goose for feathers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s the dumbest fucking thing I’ve ever heard.”
I’m looking up the Four Seasons Master Suites. Eight hundred feet of commercial and residential
real estate. In the top ten floors, each apartment has a private pool. It’s some of the
most valuable real estate on the planet, 4th and Market, downtown San Francisco,
the heart of the safest city in the United States, a technological metropolis,
a smoothly running engine generating compound growth of wealth every year,
the altar of innovation. A testament to the power of courageous people coming
together to build the future. Hong Kong and Singapore look sleepy by comparison.
“I guess if people fail to seize opportunity, that’s on them, and they kinda self-select,
they probably weren’t the right stewards of that opportunity in the first place.”
A little delivery drone flies by silently and drops off a package through an apartment window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get through the rest of the workday just fine. Our weekly 5PM resident’s poll
was pretty interesting: one item on the poll asked me to vote on whether or not
San Francisco should petition to host the 2032 International Kite Surfing Championships
at a cost of about $311.60 per taxpayer. I’m a big fan, so I voted in favor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rapidfire direct democracy
is a great way to make small changes, while the larger changes deserve much more diligent
debate. There’s currently a big discussion about whether the Sunset should have its
housing density increased – the average building is a 14-story midrise apartment
complex, interspersed with some commercial real estate. The debate is as to whether
the city should buy out homeowners in some of the shorter buildings and create more dense
skyscrapers that it can sell to new arrivals so as to keep rents low. Back in 2010,
there was a serious push in government to just keep increasing the housing stock any time
a one bedroom threatened to go over $3000 a month in rent, and now we have one of the world’s densest and
most economically productive cities.
It turns out that when you offer amazing opportunity at low cost,
an unbelievable caliber of talent concentrates. Sounds obvious, but even New York doesn’t get it.
Anyway, so there’s this big fuffle about whether to buy out six blocks of homeowners and construct another 6,000
family units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a little split because I think there are better immediate uses of capital than for the homeowner buyout –
I’d like to keep allocating R&amp;amp;D funds to the California State Semiconductor Company, for example.
I’m on the city’s Financial Optimization Committee, where maybe I’ll try to steer toward using some municipal debt product
to instead do the real estate thing, but there are a lot of variables at play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m wrapping up the day by chatting with Liza Wallen.
She runs the Fremont-based solar geoengineering firm I mentioned earlier.
As you can imagine, putting reflective particles into the upper stratosphere to block out the sun
was very
controversial when the G8 countries first started seriously considering it, but it was soon clear
that it was the only feasible way to curb global warming without relying on solving virtually impossible
coordination problems, like everyone dropping fossil fuels at once.
Liza’s company ended up presenting the most detailed (and compelling) effect models,
so they were one of five companies chosen globally to give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logistics of everything involved are difficult,
so my company has a contract with Liza’s firm to help them operate as efficiently as possible.
I would normally take the call by video from my home, but Liza in person is always great, so I’m heading to Fremont.
I’m not using BAMF because I can’t be bothered transferring between stations,
so I’m just calling a little Toaster Oven. That’s what we
call the Autonomous Taxis that ferry around small groups of people (their pickup routes optimized by yours truly) –
they’re these cute little boxes that look like toaster ovens and zip around at 80 miles an hour, which is pretty slow, but we’ll get an upgrade soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m running through Lands End. It’s 8AM on a winter day. Cool mist hangs in the air, and the gravel crunches under my running shoes. I’m looking at my Apple Watch, checking the time as I run down the hill, past the Cliff House, looking at the Pacific as it shines in the morning sun like a pool of liquid silver stretching to the horizon. California is good. I hear the waves crashing, and the air softly smells of salt and pines. To my left, I see the Pacific Towers: eight fifty-five story glass obelisks stretching into the sky, all connected by a public park up top, six hundred feet in the air. A marvel of modern engineering, only paralleled by a few buildings in Shanghai. The year is 2030. I’m fortunate to rent a one-bedroom in the Pacific Towers for $2700 a month. I live on the fourteenth floor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ten Reasons for Tech Optimism in 2021</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/optimism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ten Reasons for Tech Optimism in 2021" /><published>2020-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/optimism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/optimism.html">&lt;p&gt;I have written &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/10/24/future.html&quot;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt;
about losing my teenage optimism for technology,
and how we struggle to have bold dreams for the future.
Many people have articulated theses of this type, most famously
Peter Thiel in claiming that we’ve seen great innovation in the world of bits,
but not of atoms. However, change is in the air. I believe we are approaching an inflection point
of technological change and ambition.
In a twist of irony, COVID has done a great deal to push this along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before 2020, we were stuck in what I call the &lt;em&gt;eternal 90s&lt;/em&gt;.
With the Soviet Union defeated, the United States had no focal
objective: no great enemy to defeat, no great frontier to explore.
For almost thirty years, the same set of Bill Clinton-era trends compounded on
themselves: liberalization, globalization, and growth of the internet.
It’s been a good thirty years of steady marginal progress:
reliable growth in GDP, better medicine, higher quality of food, and so on, like clockwork.
Unfortunately, marginal change is not &lt;em&gt;inspirational&lt;/em&gt;.
It has been a long time since technology has captured the hearts and minds of
a generation like the space race did in the 1960s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter 2020. Between COVID and Trump,
the trends of the eternal 90s have ruptured somewhat.
Technological penetration has leapt forward by years.
The year 2021, and the thoughts prevalent in it, will be different from 2019,
much more so than for almost any other one-year gap in recent history.
There are several important components in this shift:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Cheap Capital&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to COVID, the American fiscal response has been aggressive.
With around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2020/04/15/coronavirus-economy-6-trillion/&quot;&gt;6 trillion dollars&lt;/a&gt;
of stimulus, capital is cheap and will be for a long time.
This is subtle, but of dominant importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. The Best Ever Funding Environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With trillions of stimulus dollars in the markets, the zero-interest-rate
search for yield of the late 2010s is more desperate than ever before.
There are more dollars in venture than there are ideas.
If there has ever been a time in which it is feasible to raise gargantuan
rounds to pursue real-world moonshots, this is it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. The Great Unbundling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many institutions exist
as a consequence of returns to scale.
While technology has slowly eroded some of their necessity,
this has greatly accelerated under COVID.
These institutions
are now clearly struggling to deliver value, and self-sufficiency is becoming a priority again.
We are on the cusp of many traditional structures and institutions
being totally overhauled and unbundled. This is an enormously exciting opportunity
across many industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. De-Urbanization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cities were Schelling points for talent in 2019,
but no longer.
COVID has catapulted remote work tools and culture forward by years.
Previously urban professionals are
moving to smaller cities and suburbs,
and owning homes years ahead of schedule.
This has wide-ranging impacts: a class of workers is suddenly
much more financially secure, tier-2/3 cities see an influx of high-earning
professionals, tier-1 cities become cheaper,
and as geography wanes in importance, opportunity becomes more accessible to all,
even on a global scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Schooling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schooling is being rapidly unbundled at all levels.
Like de-urbanization, homeschooling was previously a small, niche trend.
Under COVID, it is a necessity.
As with remote work, the demand, culture, and tools for it have advanced by years
in a few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same has occurred for higher education. Many have written about the
out-of-control costs of college, while struggling to replace the extremely
convenient all-in-one package of academics, socializing, and professional training
that college provides. But COVID has forced the unbundling of college: now that students get to meet
none of their classmates in person and are paying $60k a year for online
lectures that they could get for free off YouTube, the simple BA credential
obviously isn’t worth it for most. As education gets unbundled, it will become radically cheaper and open,
multiplying opportunity on a global scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Digital Gold and More&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fiscal response to COVID was explicitly inflationary.
The Fed has nearly doubled the assets on its balance sheet
to prop up the markets,
and the US dollar has depreciated against other currencies.
Prudent investors are worried about potential runaway inflation,
and attention turns to Bitcoin again.
Now much more mature and validated,
it is appealing as an inflation hedge.
As its ecosystem matures more, we may see
many products on top of the base layer.
In the next decade, we might not just see programmable money, but
a groundbreaking separation of state and money. The opportunities for
(tumultuous) change and innovation in this context are endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Independent Workers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With remote work, workers become more independent.
Superstars – who bring outsize value, many times their compensation –
are realizing they can go independent with their brand. You see it in
&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/08/16/spac.html&quot;&gt;investing, writing, even porn&lt;/a&gt;. The newspapers and TV
of tomorrow will look very different from those of today.
This trend will be universal across media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. New Dreams: SpaceX and Tesla&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tesla has had a dizzying ten-fold
run in the markets this year, surpassing a $500B market cap.
By valuation, the markets
think that TSLA will not obsolete &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; incumbent car companies, but &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt;
of them.
I believe that part of why $TSLA has appreciated so greatly
is that in this time of desperation,
Elon Musk delivers a vision people can believe in.
People are watching
rocket launches again, and this time they’re reusable rockets out of Musk’s
private enterprise.
He is innovating in the world of atoms, not of bits,
and that’s relatable and inspiring in a way that no software entrepreneur
before him ever was.
Tesla is barely even working on truly self-driving cars, and somehow Musk
has sold a &lt;em&gt;vision&lt;/em&gt; of autonomous vehicles that Waymo hasn’t.
People are dreaming of going to space again. Musk is inspiring a generation
of budding entrepreneurs to build things that are grand and ambitious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. New Worlds: AR/VR&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AR and VR technologies had their moment of hype in the mid-2010s, but
didn’t catch on in the mainstream.
However, a little like Bitcoin, the technology and infrastructure
has been steadily improving in the background. It’s becoming very good,
and soon it’ll be ready for primetime.
Video games and movies are going to get hit by the colossal force
of a new, more immersive medium with enormous room for experimentation.
Even mundane things like exercise and videocalls will get turned on their heads.
This will be the biggest leap in the &lt;em&gt;medium&lt;/em&gt; of computing since the smartphone
in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Digital Health&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six years ago, only medical patients had real-time feeds of their vital signs.
Thanks to Apple Watches, tens of millions of consumers now have a
continuous ECG and blood oxygen monitor.
Thousands of hobbyists wear glucose monitors.
Innovations in chips (M1) and wireless (5G)
dramatically improve the computing and streaming capacity for detailed vital sign data,
and the benefits will compound.
Over the decade, I expect us to get fitness-grade health data streams for most major vital signs,
and that analysis of this data at scale will enable early detection
of both common and grave medical conditions like heart attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what’s happening? Well, capital is cheaper than ever. It’s an amazing time
to be an entrepreneur with bold, ambitious ideas. The success of Elon Musk
is inspiring a generation to be exactly that. And where are these entrepreneurs to start?
Well, digital health and AR/VR are ripening to change people’s lives massively at scale.
We might see the separation between state and money. And if that’s not enough,
most of our traditional institutions and structures, like cities, schools, and
employment are getting unbundled as we speak, democratizing access to opportunity.
Roll up your sleeves,
pick whatever target you want, it’s a good time to build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Addendum: Empty Spaces&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this doesn’t fit strictly into the realm of technological innovation,
there’s work to be done reimagining the city, too.
Under COVID, cities have lost not just residents, but also businesses.
With retail having jumped online, and many restaurants now operating
as delivery-only cloud kitchens, there’s a big question as to what happens
with vacant prime real estate.
Are bars and clothing shops really the best we can do?
The destruction that has happened here has created an opening for experimentation
and new establishments that offer novel in-person experiences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have written previously about losing my teenage optimism for technology, and how we struggle to have bold dreams for the future. Many people have articulated theses of this type, most famously Peter Thiel in claiming that we’ve seen great innovation in the world of bits, but not of atoms. However, change is in the air. I believe we are approaching an inflection point of technological change and ambition. In a twist of irony, COVID has done a great deal to push this along.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Spiteful Investor (or There Are Always Idiots at the Cutting Edge)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/20/investor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Spiteful Investor (or There Are Always Idiots at the Cutting Edge)" /><published>2020-11-20T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/20/investor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/20/investor.html">&lt;p&gt;I like to think I’m a pretty rational investor. Not too emotional,
not too prone to FOMO, willing to wait for good deals.
So, let me tell you about a bad and embarrassing decision I made.
This story may seem pretty dumb to you, as it does to me today.
I often read about great financial disasters and think
“that’s so stupid! I would never screw up this badly.”
It turns out that’s easier said than done;
some theoretical lessons are very hard to internalize in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late 2014, I was cautiously bullish on Bitcoin. I saw the appeal
of finite-supply assets in other markets, leaned cypherpunk-libertarian,
and had run into many issues with fiat payment processors in my poker days.
However, I had also seen Liberty Reserve shut down by the FBI,
watched quaint early scams like Auroracoin,
and thought it seemed clear that the government would eventually need to
shut down this state-threatening Wild West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was bullish, but hesitant to put real skin in the game.
Along came an opportunity to bet on Bitcoin with
no personal downside: I met a young founder who had just raised $2M
from a few investors for the purpose of getting them Bitcoin exposure.
Let’s call him Mephisto.
He had negotiated 25% carry on the profits of his small fund, which was an excellent deal.
His track record made sense:
he’d been in the industry since 2012, and had made some good money
on Bitcoin and trading FPGAs.
He had brought on a young woman – let’s call her Bellatrix –
to help manage operations.
As we talked, we realized I could help them generate alpha beyond
pure Bitcoin exposure. I knew financial derivatives very well, so
my task was broadly to profit off inefficiencies in these nascent markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was 23.
Working with Mephisto and Bellatrix was like sitting on the Hindenburg.
While I was combing the market for inefficiencies, they were
struggling to get the operations fully set up.
A few weeks in, it turned out
that Mephisto and Bellatrix had been fucking in secret.
They had an equity dispute.
He went off his medication, and
suffered a psychotic breakdown.
She accused him of rape.
They called the cops on each other.
He disappeared and re-encountered the substance abuse problem
that had put him on anti-psychotic medication in the first place.
To top it all off, they lost the cold storage credentials for a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled the escape cord and resigned cleanly.
Ironically, I took a financial loss here,
since I had to have my lawyers review everything and
ensure I wasn’t liable for any fiduciary mismanagement
these two chaos clowns might undertake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point it was early 2015. Bitcoin hovered between $200 and $250 per coin.
I was totally over it. The cautiously bullish view I had gotten around to
was eviscerated by my distaste for the Mephisto episode.
I was exasperated,
liquidated nearly my entire position and sat, for a long time,
more in the bear camp than not.
Thinking about Mephisto and Bellatrix,
I said to myself, if &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; is who is managing money in Bitcoin,
there’s no hope for the sector.
Bearish on Bitcoin at a $3B market cap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of my attitude was a spiteful emotional hedge.
I think my reasoning went like this:
investing in Bitcoin could go two ways.
I could lose money, and I would be disappointed.
I could also make money,
but in that case, Mephisto and his ilk would make wildly &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; money, and
I would be upset.
If I were to invest and succeed holding the same position as Mephisto,
I’d be envious of someone I despised.
I wanted Mephisto to fail, so I wanted Bitcoin to fail.
It’s a twisted rationalization – silly in retrospect, of course.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to be a rational investor when the seas are calm.
It’s hard when it gets emotional.
Importantly,
everyone
has a threshold – if the personal relationships are close enough,
or if the stress is great enough, suddenly even the most rational actors
crack. I saw it all the time playing poker: your opponents
are stone-faced rational actors until something gets to them. They’re tired or
distracted, and suddenly they get pissed off when they normally wouldn’t,
and make bets they shouldn’t. Very few people manage to stay rational
in charged moments. The better-disciplined folks will
summon all their willpower just to walk away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this episode, I let emotional stress override my assessment of the market.
Stupidly, I let my subjective, one-off personal experience bias me against
an entire industry. Stress had me do a 180 on a carefully considered position
of conviction. Refusing to take a position out of spite, or in order to pre-empt envy
in the case of success, is even more embarrassing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there was one other important thing I hadn’t considered or realized at the time:
the cutting edge is always full of idiots.
It’s a common trope that people who are all-in on frontier tech are usually somewhat crazy.
We have a romantic
view of folks on the frontier – eccentric geniuses – but much of the time
it’s gullible bozos and scammers feeding off them.
In a historical analogy, the Wild West does not just create outlaws, it
necessarily attracts them.
My mistake here was to let the worst people
color my representation of the market.
It doesn’t matter how many scammers
and con-men there are, it matters how many people are building stable infrastructure.
It doesn’t matter how many ways there are for it to fail, it only matters
that there’s one plausible way to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’d bet that the big-name no-coiners like Nouriel Roubini, Peter Schiff,
and David Girard have a similar emotional hedge.
They’ve been calling Bitcoin snake oil for years.
Their nocoinery has been a core part of their public identities.
Knowing that you’ve been wrong all along and that all your opponents
have become millionaires would be devastating.
They’re stuck now: if they were ever to become bullish, they would
be tormented by their past decisions.
So they remain permabears, fingers in their ears,
calling it a scam and &lt;em&gt;praying&lt;/em&gt; it’ll eventually go to zero, even while the
number keeps going up. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I like to think I’m a pretty rational investor. Not too emotional, not too prone to FOMO, willing to wait for good deals. So, let me tell you about a bad and embarrassing decision I made. This story may seem pretty dumb to you, as it does to me today. I often read about great financial disasters and think “that’s so stupid! I would never screw up this badly.” It turns out that’s easier said than done; some theoretical lessons are very hard to internalize in practice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two Life Lessons from A Series of Unfortunate Events</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/snicket.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two Life Lessons from A Series of Unfortunate Events" /><published>2020-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/snicket</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/snicket.html">&lt;p&gt;Important lessons often take a long time to gestate.
I didn’t really understand linear algebra until five years after
I first took it – like in many other fields,
I had to climb far up the tower to appreciate the foundations.
Getting Plato’s &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt; took me ten years of fleeting thoughts.
Even for movies, forming an opinion sometimes takes me months of rumination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently been thinking about my
favorite childhood book series, &lt;em&gt;A Series of Unfortunate Events&lt;/em&gt;.
It seems that it took me nearly fifteen years to understand two of its core lessons.
ASOUE is a thirteen-novel Victorian-Gothic black comedy series
about three orphans and the uncle trying to steal their inheritance.
While the first few novels formulaically
follow this premise, the later novels uncover a set of deep conspiracies
surrounding their deceased parents and thieving adversaries.
As the universe of the story becomes more complex,
we realize that it’s not a simple tale of good and evil,
and the actions of the protagonists become steeped in moral ambiguity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was fifteen years old when I read the thirteenth and final novel, &lt;em&gt;The End&lt;/em&gt;.
To my endless disappointment, it concluded with nothing.
As far as I was
concerned,
every major question remained open.
Even trivially answerable questions, like about the contents of a particular plot MacGuffin,
were left cloaked in eternal silence.
If anything, the novel added &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; questions.
To a young completionist, this was awfully frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I grew older, my obsessive need for closure waned.
As I became busier, I stopped caring about tying up every end.
I learned that most people don’t care as much about literal
definitions as I do, and that most efforts are not completed but abandoned.
In that context, &lt;em&gt;The End&lt;/em&gt; made its final lesson a meaningful, if unpleasant one:
&lt;strong&gt;most ends are left frayed&lt;/strong&gt;.
The world branches forward unpredictably,
with unlucky branches dying off – no catharsis,
no punctuation, but sparks fizzling out and attentions shifting.
Reflecting on the story as an adult, it was the perfect ending to a series
about great mysteries and deep ambiguities: most of them stay unresolved forever.
And that’s all right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other important lesson I took away was one about conflict.
The core mysteries of ASOUE concern a metaphorical &lt;em&gt;Volunteer Fire Department&lt;/em&gt;
that had split into
two sides: one starts fires, the other puts them out.
Of course, this is enormously contrived. The two organizations are in
a symbiotic, but completely pointless relationship: they exist only to nullify
each others’ actions. Further, while the two sides are at first presented as morally black-and-white,
the reader learns that each side is a bit of a mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an adult, the yin-yang fire departments sound familiar.
I’ve learned that in order to give themselves purpose in life,
&lt;strong&gt;people play games&lt;/strong&gt;.
In a world where we are mostly safe from real war and disease,
we instigate new conflicts
to keep us busy and to satisfy our primal needs to compete and do battle.
If we have nothing to fight for,
we create it. Fukuyama &lt;a href=&quot;https://unherd.com/2020/09/why-fukuyama-was-right-all-along/&quot;&gt;realized this&lt;/a&gt;, and the danger it poses
to our society.
And once you realize that most conflicts are not well-reasoned,
good-faith differences of opinion but rather arbitrary symbolic battle,
then they all wind up looking just as unnecessary and ambiguous as the two volunteer fire departments.
Every dispute is sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, I’ve kept coming back to these two
core points of &lt;em&gt;A Series of Unfortunate Events&lt;/em&gt;,
which went way over my teenage head when
I first read them. Now, nearly fifteen years later, not only do they make more sense,
but they hold up a mirror to deep truths that I’ve encountered as I’ve
learned more about the world. This is the mark of good fiction.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Important lessons often take a long time to gestate. I didn’t really understand linear algebra until five years after I first took it – like in many other fields, I had to climb far up the tower to appreciate the foundations. Getting Plato’s Republic took me ten years of fleeting thoughts. Even for movies, forming an opinion sometimes takes me months of rumination.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two Paradigms of Personal Computing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/27/machines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two Paradigms of Personal Computing" /><published>2020-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/27/machines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/27/machines.html">&lt;p&gt;A frequently recurring staple of Hacker News is the &lt;em&gt;personal computing rant&lt;/em&gt;:
modern computers are black boxes, far too locked down.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
We long for our desktop computers, the early-2000s computing paradigm,
and we want to take back control of our data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sympathize greatly with this view.
For the past five years, I have exclusively run Arch Linux.
I love the early-2000s style of personal computing: text-heavy interfaces,
words rather than icons, uniform keyboard shortcuts everywhere.
I do nearly all my computing in emacs.
It is feature rich, and no product manager is ever going to change the experience, interface, or shortcuts.
My workspace allows me to be &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;.
Contrary to much modern software, emacs responds instantaneously to my keystrokes.
Every action has an immediate effect, clear on the page, with no background process ambiguity.
This is enormously satisfying.
I would characterize this computing environment as a
spiritual descendant of the typewriter:
on its own, it is a dumb machine, but when you command it, it becomes a powerful
extension of you.
The user experience is given by speed, smoothness, reliability, and nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, you’ve got iPhones and iPads.
These are not machines that you command – on the contrary, you might argue
that all their notifications command you. With touch interfaces,
facial recognition, and
voice control, these are machines that are meant to merge with you.
Instead of becoming an &lt;em&gt;extension&lt;/em&gt; of you, it becomes &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of you.
Instead of you commanding it, it is meant to anticipate your commands.
Where is the data? How does it work? Who knows. They’re total black boxes,
effectively indistinguishable from magic, whereas your Linux Desktop is a
DIYable simple machine.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many contemporary writers think of personal computing as
one paradigm that is gradually evolving. I disagree: I think there are two,
deeply different paradigms of personal computing, reflecting deeply different desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Machine as extension of the self (your Windows XP Desktop).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Machine as part of the self (your iPhone).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plenty of devices exist in the space in-between. Android phones
try to give you some control back over your device, by which they necessarily
preclude themselves from truly being &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of you. Modern versions of OS X,
with the touchbar, Siri, and integrations into all your other Apple devices, are
starting to make the leap from extending the self to being part of the self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a genre, the personal computing rant comes out of the correct view that
these are all forms of personal computing, but it fails to recognize that
within this broad umbrella, we’ve seen paradigms arise that differ in both
intent and the human desire they’re meant to meet.
It’s not that one
class of devices is replacing the other.
They are fundamentally different, and one paradigm succeeds where the other
falls short of meeting the consumers’ needs.
The terminal never met the needs of those who want Amazon Alexa, and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live in the in-between. I happily imagine a world where my Apple Watch
monitors my glucose and blood oxygen, my Eight Sleep quantifies my rest,
I mark up documents on giant touchscreens, but I sit on a clacky
IBM keyboard to write code and blog posts in a terminal that hasn’t changed
in twenty years. While your iPhone might meld with your mind by quantifying
and anticipating your every need, my terminal melds with my mind by
being fast, constant, and &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; correct. Each has its place, and I would
never trade one for the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This essay was inspired by a recent hit on Hacker News,
in which the &lt;a href=&quot;http://misc-stuff.terraaeon.com/articles/locked-down-computers.html&quot;&gt;Author is Seriously Considering Going Back to Desktop Computers&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To me, a Linux desktop is almost more like a typewriter than it is like an iPhone.
I can peek inside and understand how most of the tech works.
I can debug it, swap out components, and so on.
It’s like a mechanism of levers and cogs: complicated, perhaps, but understandable
and possible to reason deeply about. An iPhone is inaccessible in all these
respects; it might as well be a magic wand. That’s not necessarily a bad thing,
these are just very different classes of object. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A frequently recurring staple of Hacker News is the personal computing rant: modern computers are black boxes, far too locked down.1 We long for our desktop computers, the early-2000s computing paradigm, and we want to take back control of our data. This essay was inspired by a recent hit on Hacker News, &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No More Bold Visions of the Future</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/24/future.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No More Bold Visions of the Future" /><published>2020-10-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/24/future</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/24/future.html">&lt;p&gt;What do I want the future to be like?
What amazing inventions do I want to see, and help build in my lifetime?
I realized this morning that I don’t know.
I was shocked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been tinkering with technology since I was a child,
and I’ve been
investing in early-stage companies for the past five years.
More than sixty bets on the future.
I’m meant to have bold visions of a better world,
theses I support,
and capital that I allocate in a technologically optimistic way.
I began investing
in startups because I wanted to help shape the future.
And while I still get excited
talking to founders with bold ideas, I have none of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a teen, growing up on a diet of
Carl Sagan’s Cosmos and Alvin Toffler’s
Futurism, I had plenty of big ideas:
spaceflight, supersonic travel, mag-lev trains,
geodesic domes,
bio-nanotech for longevity, and social organization to provide maximum freedom for all.
Cheesy, but optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I am 29 and I have no big, optimistic ideas.
I think of plenty of arbitrages and improvements in efficiency.
And while I believe that better infrastructure
enables more construction and innovation, closing an obscure
pricing gap just isn’t like dreams of great adventure and
exploration on the frontier of human experience and possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend much time thinking about solutions to existing problems – the
incentive mismatch in mass media that is causing accelerating polarization,
how to remedy the effects of climate change, and so on.
But these are all &lt;em&gt;fixes&lt;/em&gt;, reactions.
It feels like I’m in the belly of the ship, frenetically plugging leaky holes, never
even having the space of mind to think &lt;em&gt;where the ship should go&lt;/em&gt;.
Ostensibly, those decisions are made on the bridge of the ship,
which, in October 2020, seems to be populated by well-intentioned individuals,
but hamstrung in their ability to make good collective decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent years have shown me how difficult it is to make &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; meaningful
public decision.
Every debate is endlessly contentious,
every subject has meaningful nuance,
and every decision has exceedingly hard-to-predict second-order-effects.
The world is much more complex than it was even twenty years ago,
and
the effects are paralyzing.
This is clearly felt among policymakers,
but I feel it even as a technologist:
I understand that virtually all tools
can be used – and more often than not, &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be used – for both good and evil,
and how hard the results are to predict over years in our dynamic world.
I learned that technology can rarely solve fundamental social problems, and
I’ve
seen the public perception rollercoaster of “this technology/person/policy is good” to “this is evil”
more times than I can count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This puts me in a real bind for having high-conviction views that aren’t microscopically focused.
As an example, for the past few years I have struggled developing a long-term view on bitcoin.
By network effect, I think it is clear that in the long term, we will have &lt;em&gt;either&lt;/em&gt;
fiat or crypto – either fully centralized or fully decentralized – not both.
Which world do I want to live in? I’m not sure.
On the one hand, it is clear that our existing
US financial system is fragile with systemic risk, a playball exposed to potentially irresponsible
governance.
You might call its mechanics unfair to the masses, but you’d also
need to point out that it has &lt;em&gt;actually worked&lt;/em&gt; in creating prosperity
over the past 110 years.
(And, comparing the US to other countries, it has
worked remarkably well!)
I agree with need for overhaul of the
system, but I’m not sure if it’s wise throw out the entire thing
and open up the world’s largest
power vacuum in the process. This rarely ends well.
I cannot tell, with intellectual honesty, which avenue is best
to pursue. I doubt that anyone does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other arenas of big problems and changes yield similar dilemmas.
Perhaps consequently, I have found myself not dreaming big anymore.
I dream small, where the effects
are predictable.
On dreaming big, there is the paralysis of responsibility and effects,
but there is also a level of cynicism that has
come to me over the years, as big dreams turn out to be much more fraught and
complicated as they move into reality.
The nuance, complexity, difficulty, responsibility, and often &lt;em&gt;irreversibility&lt;/em&gt;
in effecting big changes
has slowly removed the stars from my eyes as I look at technology.
Maybe that’s a good thing as I come to appreciate the gravity of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the same time,
if we don’t take big, bold, bets, we’ll be forever stuck in the valleys of local optima.
As Bezos says, the size of your risk-taking should increase with the size of your
enterprise – at scale, we should be taking many daring gambles, all the time.
But it doesn’t feel like that’s really happening.
It feels like we spend lots of effort debating marginal nuance,
sitting in the belly of the ship doing maintenance, rather than charting the course forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to be an optimist in 2020.
I admire the few&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that still have the courage to dream big and to remind ourselves
that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a future that could be amazing and that is worth fighting for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This article in particular was inspired by Blake Scholl and Boom’s
stalwart efforts to return us to an era of supersonic flight, and
Founders Fund’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/foundersfund/status/1313151184287477767?s=20&quot;&gt;opening notes&lt;/a&gt; to their annual meeting. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What do I want the future to be like? What amazing inventions do I want to see, and help build in my lifetime? I realized this morning that I don’t know. I was shocked.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Influencers as Tech Founders: Real Monetization at Last</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/17/influencer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Influencers as Tech Founders: Real Monetization at Last" /><published>2020-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/17/influencer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/17/influencer.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Dobrik&quot;&gt;David Dobrik&lt;/a&gt;,
a YouTube star with 26 million followers, is launching a social media app
called &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/dispo-live-in-the-moment/id1491684197&quot;&gt;Dispo&lt;/a&gt;.
There’s a good chance it turns him into a billionaire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dobrik is wealthy already. His monthly YouTube check is around
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.menshealth.com/entertainment/a29798708/david-dobrik-salary/&quot;&gt;$275k&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
and he probably makes a little more from his merchandise sales.
After a seven-year career becoming one of the most famous YouTubers, he’s probably
worth around $30 million. However, if he succeeds with Dispo, his earnings-to-date would
pale in comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dispo is a compelling product, and there’s a good chance it will be very successful, for two reasons.
First, Dobrik is outrageously popular with an everyman appeal and a
loyal following in a highly valuable
demographic.
Second, Dobrik’s reach is &lt;em&gt;enormous&lt;/em&gt;. By himself, he has 26 million
subscribers on YouTube, 23 million on TikTok, and 14 million on Instagram.
The rest of his entourage have millions more. Dobrik himself
has accumulated 8.5 &lt;em&gt;billion&lt;/em&gt; YouTube views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With only light marketing, Dobrik has gotten a million downloads for Dispo already.
If he starts seriously pushing Dispo,
he will easily get millions more.
Normally, the biggest hurdle for consumer software/social media apps is solving
the initial chicken-and-egg problem: how do you get people to sign up if no-one else
is on it? Dobrik bulldozes this problem. He is a one-man network effect.
While other companies spend
years slowly growing by word-of-mouth and spending millions of dollars on marketing,
Dobrik eclipses them from day one: he
gets his first million users by just telling his followers to download his cool new app.
While traditional brands
might balk at forking over tens of millions of dollars in cash
to influencer advertising campaigns of hard-to-assess effectiveness,
for Dobrik, this is free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to overstate how important this is. Lots of great products die because
they can’t get early-stage consumer traction, sometimes for no reason other than bad luck.
Dobrik can catapult a product
into the growth stage. He creates what normally takes &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt; of brand development instantly with zero cost.
Normally, an early-stage consumer product
in a highly competitive space like social media will pay about $10-30 in customer
acquisition costs (CAC) to register a single new user.
Dobrik’s following gifts him
the equivalent of tens of millions of dollars in CAC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumer software presents an elegant solution to an age-old problem: influencers
(more traditionally, celebrities) have millions of people watching their every move, but often struggle to
monetize all these eyeballs, even though attention is arguably the most valuable
scarce resource in our internet economy.
Historically, these people have sold
merchandise, been paid for appearances, done book deals, acted in movies/TV, endorsed products,
and sometimes even put out music albums.
These things all make money, but
relative to the value of their brand and the attention it gets,
these monetization techniques are earning pennies on the dollar. These are
five- and six-figure deals when their full CAC potential is worth hundreds of millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Dobrik succeeds, it will change the influencer monetization game.
While top-tier
influencers previously made single-digit millions of dollars, commercial success
for Dispo could be worth hundreds of millions, if not more.
If Dispo just raises a Series A or Series B, Dobrik’s share in Dispo (at least on paper) would
be more valuable than his current net worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless if Dobrik succeeds in this way, some influencer
will, sooner or later.
Consumer tech has been moving
steadily from San Francisco to Los Angeles over the past few years – virtually
all the cool new consumer companies are out of LA – and it’s only a matter of time
until the tech and influencer worlds intertwine more in this way.
For a start, TikTok influencers
at the Sway House are starting
to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibtimes.com/tiktok-influencers-sway-boys-turn-angel-investors-just-trying-make-smart-investments-3051715&quot;&gt;angel invest&lt;/a&gt;
into consumer social companies, and use their followings to help grow those businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intertwining seems inevitable. The entrepreneurial spirit is already there.
Emma Chamberlain (10 million YouTube followers) started a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.refinery29.com/en-us/2020/09/10042481/emma-chamberlain-coffee-merch-brand-interview&quot;&gt;coffee company&lt;/a&gt;.
Bryce Hall and Josh Richards (combined 36 million TikTok Followers) started
an &lt;a href=&quot;https://dankanator.com/74391/josh-richards-bryce-hall-launching-ani-energy-drink/&quot;&gt;energy drink company&lt;/a&gt;.
The only issue is that
merch or beverage companies have low upside and command low multiples, compared to software.
By opportunity cost, it’s not the best use of these influencers’ brands.
It’s only a matter of time until they start co-founding businesses in the
high multiple, high-upside consumer software space.
In the past, consumer tech made influencers. Soon, influencers will make consumer tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dobrik commented that he had some advertising issues
that shrunk his earnings on some of his videos by 99%, but I suspect this
was a temporary issue. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">David Dobrik, a YouTube star with 26 million followers, is launching a social media app called Dispo. There’s a good chance it turns him into a billionaire.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stripe Atlas: the Key to a $100B+ Company</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/10/atlas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stripe Atlas: the Key to a $100B+ Company" /><published>2020-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/10/atlas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/10/atlas.html">&lt;p&gt;Stripe is a well-known innovator in digital payments.
They attacked one of the most intimidating and locked-down markets,
and made it look like child’s play.
They have a compounding competitive edge
in processing payments more efficiently for their customers,
and the best-crafted
APIs in the entire industry.
Stripe is admired on these grounds, and more:
they have their own &lt;a href=&quot;https://press.stripe.com/&quot;&gt;press&lt;/a&gt;,
in line with their thoughtful, public intellectual staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stripe’s mission is to increase the GDP of the internet. As part of that
mission, one of their many products is Atlas, a service that allows
entrepreneurs from around
the world to incorporate Delaware LLCs and C-Corporations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that Atlas is core to Stripe becoming a $100B+ company.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
But what’s so special about an incorporation service?
Hundreds of thousands
of companies get incorporated every year, and there are plenty of online
incorporation services already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a start, Atlas is much better than its competitors.
Though this might at first look like a well-commoditized market,
it is not at all.
Services like LegalZoom, CooleyGo, etc. offer a smaller set of incorporation
options and
a lower quality of legal formation documents.
Meanwhile, Atlas is as good
as having an Orrick lawyer do the job, while being an online form
a tenth of that price. Even a cheap lawyer is still twice as expensive for the job.
Plus, Atlas is unique in that it services international entrepreneurs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, even being the best incorporation service in the world might be worth at
most a few billion dollars.
The exceptional value in Atlas is in the lock-in it enables for B2B services added on top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest challenge of B2B services is customer acquisition.
How do you win over enterprise clients when existing relationships are so sticky?
The current dominant strategy is to be the first one there.
Start working with a company at the
earliest stages, in order to
make actual money off them a few years down the line,
when they’re much bigger and need more expensive services.
This strategy is
everywhere:
AWS extends credits to lock the earliest startups into their
cloud platform.
Brex advertises specifically to seed-stage startups, but they only
start to really make money when those startups are Series-C companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atlas is the ultimate player in that strategy.
There’s no earlier stage to get
involved than at incorporation.
Stripe is already using Atlas in the obvious way:
companies incorporated with Atlas automatically have a Stripe account,
and can get automatically get a Silicon Valley Bank account&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; set up so they
can start processing payments, via Stripe, immediately.
That’s extremely
powerful lead-gen.
But the potential for Atlas is much greater yet:
Atlas could automatically set up the company with a corporate credit card, and
all the required insurance.
It could set a customer up with a password manager, a virtual mail address,
accounting,
and so on. Each of these are multi-billion-dollar markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The endgame for Stripe Atlas is that it offers a
&lt;em&gt;business in a box&lt;/em&gt;, and
in turn it determines the B2B service&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; spend of such a business in perpetuity.
This is staggeringly powerful: first, it demolishes barriers to entry for
new entrepreneurs, handling all the tedious operational setup items, so the
entrepreneur can focus 100% on building a great product.
This is a real social good, for entrepreneurs and their customers around the entire globe.
Second, it puts up massive barriers to entry for competing service providers:
things like credit cards, insurance, accounting, virtual mail, etc. all
have low churn. Once a company launches with Atlas, a random
accounting service provider would effectively be forever locked out from
getting that company as a customer. Atlas reigns as gatekeeper supreme.
For an infrastructure company, owning the point at which customers otherwise
start to
&lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; their infrastructure is a position of unparalleled competitive strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclosure: I am not an employee of Stripe, paid by Stripe, and do not currently
have any financial interest in Stripe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As of April 2020, Stripe is valued at around $36 billion. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Of course, the day that Stripe gets a banking license, that’s going to be
a Stripe bank account. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While most of this is B2B SaaS, it’s noteworthy that not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of it
is strictly software (for example, accounting or legal services). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Stripe is a well-known innovator in digital payments. They attacked one of the most intimidating and locked-down markets, and made it look like child’s play. They have a compounding competitive edge in processing payments more efficiently for their customers, and the best-crafted APIs in the entire industry. Stripe is admired on these grounds, and more: they have their own press, in line with their thoughtful, public intellectual staff.</summary></entry></feed>