<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-05T09:21:09-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jay Riverlong</title><subtitle>Jay Riverlong's personal website. Essays and thoughts.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">No More Movies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/05/movies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No More Movies" /><published>2021-07-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/05/movies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/05/movies.html">&lt;p&gt;In my junior year of high school, I started getting into movies.
My English teacher, who was a serious film buff, warned me half-jokingly:
&lt;em&gt;in film, you start with the best and make your way down to the worst.&lt;/em&gt;
With literature, you grow as a reader and work your way up to the greatest works,
many of which are quite difficult.
But movies are much more accessible and don’t require nearly as much time,
so it’s easier to start with the great works.
Over the years you progress to movies that are more obscure, but
not necessarily better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early 2010, I started writing short reviews for every movie
I saw. This journal is now eleven years old and comprises 819 movies.
That’s 74 movies a year, or on average almost exactly one every five days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I feel exhausted by movies. I don’t enjoy them anymore.
Every couple of days I curl up on the couch
at 10pm, scroll through Amazon Prime video, and pick something to see.
It’s almost always a disappointment. This has been going on for months.
I feel like I’m scraping the bottom of the barrel.
The mere thought of sitting
through another blockbuster for two hours fills me with dread,
and a pre-emptive boredom so overwhelming that I’d rather go do the dishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I compare that to when I was a kid, and even movies that objectively weren’t very good
would have me totally immersed. Those films of childhood were special –
they’d fill me with wonder and ideas, inspiration for scenes to then recreate in
The Sims or Lego.
These days, sometimes I’m lucky and find that feeling of immersion and awe again.
But it happens so rarely that it no longer feels
worth the effort to rake for diamonds in the muck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened? I have a couple of ideas, but no firm conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TV and Film have switched spots.&lt;/strong&gt; In the 90s – a great decade for American film –
ambitious directors strived to make movies. TV was the “idiot box”. This has changed,
probably due to the advent of streaming, which structurally changed how
people consume media. Cinema has become a bad business, and feature films
are now the domain of reliable crowdpleasers like
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/04/opinion/martin-scorsese-marvel.html&quot;&gt;Marvel&lt;/a&gt; installments.
For ambitious indie directors in 2021, the medium of choice is the ten-episode miniseries.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-Censorship.&lt;/strong&gt;
Comedy was big in the early 2000s. Movies like Superbad or the Hangover
had meaningful impacts on popular culture.
But since 2012, the only successful comedies have been animations
aimed at young children.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
The 2000s-era teen/adult comedy has died out, despite
immense popularity. Why?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Adult comedy thrives on irreverence. Over the past decade, we’ve become touchy
about &lt;em&gt;what’s okay to say or laugh at&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;em&gt;Borat&lt;/em&gt; could not be made today.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
More generally, making challenging, contrarian films these days
basically requires you to be an established auteur.
Otherwise, the constraints on what films can get made (funded) grow tighter every year,
and viewers get &lt;em&gt;more of the same&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Stories are the Same.&lt;/strong&gt;
Kurt Vonnegut once said that there are only six types of story.
The fundamental constraints of the medium (and to a lesser extent, audience preferences)
lead to the same story being told, over and over again.
If you’ve seen an archetypal movie like &lt;em&gt;The Godfather&lt;/em&gt;, then there are hundreds
of films that will feel like boring, worse copies. Having seen lots of movies,
I do not recall the last time
I felt &lt;em&gt;surprised&lt;/em&gt; watching a movie.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You Learn the Tricks.&lt;/strong&gt; As an experienced viewer, you learn the directors’ tools.
&lt;em&gt;The main character isn’t going to die this early, there’s another hour in the movie.
That’s probably a Chekhov’s gun.&lt;/em&gt; As you learn all the common tropes and devices,
it becomes impossible &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to notice them, and movies become yet another layer of predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passive Media Consumption is Fundamentally Bad.&lt;/strong&gt;
Many years ago, a friend tried to convince me that the passive consumption
of any media – film or television, maybe even music – was bad for the soul.
To unthinkingly let a wave of content break over you is to inundate yourself
with noise, to be filled with other people’s mediocre thoughts and games.
Certainly, passively consuming media usually leaves me disillusioned:
time spent, but nothing gained. (Porn is the emptiest calorie of them all.)
Film is passive consumption by definition, because it’s best when you’re fully immersed.
I’m not sure if I agree that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; media is thus fundamentally and inescapably bad,
but much of it is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus comes the slow disappointment of watching movies.
First you don’t understand them.
Then you understand them, and they’re captivating.
Then you understand them too well, and they’re boring.
Special effects become ordinary,
deep movies become dull, groundbreaking themes become repetitive.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
You realize some revered directors are just hacks.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps worst of all is the realization that the movies you like are very rare,
and as you dive deep into film, you’re on a quest for the one-in-a-hundred
experience.
One of my favorite movies is &lt;em&gt;Eyes Wide Shut&lt;/em&gt;.
I have seen all movies that anyone on the internet has recommended as being
“like &lt;em&gt;Eyes Wide Shut&lt;/em&gt;”. Spoiler alert: none of them are. Not even close.
&lt;em&gt;Pulp Fiction&lt;/em&gt; had mass appeal, many directors tried to copy it, but it remains unique.
One of the great things
about movies is how many there are – you’d think the variety is enormous – but
as per points 1-4 above, it’s actually surprisingly narrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is one to do but re-watch one’s favorites?
That carries little novelty,
but maybe it’s good in that it’s self-limiting.
A saving grace for re-watching is that some films take multiple viewings to be appreciated,
and sometimes those viewings have to be spaced out over years.
Some movies can only be understood and &lt;em&gt;felt&lt;/em&gt; by people at a particular point in
their lives. My father’s favorite movie is &lt;em&gt;Lost in Translation&lt;/em&gt;. I found it
unrelatable, but maybe once I’ve gone through my forties and a mid-life crisis,
I will find it speak closely to me. Maybe that is what we do as moviegoers –
watch them so we know what to watch again – but I cannot shake how terribly
dissatisfying that labor is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Some people might consider &lt;em&gt;Deadpool&lt;/em&gt; of 2018 a comedy, but I wouldn’t.
I think it’s much more of a traditional superhero movie with some comedic elements. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Another argument you could advance is that TV and Film have generally
been moving away from &lt;em&gt;comedy&lt;/em&gt; as a genre. The sitcom-and-laugh-track era
appears to be over, thank heavens. TV has certainly become more high-brow
over the past decade, moving toward ambitious long-form stories.
Ultimately, comedy carries a connotation of cheap laughs, a lack of
sophistication, saying many words but communicating no &lt;em&gt;meaning&lt;/em&gt;.
To today’s generation of filmmakers, a comedy may feel like a dull proposition. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Borat sequel of 2020 could only be made because Sacha Baron Cohen
is already highly established and can afford to take risks, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; he was making
a sequel to one of the most popular comedies of all time.
(That’s predictable revenue.) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Split personality” is an interesting premise for a movie exactly &lt;em&gt;once&lt;/em&gt;
in the lifetime of the viewer, and thereafter it’s a dullard. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m nearly done with David Lynch’s oeuvre of work, and
my disappointment is immeasurable. For a full decade, I had Lynch in my mind
as one of the great names in American Cinema.
I watched Blue Velvet as a teen and was blown away.
And since then it’s been all downhill.
Mulholland Drive was okay.
&lt;em&gt;Fire Walk with Me&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Lost Highway&lt;/em&gt; are obviously awful movies
that he had no clue – zero, nada, zilch – how to tie together
into a satisfying story or ending.
Twin Peaks after the third or fourth episode was a similar disaster.
Lynch apologists will write “ooh, he’s so quirky and ~weird~”, but no,
the weirness is a side-effect of the man being incapable of seeing a story through. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In my junior year of high school, I started getting into movies. My English teacher, who was a serious film buff, warned me half-jokingly: in film, you start with the best and make your way down to the worst. With literature, you grow as a reader and work your way up to the greatest works, many of which are quite difficult. But movies are much more accessible and don’t require nearly as much time, so it’s easier to start with the great works. Over the years you progress to movies that are more obscure, but not necessarily better.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aging into Irrationality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/26/irrationality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aging into Irrationality" /><published>2021-06-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/26/irrationality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/26/irrationality.html">&lt;p&gt;My parents are smart, well-educated people.
But as they hit their fifties and sixties,
they started having fearful views on flying.
They’re both still frequent flyers
and not afraid of flying &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;,
but they became very particular about which airlines and planes are “safe” and which aren’t.
When the Boeing 737 Max safety debacle happened, they were drumming about it for
weeks – talking about never flying Boeing again – even though boarding the 737 Max was still
obviously statistically safer than driving, or crossing the street.
They understood the stats, but somehow emotion had them gripped tight.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it strange to see my parents become irrationally afraid over the years.
But as I’ve become older, I’ve begun to see hints of the same in me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, I became afraid of heights. I’m not sure why. It happened almost overnight.
Before, I could walk over bridges with thin railings and steep drops, sit on
chairlifts of absurd heights, and dance on forty-storieth balconies.
These days, the same scenarios put me in an anxious panic.
That feels very weird: for most of my life, I’ve been in control
of my emotions, generally unafraid of anything.
And all of a sudden, mid-way through being 28, deep anxiety over heights
starts dictating how I live my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, I’ve been thinking about going vegetarian.
My position on meat has always been
that animals carry zero moral value, i.e. eating chicken isn’t
different from eating beans.
But the idea of eating
animals is becoming more and more &lt;em&gt;gross&lt;/em&gt; to me.
My moral position is unchanged, but
almost inexplicably, it’s the idea of the animal itself – an alien but familiar lifeform,
living, breathing, getting slaughtered, and so on – that is becoming uncomfortable to me.
The more it’s on my mind, the more of a visceral repulsion I feel. Rational? No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, it feels like my rationality of thought is very slowly being replaced
by emotional compulsion.
I have a hunch this is symptomatic of information overload, as if
my thinking is becoming unclear, polluted with &lt;em&gt;too much stuff&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a child and young adult, I navigated reasonably simple universes
of information.
I was highly rational (probably unusually so), and extremely consequent in how I made my decisions –
I didn’t really think about anything other than what I was trying to optimize.
Inadvertently, I cut through the noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the noise is too thick to cut through. I’m sitting on the emotional accumulation of decades of life,
a mass of experiences and information cluttering my mind.
I’m distracted all the time by notions of second-order effects, what-if edge cases,
weird traumas, and social virtue signals.
I suspect that when there’s such a morass of information that it becomes difficult
to navigate, emotions take over as a shortcut to analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s neither surprising nor necessarily bad that we rely more on our emotions as we age.
When we’re younger, we have no experience, so we (should) have to reason about
things from first principles. As we get older, we accumulate experience, which
gives rise to valuable but intangible things like &lt;em&gt;taste&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;intuition&lt;/em&gt;.
These are
emotional internalizations of lessons learned.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
It is very satisfying when
you can do very precise, very correct work just on intuition from years of experience.
The danger is that as you get older and older,
eventually you’re running &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; on intuition, not reason,
and the experiences that created your intuition become outdated.
You haven’t had to &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; in a long time, and usually you were right,
but slowly, you’re wrong more and more often. If you’ve let yourself rely too heavily on
intuition and haven’t kept flexing your thinking muscles, you’re in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful thinking is clear thinking, and
clear thinking is &lt;em&gt;simple&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
That requires structuring a huge mess of thoughts, and cutting through them
cleanly to get to the core.
The huge mess of thoughts only becomes larger as we become older,
and more inundated with information online.
Somewhat ironically, the more information you ingest, the harder you have to work
to maintain clarity of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;What’s interesting is that they seem afraid not so much for their own lives
as for the lives of their adult children. My parents are happy to fly together.
But if my siblings and I are on the same plane, my parents will be very upset.
“What if the plane crashes? Then it’s all for nothing!” In their minds,
losing
their children at this stage in life is a fate worse than death.
I suspect that having children
has a large, evolutionary cognitive effect on how we view and prioritize &lt;em&gt;risk&lt;/em&gt;
that it is a big part of aging into irrationality. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Some might call these curve fits to empirical data observed. The more data,
the better the curve fit. But such curve fits (intuitions) usually have
a lifespan: very little real-world time-series data has patterns that are permanent. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There’s been a recent scandal in the press about Peter Thiel having $5B in his Roth IRA.
It’s a perfect and funny example of successful, clear, and simple thinking –
putting startup stock in a self-directed Roth
is very easy and extremely valuable to do, but very few founders do it.
I suppose it is just an “unusual” thing to do – power to those who cut through the noise
and go for it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My parents are smart, well-educated people. But as they hit their fifties and sixties, they started having fearful views on flying. They’re both still frequent flyers and not afraid of flying per se, but they became very particular about which airlines and planes are “safe” and which aren’t. When the Boeing 737 Max safety debacle happened, they were drumming about it for weeks – talking about never flying Boeing again – even though boarding the 737 Max was still obviously statistically safer than driving, or crossing the street. They understood the stats, but somehow emotion had them gripped tight.1 What’s interesting is that they seem afraid not so much for their own lives &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fear of Injury: Reconnecting Body and Mind</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/08/falling.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fear of Injury: Reconnecting Body and Mind" /><published>2021-03-08T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-03-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/08/falling</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/08/falling.html">&lt;p&gt;The other week, I was riding my bicycle to the store. I’m in the bike lane.
A car rolls up on my left. There’s a traffic light.
Suddenly, the car swerves to make a right turn, over the bike lane, and cuts me off.
It hits my front wheel.
I slam my brakes, but it is too late. I fall over and
hit the ground. The car keeps driving. A second or two passes. I’m lying on the asphalt
trying to memorize the license plate. My wheels are spinning in the air.
Pumping with adrenaline, I pick myself up.
Miraculously, my bicycle is not bent. I’ve got tiny scrapes on my hands.
I have a bigger scrape on my knee – maybe two inches of road rash, a little bit of blood.
I brush off the dirt.
Nothing serious, I assess, and I get back on my bike, ride to the store – adrenaline still pumping, furious –
buy milk, and carefully ride on home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I rode home, I thought: when was the last time I had gotten a small scrape?
I couldn’t remember. Maybe it was literally a decade ago, when I played some pickup ice hockey
and wound up with a couple of small cuts after nasty falls on ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the years since, as I had literally never gotten injured, I had become afraid.
Having forgotten what it was like to take a tumble, that unknown became scarier and scarier.
I was terrified of crashing my bicycle. What if I fall?
Roller blading? Sounds like a great way to get road rash.
Rock climbing? No thanks.
Even riding a lime scooter felt a little anxiety-inducing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time indoors, looking at screens. COVID quarantine
made my lifestyle only more sedentary. This has many health effects,
but a rarely-discussed one is that your world of physical activity becomes smaller:
you become scared of activities where you could get just slightly hurt.
You lose the fitness and courage to take
on demanding stuff like kiteboarding. The thrills of mountain biking, surfing, and back-flips
become off limits. You’re just so damn comfortable all the time
that even going to the doctor’s to get vaccinated is a six-sigma earthquake-tier
disruption to your comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s bad. When I was a kid, I was pretty indoorsy, but I still got little scrapes
all the time. I fell off my bicycle more times than I can count. I got concussions,
smashed my Razor Scooter, and jumped off a lot of unreasonably tall structures.
I knew the limits of my physical world, and my body, very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an adult, it’s pathetic that my world became smaller.
When’s the last time I climbed anything? &lt;em&gt;When’s the last time you touched something that wasn’t man-made?&lt;/em&gt;
It’s like there’s a tactile, physical sense that slowly gets lost as your fingers just run up and down a keyboard all day.
It feels like I spent too
much time living in my mind and not enough in my body, or even being aware of it.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
You work out, get in good shape, but for what? To impress others in a game where
muscles are a status symbol?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; What happened to enjoying your body by &lt;em&gt;using it&lt;/em&gt;,
flexing its limits, feeling its power as you physically conquer the elements?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No citizen has a right to be an amateur in the matter of physical training. What a disgrace it is for a man to grow old without ever seeing the beauty and strength of which his body is capable.&lt;/em&gt; - Socrates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socrates’ commentary on physical fitness was apt, but
it needs to be updated for the twenty-first century of
sterile gym machines and hyper-optimized workouts:
it is a tragedy to be so sedentary that you are hesitant to
get physical with nature.
To be afraid of minor injuries that your body has evolved
to be able to sustain a thousand times over. Our bodies are amazingly capable,
and most of us never put them even remotely to the test. Taleb would say
that we’re becoming fragile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t love getting into a traffic accident. But it was good to pick up a small scrape.
It blew away a lot of fear, and reminded me just how capable and resilient the body is.
I’m too young to feel so fragile. I’m determined to head out there more,
play with my hands, climb stuff, get physical with nature.
So what if I fall?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Paul Skallas &lt;a href=&quot;https://paulskallas.substack.com/p/book-rec-5&quot;&gt;reminded me&lt;/a&gt; that
in our Western society, it’s been common since the days of Descartes
to view the body and mind as very separate – the mind as the supreme thing
in a meaningless vessel. I think this view is largely mistaken. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A great, tangentially related read: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bloodknife.com/everyone-beautiful-no-one-horny/&quot;&gt;Everyone is Beautiful and No One is Horny&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The other week, I was riding my bicycle to the store. I’m in the bike lane. A car rolls up on my left. There’s a traffic light. Suddenly, the car swerves to make a right turn, over the bike lane, and cuts me off. It hits my front wheel. I slam my brakes, but it is too late. I fall over and hit the ground. The car keeps driving. A second or two passes. I’m lying on the asphalt trying to memorize the license plate. My wheels are spinning in the air. Pumping with adrenaline, I pick myself up. Miraculously, my bicycle is not bent. I’ve got tiny scrapes on my hands. I have a bigger scrape on my knee – maybe two inches of road rash, a little bit of blood. I brush off the dirt. Nothing serious, I assess, and I get back on my bike, ride to the store – adrenaline still pumping, furious – buy milk, and carefully ride on home.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lolita, Fourteen Years Later</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/06/lolita.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lolita, Fourteen Years Later" /><published>2021-03-06T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-03-06T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/06/lolita</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/06/lolita.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lolita, light of my life, fire of my loins. My sin, my soul.&lt;/em&gt;
So open these infamous pages. I first read them when I was sixteen.
I was just starting on serious literature: I had read &lt;em&gt;Gatsby&lt;/em&gt; for the first time,
and was mesmerized.
A friend – deeper and edgier than I –
recommended &lt;em&gt;Lolita&lt;/em&gt; next, and off I went with a paperback
from my local library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourteen years later, I am thirty. We are here again because
I know that much of what I had read or seen as a child had gone
far over my head.
I was always too analytical to see the
forest for the trees: I wrote movie reviews about cinematography
but couldn’t speak about the plot.
I dissected poems by meter and imagery,
but had no idea what they meant.
Even for &lt;em&gt;Gatsby&lt;/em&gt;, I appreciated the beautifully crafted prose,
but the human essence of the story had passed me by.
I expected that &lt;em&gt;Lolita&lt;/em&gt;
too had key parts that I had missed.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was sixteen, I finished the text knowing that I had witnessed
a work of great, haunting beauty. The prose was second to none;
lyrical and evocative in its wordplay, steeped in staggering creativity and
cleverness. On a second read, this holds entirely.
Humbert Humbert’s narration remains vivid and engrossing,
sometimes so much so
that you cannot help but feel depraved Humbert tugging at your heartstrings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a teen, moral judgment came with caveats.
Obviously Humbert was despicable.
But, ever so eloquent and pathetic, he could capture grains of sympathy.
I grappled with the question posed by Robertson Davies: &lt;em&gt;is Lolita
about the corruption of an innocent child by a cunning adult, or about the
exploitation of a weak adult by a corrupt child?&lt;/em&gt; As an adult,
this question is easily answered. Humbert is a monster, monster, monster,
through and through. He turns an innocent child into his sex slave.
Moral condemnation could not be more clear-cut.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why was it hard for me to pass absolute judgment on Humbert on my first read?
First, as a teenage boy with a reasonably stable home life,
it was hard to truly &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; the pain
and suffering of sexual abuse.
I understood that it was wrong and worthy of condemnation,
but I was just too young to understand or feel the sheer magnitude of that wrongness.
With no frame of reference,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
it remained abstract and somewhat inaccessible to true empathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, as a teenager it was difficult to understand the
power imbalance between a child and an adult.
You can’t know what it’s like to be an adult without having been one.
You figure that adults are bigger, older versions of you, but you don’t really know
what that means beyond drinking or voting.
As an adult, you know exactly how
much you’ve grown and how your sixteen-year-old self was
all kinds of naive and immature.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As an adult reader, Humbert’s manipulation, coercion,
and exploitation of a helpless orphan is clear as day, leaving not a shadow of nuance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humbert’s depravity comes out of his self-absorption: he is boundlessly arrogant,
and does not see the humanity of anyone else, least of all Lolita.
This is a &lt;em&gt;solipsist&lt;/em&gt; novel: told by self-obsessed Humbert,
he views only himself and his feelings as real, even his “love” for Lolita is not
love for her as a person but obsession with &lt;em&gt;an idea of a Lolita&lt;/em&gt; in his mind.
There was a thread of solipsist-existentialist fiction in the early 20th century,
and &lt;em&gt;Lolita&lt;/em&gt; fits in with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lolita is also a &lt;em&gt;surrealist&lt;/em&gt; novel.
Surrealism was the premier force in the arts for decades prior, and
&lt;em&gt;Lolita&lt;/em&gt; nods to them: it is full of outrageously unlikely coincidences,
and Humbert’s vaudevillian descriptions leave an undercurrent of mad distortion
throughout. The final scenes, with Humbert at his most deranged, may well be a
dream sequence. It wouldn’t be surprising, since
&lt;em&gt;Lolita&lt;/em&gt; is full of references to psychoanalysis.
Nabokov was catching the end of the mania Freud and Jung
had kicked off, and it’s clear that Nabokov held none of it in high esteem.
The psychoanalytic commentary throughout the novel ranges from dubious to farcical.
It is interesting to see &lt;em&gt;Lolita&lt;/em&gt; not just as a novel unto itself, but placed
precisely at the end of the solipsist, surrealist, and psychoanalytic movements,
like punctuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;em&gt;Lolita&lt;/em&gt; is a story about no closure.
Humbert blames his acts on the non-consummation of his childhood relationship. He seeks that
closure in Lolita – even trying to recreate that exact same moment with her –
but his efforts are futile. Lolita too denied him catharsis;
the relationship ends abruptly, but his hopes remain open. When he finally
kills his rival Quilty,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; there is no satisfaction either. Quilty, intoxicated out of his mind,
can’t even listen to Humbert’s grand monologue of justice,
and won’t submit to Humbert’s dreams of glorious execution.
From his cell, Humbert hopes that his Lolita will
live on long after him and be commemorated in his work,
but she dies promptly, and his work – the novel – does not commemorate &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt;.
Given Humbert’s dehumanization of Lolita, the novel provides
no view into her life, feeling, hopes, or dreams – it only commemorates Humbert’s depravity.
So crumble even his final hopes at posthumous closure.
Nothing wraps up cleanly in this story; all ends are &lt;a href=&quot;https://jayriverlong.github.io/2020/11/17/snicket.html&quot;&gt;left frayed by humans&lt;/a&gt;,
and fixed only by fate’s hand of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;!-- commenting this out in case i ever want to recycle it... think the first paragraph
i've already basically included, and the second paragraph isn't really worth diving in on

[^9]: Actually, there were two more observations that didn't merit inclusion in the body proper,
    so forgive me as I shamelessly stick them into this footnote:


    The first is that Humbert is an *everyday asshole*. He's already a rapist monster, of course,
    but he also has no redeeming interactions with others.
    In fact, he is boundlessly arrogant, self-absorbed, judgmental, and hateful toward others.
    He does not see the humanity of anyone but himself,
    certainly not of any women (with possible exception of Lolita at the very end).
    Other characters, even his own wives, appear surrounded by insults.
    To him, they are brainless, porcine, sallow, phocine,[^4] stale-fleshed, hideous, babbling, absurd,
    scampering, scurrying, swines, Boschian cripples, and so on. As a teenager, you may have some appetite
    for edgy cynicism and snarky insults. As an adult, you've seen enough pitiful, hateful men
    to spot Humbert chief among their ranks.


    The second is that Humbert is a *loser*.
    He presents himself as an academic,
    an erudite scholar, and fools many characters with his professorial air.
    To an adult, it is clear that Humbert as a lazy dilettante.
    He is a trust-fund layabout, his work is forever unfinished,
    and what he shows of it is laughably bad.
    The novel contains one or two of his terrible poems,
    and his one publication that he names -- &quot;The Proustian theme in a letter from Keats to Benjamin Bailey&quot;
    -- is, if you know who these people are, utterly ridiculous by its title alone.
    The combination of everyone's-an-idiot-but-me condescension,
    farcically pretentious &quot;scholarly work&quot; and self-importance reminded me of Ignatius J. Reilly
    from *A Confederacy of Dunces*. I found myself reading
    Humbert's preposterous, stilted self-aggrandizements, and thought they could've come
    straight off the page of *Dunces*.

[^4]: Seal-like, which admittedly is a hysterical way to describe a fellow beachgoer.
--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On my not-particularly-difficult quest to see all of Kubrick’s films,
I also watched the 1962 film rendition of Lolita when I was nineteen,
in an airport lounge of all places.
Beside dim memories of a few scenes, I don’t remember the film. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And Robertson Davies seems like one hell of a creep with his Humbert-apologist thesis. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are also details in the book, iceberg-style suggestions that
hint at the horrid &lt;em&gt;extent&lt;/em&gt; of the abuse that I did not pick up on as a teen.
The novel has very few scenes that are explicitly sexual, and I think
you have to be an adult to read into what’s implied. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is a little like when you were in high school, and one of your &lt;em&gt;very cool&lt;/em&gt; friends
was in fact so cool and mature and grown up that they were dating someone in their 20s.
As an adult, of course, you know that the people in their 20s dating high schoolers
are walking, talking, red flags. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I wasn’t sure whether Humbert or Quilty is the greater villain of the story.
Perhaps that’s the point: both are utterly reprehensible, and such monsters are
not unique but rather crawling in the woodwork everywhere. Lolita finally tells us that
she would rather go back to live with Quilty, a child pornographer who broke her heart, than Humbert.
This tells us all we need to know to hammer the final nail of judgment into Humbert’s coffin. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Lolita, light of my life, fire of my loins. My sin, my soul. So open these infamous pages. I first read them when I was sixteen. I was just starting on serious literature: I had read Gatsby for the first time, and was mesmerized. A friend – deeper and edgier than I – recommended Lolita next, and off I went with a paperback from my local library.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Advice? Just Say No</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/27/advice.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advice? Just Say No" /><published>2021-02-27T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/27/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/27/advice.html">&lt;p&gt;Advice is dangerous.
Like a horoscope, advice
often sounds well-crafted and relevant,
but believing it is rarely productive.
With clever turns of phrase and time-honored proverbs, you can
turn any position into an elegant, self-evident truth.
“One bird in the hand is better than two in the bush” say some, and others
respond “never compromise, doubling down is the only way to succeed”.
“The customer is always right” but also “sometimes you gotta fire your customer.”
Warren Buffett is quoted religiously for his investment advice,
and a big reason for that is that he has given so much advice
in his career that you can quote him to argue one way, and quote him for the
counter-argument too. What is one to believe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programmers learn this early on in their careers. On a late night debugging
an issue, they’ll Google the error message to find… &lt;a href=&quot;https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/wisdom_of_the_ancients.png&quot;&gt;no results&lt;/a&gt;.
Every other issue could be solved by copy-pasting from StackOverflow,
but not this one. A sinking feeling sets in. &lt;em&gt;You’re on your own now&lt;/em&gt;.
No advice will help you now, you have to figure it out yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other, less mechanical domains, such moments are rare.
There’s always relevant-seeming advice.
Career advice is full of idiosyncratic and contradictory positions,
and business advice legendarily so.
The contradictory diversity is because when people give advice, it tends to directly
reflect their own experiences,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and most people’s experiences
are quite different from one another. Businesses can be startlingly unique
in the details, so it’s no surprise that one person will tell you
to focus on scalability, and another will tell you to do things that don’t scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because advice is usually a generalization of “this worked for me”, it’s important
to see that advice is usually &lt;em&gt;reasoning by analogy&lt;/em&gt;, which is dangerous.
“If we say that
your situation is like mine fifteen years ago, then you should do this…”
is the silent preamble that should caveat most advice.
It breaks the same way that reasoning by analogy does:
surprise surprise, your situations are not
actually analogous. They’re different in the details, and the details matter.
Most advice is not good or bad, but &lt;em&gt;inapplicable&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But surely there exists useful advice? Yes, there exist &lt;em&gt;playbooks&lt;/em&gt;. At scale,
collectives of people have figured out roughly how to optimize a process. There’s a playbook
for getting into a good college. There’s a playbook for interviewing at Amazon,
starting a B2B SaaS company, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%C3%A1szl%C3%B3_Polg%C3%A1r&quot;&gt;becoming a Chess Grandmaster&lt;/a&gt;.
These playbooks are syntheses of successful approaches, like people
figuring out together how to speed-run a video game.
However, in the real world, the territory is always changing.
These playbooks, even good ones like YC’s
Startup School, have expiration dates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are you to do if there’s no playbook? Well, you’re on your own.
Silicon Valley types would say “think from first principles”,
which is generally
your best bet, but it can be hard to get the premises right.
More importantly,
it’s time to trust yourself.
If you are in an area with no playbooks,
you have graduated to the frontier.
You are there because you are good at what you do.
If you are good at what you do, then why not double down on your own
intuition?
&lt;em&gt;Do what you think is best&lt;/em&gt; is usually good advice to those
who have already shown exceptional capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony that this is an advice post does not escape me. Of course it follows my own
experience: in my younger days I spent much time seeking mentorship and advice.
The advice I received was generally not very good.
I remember running my first prospective
angel investment past a number of venture capitalists I respected.
They all passed, citing various qualms.
The investment seemed like a no-brainer to me,
but given the bearishness of these experts,
I passed, thinking “surely there’s something I’m not getting here”. In the end, all the investors
were wrong, my intuition was right, their advice was just noise and I missed a phenomenal deal.
From there on I stopped listening to what others said, and strictly followed my own judgement:
if I’m here, I got here because I’m good at what I do, and so I’ll just trust myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is full of noise. Advice is a combination of people’s genuine opinions and their
performative signalling, repeating the tenets of their in-group.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
This form of noise is omnipresent, and it’ll pull you in all directions.
You could spend all day listening to two business gurus give perfectly contradictory advice; it
all nets out to zero. For the most part, just listening to it will &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jayriverlong/status/1346370366336163844?s=20&quot;&gt;muddy your thinking&lt;/a&gt;
and lead you through all sorts of mental contortions to conform to the intellectual aesthetics of others,
instead of carving the way you believe to be true.
There’s a way to cut through the noise: ignore it, trust yourself, research carefully, reason rigorously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is excepting an even more dangerous form of advice, the purely theoretical
advice given by someone who has zero practical experience with the subject matter. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Extremely common in business contexts. “Naval says…”, “Charlie Munger says…”,
and so on. These are fortune cookies not intended to communicate any meaningful truth about the world,
but to signal that you follow the same gurus and belong to the same group. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Advice is dangerous. Like a horoscope, advice often sounds well-crafted and relevant, but believing it is rarely productive. With clever turns of phrase and time-honored proverbs, you can turn any position into an elegant, self-evident truth. “One bird in the hand is better than two in the bush” say some, and others respond “never compromise, doubling down is the only way to succeed”. “The customer is always right” but also “sometimes you gotta fire your customer.” Warren Buffett is quoted religiously for his investment advice, and a big reason for that is that he has given so much advice in his career that you can quote him to argue one way, and quote him for the counter-argument too. What is one to believe?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Infidelity Online: Simping and Sex in 2020</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/19/infidelity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Infidelity Online: Simping and Sex in 2020" /><published>2021-02-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/19/infidelity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/19/infidelity.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently turned thirty years old. I had my first kiss when I turned fifteen,
so now
half my life has been threaded by a continuous push-pull tango with women.
With every romantic interest there is a dance of desire and rejection,
moves for the other person to catch and play.
Dating and dancing are alike – when it’s good, you feel a fluidity and belonging that is
hard to surpass.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the dancers eventually get tired, maybe by themselves or more directly of each other.
Every step has been explored, and
the journey of getting to know another person eventually ends. You arrive
as one. That is magical, and there may be new things to discover together,
but the rush of diving deep with a stranger is long gone.
What happens then? Do you keep dancing, or do you head to the bar for a drink,
and find someone new to dance with?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve turned thirty and the notion of long-term monogamous relationships slowly
becomes an overwhelming force of gravity in my life, I have been thinking about infidelity.
The truth is that I’ve always been somewhat drawn to it.
And in our Western, Christian culture, it seems hard to discuss that openly.
Despite clear empirical evidence, the mere
acknowledgement that monogamy can be &lt;em&gt;difficult&lt;/em&gt; seems mostly taboo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core issue is that dating short-term and long-term are qualitatively very different.
Those who are single miss the serene stability and trust of a multi-year relationship,
the peace of sitting around the kitchen table figuring out your tax returns. Married folks
miss the head-over-heels intensity and craziness of dating in their early twenties.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Our public discourse frames
this as an evolution where the long-term is superior, the refined version
of the short-term.
That may well be true, but
it is a trade-off between very different experiences. You can’t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; have both,
and those who try rarely succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been in many relationships: a few days here, a few years there.
In my multi-year relationships, the
routine of the dance had me occasionally missing the single life and
peeking at other partners, especially as the pressures of true long-term commitment
began to mount.
That wasn’t a conscious thing, but something I seemed to do automatically.
I might run into a cute girl, and instinctively dial up my charm to 11.
I would not ask her for her number, but I would do
everything short of that – like I’m testing that I still got it, and
the way she’s looking at me, I know that if I were to ask her out she would say yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe these flirtations with infidelity are taboo-ish-but-universal experiences.
However, 2020’s dual prongs of isolation and extremely-online-ness have changed
the context of sex. With most people stuck at home and their
sex lives having fallen off a cliff, it seems that the online
public square has become much more sexual. For crying out loud, &lt;em&gt;simping&lt;/em&gt; is a part
of the national vocabulary now. This is no coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remarkably, the personas of online sex work have changed:
porn used to be done by strict acting professionals in studios. It seems that
the most popular porn now is produced by couples, and women who clearly have boyfriends.
OnlyFans is full of them. It’s like we’ve dropped a layer of pretense about the whole thing.
Women who have boyfriends produce porn that is watched by men who have girlfriends.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
It’s &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; a love square. Abstractly, there’s something about this that feels
like wife-swapping with a few steps removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growing prevalence of online sex work, the normalization of simping,
horny on main, etc. all feeds
into a culture that is more open to the sexual (not necessarily romantic)
desire for a person other than your romantic partner.
It is in this context that I think about infidelity:
lots of people have a
combined (1) nostalgia
for the parties and one-night stands of years ago
and (2) pent-up sexual desire for novelty.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
They may not seek a real change romantically, but their biologies&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
leave them hungry for conquest. The changing sexual environment online
is opening up and normalizing many avenues for satisfaction here,
but it’s stopping just short of allowing that actual, in-person physical moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will this change? The stigmas against infidelity – whether permitted or not – in real life
are powerful. The stigmas against infidelity &lt;em&gt;online&lt;/em&gt; are blurry at best:
partners in couples watch porn and get sexual gratification independently.
Wife Guys on Twitter lust after e-girls. Women with
boyfriends sell nudes to thousands of male strangers. It feels like the digital and physical
worlds may not have differing standards for &lt;em&gt;romance&lt;/em&gt;, but they have vastly differing standards
for &lt;em&gt;sex&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, people bundled the notions of romance and sex into one.
Progressives have unbundled the two somewhat – one is possible without the other –
but we’re now at a second unbundling: online vs. offline.
Online, there seems to be a weird new liminal space of behavior and morality,
challenging how we think about sex, and making &lt;em&gt;infidelity&lt;/em&gt; blurry in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The open question is how these standards will interplay in the future. Maybe we’ll
live in a world where real life remains overwhelmingly culturally monogamous
and supportive of the nuclear-family model,
but digital life turns into more and more of a polyamorous playscape.
It would be a strange world, where certain thoughts about people in three dimensions
are taboo, but in two dimensions it’s A-OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gets weirder when you think about
the implications of future advances in sex-tech. Like, is masturbation cheating?
Most people will say no.
Is it cheating to be plugged into your VR Headset while wearing a Stimulatron 3000
Codpiece to have your 57th sexual encounter with your virtually AI-generated partner?
Is it cheating when, post-orgasm, that same Siri-voiced partner softly reassures you about your
childhood traumas?
Beats me. The very norms themselves are in for a rollercoaster ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Done poorly, dancing and dating both feel awkward and only heighten your self-awareness
and insecurities. Bad dates and bad dances feel like unwieldy objects colliding. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I suspect that a partial driver of affairs is simple nostalgia. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are other cases, of course, but I think this represents reasonably
accurately a plurality, if not majority of cases. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Incidentally, you really see the influence of the internet in how porn
has changed between 1990 and 2020. A world of difference: from 90-minute long
B-movies with actual plots to twelve-minute shots of three positions with a
preposterous and irrelevant setup. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The astute reader might point out that it’s not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; biology, but a whole host
of societal, anthropological, etc. factors. I’m willing to lump all of these into one
here, though I appreciate that such compulsions are multivariate in their causes. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently turned thirty years old. I had my first kiss when I turned fifteen, so now half my life has been threaded by a continuous push-pull tango with women. With every romantic interest there is a dance of desire and rejection, moves for the other person to catch and play. Dating and dancing are alike – when it’s good, you feel a fluidity and belonging that is hard to surpass.1 Done poorly, dancing and dating both feel awkward and only heighten your self-awareness &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Institutional Seed Rounds are Bad for Founders</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/07/seed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Institutional Seed Rounds are Bad for Founders" /><published>2021-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/07/seed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/07/seed.html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote my first angel checks in 2014. I’ve now written almost 70.
The landscape has changed greatly: back in the day,
I would see seed rounds valued at $4-8M post-money, with $1-2M invested
so the investors would get about 25% of the company.
To boot, the lead investor would usually get a board seat,
and the company would take another 10% dilution in form of an options pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2021, deals at $4-8M post-money are called pre-seeds.
Today’s seed has crept toward the Series A of old, with post-money valuations
generally not below $10M, the median in the $12M-15M range, and the high end
at $20M or beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fantastic that founders are able to raise at greater valuations, and commensurately more money.
Instead of raising $1M at $4M post, founders today are raising $3M at $12M post. That’s great, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, maybe. You’ll notice that the &lt;em&gt;investor ownership&lt;/em&gt; at the seed stage – 25% – is the only
element that has remained constant. The founder is still &lt;em&gt;selling the same amount of the company&lt;/em&gt;.
They’re getting more dollars in return. Is that a good deal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, maybe. Dollars in the bank have diminishing returns for a seed-stage founder.
Can you make productive use of $250K on day one? Totally. $1M? Probably, over 12-18 months.
$3M? It gets harder to allocate larger amounts of capital efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is compounded by the fact that successful startups are now raising rounds &lt;em&gt;faster&lt;/em&gt; than before.
VCs are hungry to deploy capital, so follow-on rounds and pre-empts are happening more than before.
I’ve seen companies raise their Series As at good valuations while only half-way to the “traditional” Series A
benchmark. I’ve seen Series Bs three months after the A. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this environment, VCs are under significant pressure to deploy their funds.
They aggressively push capital on founders.
The result is that good companies are raising, at the seed stage, capital they will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; deploy.
And that’s a waste of the dilution they take on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strong startups are raising monster seed rounds, $3M plus.
In the old paradigm, that would be for a 18-24 month runway,
so implying an average spend of $125-167k a month.
Actually doing that &lt;em&gt;productively&lt;/em&gt; is hard.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
It implies building a 15+ person team.
That’s tough in itself. But now you actually need to deploy &lt;em&gt;even faster&lt;/em&gt;,
because the old paradigm has been broken.
If you’re good, you may no longer need 18 or 24 months to get to the Series A.
You’ll get there in 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, suppose you raised a $3M seed, and you get to your Series A in 12 months.
You’ve still got $2M in the bank.
You &lt;em&gt;paid&lt;/em&gt; 17% of your company – a co-founder-level chunk – for that capital.
You gave away a board seat. You swallowed the options pool shuffle.
All that for capital that you now don’t need.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You raise your Series A.
The press will cheer you on for being capital efficient.
Your friends will congratulate you on the great brand name that’s getting put on your website
and on your board. And you will bow and shake hands and perform all the social graces,
with the venture capital force-feeding tube still
hanging out of your mouth. But knowing that you’ve thrown away 17% of your company
at the seed should make you sick to your stomach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maybe you’ll raise a smaller seed. You’d like the same valuation, of course.
But the institutions won’t like that.
“Sorry, we have a minimum ownership requirement of 20%”, they’ll tell you.
Needless to say, minimum ownership requirements are bullshit.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is a founder to do? The simple answer is to abandon the institutional raise,
and stick with angels and angel-style investors. This is another big change since 2014:
the number of angels in the market must have increased 100-fold. I’m being hyperbolic,
but it feels like half the valley is angel investing these days.
&lt;em&gt;Everyone&lt;/em&gt;, VC firms and individuals alike, are aggressively deploying capital.
Importantly, angels will pay institutional valuations, and the better ones are
so well-networked that they can help you put together an entire round.
It’s now well possible to put together a multi-million dollar round without a traditional venture firm
involved: the best example is probably &lt;a href=&quot;https://tech.eu/brief/front-series-c/&quot;&gt;Front’s Series C&lt;/a&gt;,
a $59M round led entirely
by individuals, with traditional VC firms only getting small allocations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four other key benefits to skipping the institutions as you break your round down
for many smaller checks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The use of SAFEs enables &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/hiresfund.html&quot;&gt;high-resolution fundraising&lt;/a&gt;.
Close parties as they commit. You
no longer need to get everyone together in an institutional round to close. (Of all rounds that collapse,
timing is usually the main factor.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No board seats. If you don’t have a lead investor, then no investor has the muscle to negotiate
themselves meaningful corporate control.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many small investors who hustle usually constitute a bigger, more helpful network than your one point-person at a VC firm,
 particularly for early-stage companies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You dictate the deal terms. Again, with no lead investor, no-one has the muscle to force better terms for themselves.
 You’re in control.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a competitive time in the market. Many people, myself included, have written
about how &lt;a href=&quot;https://jayriverlong.github.io/2020/08/16/spac.html&quot;&gt;personal brands are disrupting venture capital&lt;/a&gt;
via Rolling Funds and other mechanisms. it turns out that going with the newly liquid kids on the block
has material advantages over going with the capital gatekeepers of old. This is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Startups can burn capital aggressively, pay for top-tier services and best-in-class salaries,
but that kind of spending culture usually sets up for difficult conversations about operating
economics at later stages, so I can’t recommend it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Astute readers will point out that maybe it wasn’t so unwise to take on more capital,
because you &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; not have gotten to your Series A so quickly. Sure. However,
in our example, tacking on a six or twelve-month buffer would have implied only another 4-8% dilution,
as opposed to the 17%. You’re still talking about a &lt;strong&gt;massive&lt;/strong&gt; piece of equity. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are many respects in which they are bullshit, and many reasons for it,
but going through all of them in detail seems like good material for another essay. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I wrote my first angel checks in 2014. I’ve now written almost 70. The landscape has changed greatly: back in the day, I would see seed rounds valued at $4-8M post-money, with $1-2M invested so the investors would get about 25% of the company. To boot, the lead investor would usually get a board seat, and the company would take another 10% dilution in form of an options pool.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bitcoin and Secrecy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/27/bitcoin.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bitcoin and Secrecy" /><published>2020-12-27T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/27/bitcoin</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/27/bitcoin.html">&lt;p&gt;Growing up, I read mysteries and pirate stories. Buried treasure, hidden behind
cryptic puzzles. I read Dan Brown novels about secret societies and great meanings
hidden in small messages. In the modern day, it seemed that this romantic notion
of secrecy – that great wealth can be hidden in small messages – was over forever.
Your money sits in bank accounts, with brokerage firms, in contracts, and so forth.
Hiding a treasure? &lt;em&gt;Owning&lt;/em&gt; something that only you have control over? Good luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt some sadness that this era of simple mystery and treasure seemed over.
(To be fair, more transparency is also a good thing.) But Bitcoin changes this:
you can store an arbitrary amount of wealth behind a single private key. And you
can turn that single private key into a twelve-word passphrase. You can destroy
the key, and remember just those twelve words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, &lt;strong&gt;your identity&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;your memory&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;your money&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;your speech&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turn your passphrase into a song or a poem and write it down, there’s your cryptic puzzle
hiding a treasure. Split it into pieces and hide them with seven objects in
obscure corners of the world, there are your horcruxes. There’s the substrate for
true ownership, for guarding treasure, and for the mystery stories of old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplicity of Bitcoin – that ownership of a few words, short enough to be
remembered, can store arbitrary, uncensorable wealth – re-creates that romantic
notion of secrecy. The old map pointing to vast treasure is new again.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Growing up, I read mysteries and pirate stories. Buried treasure, hidden behind cryptic puzzles. I read Dan Brown novels about secret societies and great meanings hidden in small messages. In the modern day, it seemed that this romantic notion of secrecy – that great wealth can be hidden in small messages – was over forever. Your money sits in bank accounts, with brokerage firms, in contracts, and so forth. Hiding a treasure? Owning something that only you have control over? Good luck.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The San Francisco that Could Have Been</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/sf.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The San Francisco that Could Have Been" /><published>2020-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/sf</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/sf.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m running through Lands End. It’s 8AM on a winter day.
Cool mist hangs in the air, and
the gravel crunches under my running shoes.
I’m looking
at my Apple Watch, checking the time as I run down the hill, past the Cliff House,
looking at the Pacific as it shines in the morning sun
like a pool of liquid silver stretching to the horizon.
California is good.
I hear the waves crashing, and the air softly smells of salt and pines.
To my left,
I see the Pacific Towers:
eight fifty-five story glass obelisks stretching into the
sky, all connected by a public park up top, six hundred feet in the air.
A marvel of modern engineering, only paralleled by a few buildings in
Shanghai. The year is 2030. I’m fortunate to rent a one-bedroom in the Pacific Towers
for $2700 a month. I live on the fourteenth floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shower while Siri reads me my emails. “Archive, archive, skip, schedule for 10AM”:
speech recognition lets me take care of a full night of notifications.
Though my executive and product leaders are in San Francisco,
my company otherwise runs on a 24/7 global team, so work accumulates
throughout the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I step out of the shower. My bathroom’s ceiling fans all immediately point hot air at me
to help me dry off faster. (It’s cozy, too.) I’m rubbing my hair with a towel when
soft ringing emanates throughout the apartment. “Who is it?” I ask. “It’s Jess Bergman”
Siri replies. Six hundred speakers and microphones hidden in the walls throughout my 900 square feet
make it feel remarkably natural to talk to my virtual assistant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pick up”. Jess is on the phone. She’s telling me that one
of our customers, an oil-shipping company, suffered some kind of bizarre bug
where we dispatched one of their tankers without filling it entirely.
It’s a costly error – $8M in oil that’s left sitting somewhere.
Jess and I
suspect some of the customer’s tanker sensors are defective, and we line up
a diagnostic team to take a look. We sell logistical optimization
software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m heading down the elevator to the Pacific Towers to the underground BAMF stop.
BAMF was the 2022 successor to BART – everyone recognized “Bay Area Rapid Transit”
as a hilarious oxymoron, an embarrassment compared to our global peers, so our local
government and industry leaders created Bay Area Mega Fast: an autonomous metro system
modeled after the Hong Kong and Tokyo subways – just twice as fast. Trains arrive
every 30 seconds, and I’ll be at my office in the Tenderloin in exactly 114 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s only one stop in-between. I’m proud to say that my company helped design
some of the BAMF network for optimal throughput –
like all Bay Area projects, it’s a public-private partnership, and the government
brought in the best logistical optimizers from industry.
Even eight years ago, I’m flattered to say that was us. We’re better now,
but we still have a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m wearing my Raycasters inside the BAMF train.
They’re one brand of many smart glasses that overlay
useful information on my field of vision. I usually turn off the
auto-recognize, subtitles, and maps, but keep on my vital sign displays.
The data is beamed straight from my apple watch. Eyeball control makes it super easy
to navigate the interface. It seems that my blood sugar is a little low. I flick
through the suggestions. “Eat a quarter of a Snickers bar”, it says. Great, I’ve got some at the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m out the BAMF and straight up the elevator. My company has half the 85th floor
of the Civic Spiral. The building is a glass tornado. It was completed two years ago,
and it’s the tallest office building in the world. Rent here is unbelievably
expensive – nearly $200 per square foot per year. But it’s a good splurge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a meeting to talk about the status on the oil shipping bug
and get a little more clarity. I’m chatting with the team in Dubai, and my
EARS2 earphones do real-time translation from Arabic to English. It’s amazing.
The EARS2 founder is a buddy of mine, his office is just the floor below.
He’s got an unbelievable view of the Golden Gate Bridge and the Alcatraz International Airport,
where Elon Musk’s grasshopper rockets land and take off all day, sending San Francisco
residents around the globe at Mach 2 for lunch meetings. I think it’s extravagant, but to each their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I step out for lunch with Sam Fultzmann. He’s the craziest guy I know,
which is why I love having lunch with him.
We step outside the Civic Spiral and grab little electric longboards
to scoot to our favorite Shawarma shop. The longboards recognize me by RFID
sensor and automatically bill my Stripe bank account, accurately to the millionth of a dollar.
We arrive at Bilal’s Bar and Grill on Market Street.
The line for seating is forever long.
The GDP of the Tenderloin is nearly a trillion dollars now, but some things just don’t change.
We register ourselves for a seating spot
with a watch tap, and go for a walk under the trees while we wait.
San Francisco got a lot greener
after human-driven cars were banned in 2023. The streets were narrowed since
autonomous vehicles and personal things like bicycles and skateboards just needed
much less space. The fact that just seven years ago, people were driving around
twenty-foot-long trucks &lt;em&gt;for just themselves&lt;/em&gt; that they left parked 92% of the time
is so crazy that I can hardly fathom it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it’s winter, it’s pretty warm outside. There isn’t a building &lt;em&gt;under&lt;/em&gt; 300 feet around me,
it’s glass and concrete as far as the eye can see. That makes it a little warmer on the ground,
but the trees help, and there’s a Fremont company experimenting with upper-stratosphere reflective
seeding to mitigate global warming, which is the overarching culprit here.
I’m due to stop by there later today, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over lunch, Sam tells me that he angel invested in Telomize, a Palo Alto company that
does telomere lengthening for anti-aging. (Everyone’s an angel investor now that
there’s an income tax break if you invest your income in early-stage companies.)
We haven’t cracked the aging nut yet, but we’re close.
I quiz Sam about the prospects of the company, and he admits that he invested
just to get early access to their product. He’s on it right now. I joke that
it could be harmful, but Sam doesn’t care: whatever, there’s no regulatory body
that can stop him from experimenting with novel treatments.
He has an 8G feed
continuously streaming 200 GB a second of vital sign data back to Telomize
company to track the effectiveness and safety of the treatment. There are 35,000
other crazies like him, and between the lot of them they’re constructing a pretty good
medical study in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tell Sam about the oil problem. He tells me he read a book the other day
about Rockefeller and the Oil Magnates of the turn of the 20th century: “did you know
that Cleveland, Ohio used to be the wealthiest city in the United States?” he bursts
out, guffawing. “Cleveland? These guys don’t even have a space program”, I laugh.
(The Bay Area has three now, all private enterprise with some public backing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What happened?” I ask Sam. “Well, jeez, it’s like Cleveland just sort of found
itself in the middle of an oil boom, geographically. One year they were like
any other second-tier industrializing city, and then they suddenly had this
huge influx of wealth and enterprise that they didn’t really understand…
or know how to keep, once things started moving.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So what happened, specifically?” I ask. “Well, the same thing that happens whenever
you try to hold sand with your hands and don’t get a bucket: phoosh, it runs through
your fingers and then it’s gone. A few decades later the oil industry was in Oklahoma,
Texas, everywhere, and then Cleveland was just a small part of it. Standard Oil and what-have-you
relocated to New York City.” Sam takes a bite from his meatless burger.
“I think the people of Cleveland were so caught off-guard by the enormous opportunity
that hit them in the face that they reacted with some level of arrogance, hubris, and
spent their time kind of pooh-poohing the industry, not realizing how lucky they
were to be in pole position in the &lt;em&gt;competition&lt;/em&gt; for this ginormous industry.
So they were asleep at the wheel, and only when the industry moved into other cities
did the people of Cleveland understand, by the sheer voracity of competition,
 how valuable this new industry was.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You’re telling me the golden goose made a nest in their back yard and they basically
just stayed inside drinking beers and jacking off.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah. And sometimes plucking the goose for feathers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s the dumbest fucking thing I’ve ever heard.”
I’m looking up the Four Seasons Master Suites. Eight hundred feet of commercial and residential
real estate. In the top ten floors, each apartment has a private pool. It’s some of the
most valuable real estate on the planet, 4th and Market, downtown San Francisco,
the heart of the safest city in the United States, a technological metropolis,
a smoothly running engine generating compound growth of wealth every year,
the altar of innovation. A testament to the power of courageous people coming
together to build the future. Hong Kong and Singapore look sleepy by comparison.
“I guess if people fail to seize opportunity, that’s on them, and they kinda self-select,
they probably weren’t the right stewards of that opportunity in the first place.”
A little delivery drone flies by silently and drops off a package through an apartment window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get through the rest of the workday just fine. Our weekly 5PM resident’s poll
was pretty interesting: one item on the poll asked me to vote on whether or not
San Francisco should petition to host the 2032 International Kite Surfing Championships
at a cost of about $311.60 per taxpayer. I’m a big fan, so I voted in favor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rapidfire direct democracy
is a great way to make small changes, while the larger changes deserve much more diligent
debate. There’s currently a big discussion about whether the Sunset should have its
housing density increased – the average building is a 14-story midrise apartment
complex, interspersed with some commercial real estate. The debate is as to whether
the city should buy out homeowners in some of the shorter buildings and create more dense
skyscrapers that it can sell to new arrivals so as to keep rents low. Back in 2010,
there was a serious push in government to just keep increasing the housing stock any time
a one bedroom threatened to go over $3000 a month in rent, and now we have one of the world’s densest and
most economically productive cities.
It turns out that when you offer amazing opportunity at low cost,
an unbelievable caliber of talent concentrates. Sounds obvious, but even New York doesn’t get it.
Anyway, so there’s this big fuffle about whether to buy out six blocks of homeowners and construct another 6,000
family units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a little split because I think there are better immediate uses of capital than for the homeowner buyout –
I’d like to keep allocating R&amp;amp;D funds to the California State Semiconductor Company, for example.
I’m on the city’s Financial Optimization Committee, where maybe I’ll try to steer toward using some municipal debt product
to instead do the real estate thing, but there are a lot of variables at play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m wrapping up the day by chatting with Liza Wallen.
She runs the Fremont-based solar geoengineering firm I mentioned earlier.
As you can imagine, putting reflective particles into the upper stratosphere to block out the sun
was very
controversial when the G8 countries first started seriously considering it, but it was soon clear
that it was the only feasible way to curb global warming without relying on solving virtually impossible
coordination problems, like everyone dropping fossil fuels at once.
Liza’s company ended up presenting the most detailed (and compelling) effect models,
so they were one of five companies chosen globally to give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logistics of everything involved are difficult,
so my company has a contract with Liza’s firm to help them operate as efficiently as possible.
I would normally take the call by video from my home, but Liza in person is always great, so I’m heading to Fremont.
I’m not using BAMF because I can’t be bothered transferring between stations,
so I’m just calling a little Toaster Oven. That’s what we
call the Autonomous Taxis that ferry around small groups of people (their pickup routes optimized by yours truly) –
they’re these cute little boxes that look like toaster ovens and zip around at 80 miles an hour, which is pretty slow, but we’ll get an upgrade soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m running through Lands End. It’s 8AM on a winter day. Cool mist hangs in the air, and the gravel crunches under my running shoes. I’m looking at my Apple Watch, checking the time as I run down the hill, past the Cliff House, looking at the Pacific as it shines in the morning sun like a pool of liquid silver stretching to the horizon. California is good. I hear the waves crashing, and the air softly smells of salt and pines. To my left, I see the Pacific Towers: eight fifty-five story glass obelisks stretching into the sky, all connected by a public park up top, six hundred feet in the air. A marvel of modern engineering, only paralleled by a few buildings in Shanghai. The year is 2030. I’m fortunate to rent a one-bedroom in the Pacific Towers for $2700 a month. I live on the fourteenth floor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ten Reasons for Tech Optimism in 2021</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/optimism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ten Reasons for Tech Optimism in 2021" /><published>2020-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/optimism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/optimism.html">&lt;p&gt;I have written &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/10/24/future.html&quot;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt;
about losing my teenage optimism for technology,
and how we struggle to have bold dreams for the future.
Many people have articulated theses of this type, most famously
Peter Thiel in claiming that we’ve seen great innovation in the world of bits,
but not of atoms. However, change is in the air. I believe we are approaching an inflection point
of technological change and ambition.
In a twist of irony, COVID has done a great deal to push this along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before 2020, we were stuck in what I call the &lt;em&gt;eternal 90s&lt;/em&gt;.
With the Soviet Union defeated, the United States had no focal
objective: no great enemy to defeat, no great frontier to explore.
For almost thirty years, the same set of Bill Clinton-era trends compounded on
themselves: liberalization, globalization, and growth of the internet.
It’s been a good thirty years of steady marginal progress:
reliable growth in GDP, better medicine, higher quality of food, and so on, like clockwork.
Unfortunately, marginal change is not &lt;em&gt;inspirational&lt;/em&gt;.
It has been a long time since technology has captured the hearts and minds of
a generation like the space race did in the 1960s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter 2020. Between COVID and Trump,
the trends of the eternal 90s have ruptured somewhat.
Technological penetration has leapt forward by years.
The year 2021, and the thoughts prevalent in it, will be different from 2019,
much more so than for almost any other one-year gap in recent history.
There are several important components in this shift:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Cheap Capital&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to COVID, the American fiscal response has been aggressive.
With around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2020/04/15/coronavirus-economy-6-trillion/&quot;&gt;6 trillion dollars&lt;/a&gt;
of stimulus, capital is cheap and will be for a long time.
This is subtle, but of dominant importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. The Best Ever Funding Environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With trillions of stimulus dollars in the markets, the zero-interest-rate
search for yield of the late 2010s is more desperate than ever before.
There are more dollars in venture than there are ideas.
If there has ever been a time in which it is feasible to raise gargantuan
rounds to pursue real-world moonshots, this is it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. The Great Unbundling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many institutions exist
as a consequence of returns to scale.
While technology has slowly eroded some of their necessity,
this has greatly accelerated under COVID.
These institutions
are now clearly struggling to deliver value, and self-sufficiency is becoming a priority again.
We are on the cusp of many traditional structures and institutions
being totally overhauled and unbundled. This is an enormously exciting opportunity
across many industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. De-Urbanization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cities were Schelling points for talent in 2019,
but no longer.
COVID has catapulted remote work tools and culture forward by years.
Previously urban professionals are
moving to smaller cities and suburbs,
and owning homes years ahead of schedule.
This has wide-ranging impacts: a class of workers is suddenly
much more financially secure, tier-2/3 cities see an influx of high-earning
professionals, tier-1 cities become cheaper,
and as geography wanes in importance, opportunity becomes more accessible to all,
even on a global scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Schooling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schooling is being rapidly unbundled at all levels.
Like de-urbanization, homeschooling was previously a small, niche trend.
Under COVID, it is a necessity.
As with remote work, the demand, culture, and tools for it have advanced by years
in a few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same has occurred for higher education. Many have written about the
out-of-control costs of college, while struggling to replace the extremely
convenient all-in-one package of academics, socializing, and professional training
that college provides. But COVID has forced the unbundling of college: now that students get to meet
none of their classmates in person and are paying $60k a year for online
lectures that they could get for free off YouTube, the simple BA credential
obviously isn’t worth it for most. As education gets unbundled, it will become radically cheaper and open,
multiplying opportunity on a global scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Digital Gold and More&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fiscal response to COVID was explicitly inflationary.
The Fed has nearly doubled the assets on its balance sheet
to prop up the markets,
and the US dollar has depreciated against other currencies.
Prudent investors are worried about potential runaway inflation,
and attention turns to Bitcoin again.
Now much more mature and validated,
it is appealing as an inflation hedge.
As its ecosystem matures more, we may see
many products on top of the base layer.
In the next decade, we might not just see programmable money, but
a groundbreaking separation of state and money. The opportunities for
(tumultuous) change and innovation in this context are endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Independent Workers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With remote work, workers become more independent.
Superstars – who bring outsize value, many times their compensation –
are realizing they can go independent with their brand. You see it in
&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/08/16/spac.html&quot;&gt;investing, writing, even porn&lt;/a&gt;. The newspapers and TV
of tomorrow will look very different from those of today.
This trend will be universal across media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. New Dreams: SpaceX and Tesla&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tesla has had a dizzying ten-fold
run in the markets this year, surpassing a $500B market cap.
By valuation, the markets
think that TSLA will not obsolete &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; incumbent car companies, but &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt;
of them.
I believe that part of why $TSLA has appreciated so greatly
is that in this time of desperation,
Elon Musk delivers a vision people can believe in.
People are watching
rocket launches again, and this time they’re reusable rockets out of Musk’s
private enterprise.
He is innovating in the world of atoms, not of bits,
and that’s relatable and inspiring in a way that no software entrepreneur
before him ever was.
Tesla is barely even working on truly self-driving cars, and somehow Musk
has sold a &lt;em&gt;vision&lt;/em&gt; of autonomous vehicles that Waymo hasn’t.
People are dreaming of going to space again. Musk is inspiring a generation
of budding entrepreneurs to build things that are grand and ambitious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. New Worlds: AR/VR&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AR and VR technologies had their moment of hype in the mid-2010s, but
didn’t catch on in the mainstream.
However, a little like Bitcoin, the technology and infrastructure
has been steadily improving in the background. It’s becoming very good,
and soon it’ll be ready for primetime.
Video games and movies are going to get hit by the colossal force
of a new, more immersive medium with enormous room for experimentation.
Even mundane things like exercise and videocalls will get turned on their heads.
This will be the biggest leap in the &lt;em&gt;medium&lt;/em&gt; of computing since the smartphone
in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Digital Health&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six years ago, only medical patients had real-time feeds of their vital signs.
Thanks to Apple Watches, tens of millions of consumers now have a
continuous ECG and blood oxygen monitor.
Thousands of hobbyists wear glucose monitors.
Innovations in chips (M1) and wireless (5G)
dramatically improve the computing and streaming capacity for detailed vital sign data,
and the benefits will compound.
Over the decade, I expect us to get fitness-grade health data streams for most major vital signs,
and that analysis of this data at scale will enable early detection
of both common and grave medical conditions like heart attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what’s happening? Well, capital is cheaper than ever. It’s an amazing time
to be an entrepreneur with bold, ambitious ideas. The success of Elon Musk
is inspiring a generation to be exactly that. And where are these entrepreneurs to start?
Well, digital health and AR/VR are ripening to change people’s lives massively at scale.
We might see the separation between state and money. And if that’s not enough,
most of our traditional institutions and structures, like cities, schools, and
employment are getting unbundled as we speak, democratizing access to opportunity.
Roll up your sleeves,
pick whatever target you want, it’s a good time to build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Addendum: Empty Spaces&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this doesn’t fit strictly into the realm of technological innovation,
there’s work to be done reimagining the city, too.
Under COVID, cities have lost not just residents, but also businesses.
With retail having jumped online, and many restaurants now operating
as delivery-only cloud kitchens, there’s a big question as to what happens
with vacant prime real estate.
Are bars and clothing shops really the best we can do?
The destruction that has happened here has created an opening for experimentation
and new establishments that offer novel in-person experiences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have written previously about losing my teenage optimism for technology, and how we struggle to have bold dreams for the future. Many people have articulated theses of this type, most famously Peter Thiel in claiming that we’ve seen great innovation in the world of bits, but not of atoms. However, change is in the air. I believe we are approaching an inflection point of technological change and ambition. In a twist of irony, COVID has done a great deal to push this along.</summary></entry></feed>